<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-04T10:22:06-05:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ed Burns Blog</title><subtitle>Ed Burns blogs here, mostly about Java and software, but sometimes about other random things.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ed’s JavaLand 2022 Session Picks (Updated)</title><link href="/blog/2022/02/15/javaland-2022-picks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ed’s JavaLand 2022 Session Picks (Updated)" /><published>2022-02-15T18:25:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T18:25:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2022/02/15/javaland-2022-picks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022/02/15/javaland-2022-picks.html">&lt;p&gt;Cross posted at &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/edburns00/eds-javaland-2022-session-picks-updated-2ghj&quot;&gt;dev.to&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021/05/19/build-picks.html&quot;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; “session picks” post I lamented, “Ever since the end of in-person events, I have not bothered to do my traditional session picks posts”.  Well, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://javaland.eu&quot;&gt;JavaLand 2022&lt;/a&gt; fast approaching, the time has come to resume the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All times in local timezone in JavaLand.  See &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.javaland.eu/de/programm/&quot;&gt;the program&lt;/a&gt; for more details on each session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;monday-14-march-2022&quot;&gt;Monday, 14 March 2022&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1700---1900-dambali-matamba---pattern-matching-mit-java&quot;&gt;17:00 - 19:00 Dambali (Matamba) - Pattern matching mit Java&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before JavaLand is usually reserved for JavaLand kids activities, but with Coronavirus I have not heard about any such plans.  What I do see on the schedule is one talk from German Java conference veteran &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sippsack&quot;&gt;Falk Sippach&lt;/a&gt; and newcomer &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MBoegie&quot;&gt;Merlin Bögershausen&lt;/a&gt; about pattern matching in Java.  Nope, it’s not regular expressions they’re talking about.  They are talking about language level features such as pattern matching in switch statements, records, and arrays, as described in this authoritative blog post from &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.oracle.com/javamagazine/post/java-project-amber-lambda-loom-panama-valhalla&quot;&gt;Andrew Binstock&lt;/a&gt;.  The talk is in German, but well worth a look.  It’s also the only scheduled talk on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tuesday-15-march-2022&quot;&gt;Tuesday, 15 March 2022&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;0830---0910-schauspielhaus---unittesting-für-jakarta-ee---das-vernachlässigte-wesen&quot;&gt;08:30 - 09:10 Schauspielhaus - Unittesting für Jakarta EE - das vernachlässigte Wesen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years of working mainly with the arrangement of boxes on architecture diagrams, and the JSON it takes to connect those boxes, I look forward to looking deep inside a single box at the humble Unit Test. Join &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/guhilling/&quot;&gt;Gunnar Hilling&lt;/a&gt; for this Jakarta EE focused look at this neglected discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also close out my conference picks with a talk about assertions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;0930---1000---silverado---begrüßung&quot;&gt;09:30 - 10:00 - Silverado - Begrüßung&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been to every JavaLand ever, and I can attest that Fried’s energetic greetings are not to be missed. I am sure it will be especially emotional after we’ve all been through two years of pandemic hardship. If you are interested in my take on being thankful to be at a conference after two years of pandemic hardship, check out &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021/11/22/workshoptage-keynote-summary-document.html&quot;&gt;this previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1000---1040---silverado---common-misunderstandings-in-software-architecture&quot;&gt;10:00 - 10:40 - Silverado - Common Misunderstandings in Software Architecture&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am unfamiliar with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Cairolali&quot;&gt;Dr. Carola Lilienthal&lt;/a&gt;, but her book “Sustainable Software Architecture” looks excellent. This talk is likely a distillation of the lessons in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1100---1040---schauspielhaus---quarkus-a-bliss-for-developers&quot;&gt;11:00 - 10:40 - Schauspielhaus - Quarkus: a Bliss for Developers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Soto Bueno is delivering a talk on Red Hat’s flagship, post-monolith,
cloud-native, enterprise Java developer runtime. I’m confident it will
be true to the legacy of excellent talks from the legendary Burr
Sutter.  Even though this talk competes with Ivar Grimstad’s Jakarta
EE 10 talk, I prioritize this one because I see Quarkus as delivery
vehicle for some Jakarta EE specs.  Look at it this way: EE10 is the
future, and some of the EE10 specs will eventually show up in Quarkus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1200---1240---wintergarden---low-cost-cloud-native-open-standard-java-on-azure-kubernetes-service&quot;&gt;12:00 - 12:40 - Wintergarden - Low Cost, Cloud Native, Open Standard Java on Azure Kubernetes Service&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My biased opinion recommends my own session.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/emilyfhjiang&quot;&gt;Emily Jiang&lt;/a&gt; and will observe that customers have made it clear: they want Kubernetes, but they want it easy and affordable. It is possible to address these two competing concerns by using open source runtimes on commodity hardware. This lecture shows how to use the EPLv1 licensed Open Liberty runtime on vanilla Azure Kubernetes Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I wasn’t giving this talk, I would attend &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/johanjanssen42&quot;&gt;Johan Janssen’s&lt;/a&gt;
“Why and How to Upgrade to Java 17” in Silverado.  I find an in-person conference is really great for these “one stop shop” sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1300---1340---silverado---the-project-that-changed-my-mind-on-java-modules&quot;&gt;13:00 - 13:40 - Silverado - The Project that Changed my Mind on Java Modules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Java modules is the feature that should have been in JDK 1.0, but for
many extremely valid reasons did not show up until eleven years
later. Most of the trouble people have had using Java modules in
practice can be traced to necessary decisions projects have had to
make in the absence of such a core feature in the JDK.  The problem of
modularity is fundamental to computer science, and the Java module
system is one answer to that problem for the Java platform.  The
abstract for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JaapCoomans&quot;&gt;Jaap Coomans’s&lt;/a&gt; talk
states, “That’s when the box of Pandora really opened up.” Yep, that
is the most common experience of people trying to use Java modules in
practice. I am very curious to see Jaap’s answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1400---1440---silverado---debugging-distributed-systems&quot;&gt;14:00 - 14:40 - Silverado - Debugging Distributed Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This topic is solid gold.  In my lexicon “debugging” is the same thing
as “deeply understanding”. If you can’t debug a system, you can’t
claim to deeply understand it.  I expect Java Champion &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bjschrijver&quot;&gt;Bert Jan
Schrijver&lt;/a&gt; will leave you with
actionable lessons on this essential skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1500---1540---rotunde---jvm-ergonomics-and-the-container-deep-dive&quot;&gt;15:00 - 15:40 - Rotunde - JVM Ergonomics and the Container: Deep Dive&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that popped into my mind when reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Tommy1199&quot;&gt;Sascha Selzer’s&lt;/a&gt; abstract for “JVM Ergonomics and the Container: Deep Dive” was Martin Thompson’s 2017 JavaLand Keynote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.javaland.eu/de/home/news/details/?tx_news_pi1%5Bnews%5D=1327&amp;amp;tx_news_pi1%5Bcontroller%5D=News&amp;amp;tx_news_pi1%5Baction%5D=detail&amp;amp;cHash=bb7d83b09cba83204cb0c902d1700990&quot;&gt;Mechanical Sympathy&lt;/a&gt;.  Martin’s concept is all about understanding the relationship between the hardware and the software running on top of it.  Given the complete centrality of containerized workloads to our current practice, this talk seems essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1600---1640---rotunde---observing-cloud-native-java-apps-using-opentelemetry-on-aws-gcp-and-azure&quot;&gt;16:00 - 16:40 - Rotunde - Observing Cloud Native Java Apps Using OpenTelemetry on AWS, GCP and Azure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sticking with the operations angle, this talk covers OpenTelemetry.  I’d say that OpenTelemetry will do for observability what the Servlet API did for CGI-BIN: make it standard for all Java apps.  Check this talk by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.xing.com/profile/Bernhard_Lubomski/cv&quot;&gt;Bernhard Lubomski&lt;/a&gt; out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1700---1740---wintergarten---openid-connect-support-in-jakarta-ee-10&quot;&gt;17:00 - 17:40 - Wintergarten - OpenId Connect Support in Jakarta EE 10&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rdebusscher&quot;&gt;Rudy De Bunsscher&lt;/a&gt; is a driving
force behind Payara and also an active Jakarta EE contributor. This
talk demonstrates the continued vitality of Jakarta EE by showing how
the OpenId Connect standard is supported in Jakarta EE 10.  From a
historical perspective, the Security API, introduced by David Blevins
in Jakarta EE 8, is a great foundation for OpenId Connect.  I am curious to see if Spring adopts the Security spec or continues in their
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZAJMBFq85s&quot;&gt;go your own way&lt;/a&gt;
approach when it comes to the “invent vs adopt” decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1800---1840---silverado---how-to-survive-a-live-coding-session&quot;&gt;18:00 - 18:40 - Silverado - How to Survive a Live Coding Session&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have observed the world-master of live coding, Dr. Venkat
Subramaniam, and wondered, “how does he do it?” This meta-session
about live coding sessions from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rucek&quot;&gt;Jacek
Kunicki&lt;/a&gt; offers, “tips and tricks [to] help
you feel more comfortable and prepared for (almost)
everything. Real-life horror stories included!”  Sounds great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1900---1940---quantum-12---die-neue-gesprächskultur-ganz-wie-in-panama&quot;&gt;19:00 - 19:40 - Quantum 1+2 - Die neue Gesprächskultur: ganz wie in Panama&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad to see my JSF expert group old colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/378749161&quot;&gt;Bernd Müller&lt;/a&gt; is still doing new and exciting different things in the Java world.  This particular topic of native-Java interaction (but not the GraalVM kind) is close to my heart, having worked with JNI over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www-archive.mozilla.org/oji/&quot;&gt;20 years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wednesday-16-march-2022&quot;&gt;Wednesday, 16 March 2022&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;0900---0940---wintergarden---java-at-microsoft---behind-the-scenes&quot;&gt;09:00 - 09:40 - Wintergarden - Java at Microsoft - Behind the scenes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first published this post, I had recommended Fabian’s talk
titled “State of the Java Metrics Libraries” in Rotunde.  I still want
to see this talk, but I must recommend you attend my colleagues
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/karianna&quot;&gt;Martijn Verburg&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gdams&quot;&gt;George
Adams’s&lt;/a&gt; talk about the latest entrant in
the OpenJDK ecosystem, Microsoft. You can read more about it in this
blog post announcing &lt;a href=&quot;https://devblogs.microsoft.com/java/microsoft-deepens-its-investments-in-java/&quot;&gt;Microsoft joining the JCP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1000---1040---wintergarten---increase-your-productivity-with-intellij&quot;&gt;10:00 - 10:40 - Wintergarten - Increase Your Productivity with IntelliJ&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own interviews with &lt;a href=&quot;https://ridingthecrest.com/&quot;&gt;Rockstar Programmers&lt;/a&gt; support the observation that mastery of tools is the single most important skill in the Rockstar programmer’s toolbox. This session from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BoukeNijhuis&quot;&gt;Bouke Nijhuis&lt;/a&gt;, gives you tips for mastery of the most masterful Java IDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1100---1140---wintergarten---from-zero-to-spring-boot-hero-with-github-codespaces&quot;&gt;11:00 - 11:40 - Wintergarten - From Zero to Spring Boot Hero with GitHub Codespaces&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you heard of GitHub codespaces? Well, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sKriemhild&quot;&gt;Sandra Ahlgrimm&lt;/a&gt; is a past master of this transformative developer technology.  She joins forces with &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/martinlippert&quot;&gt;Martin Lippert&lt;/a&gt; to show how to become super productive with CodeSpaces and Spring Boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1200---1240---stocks---der-application-server-ist-tot----es-lebe-jakarta-ee&quot;&gt;12:00 - 12:40 - Stock’s - Der Application Server ist tot (?) - es lebe Jakarta EE!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main job at Microsoft is to ensure Java EE application server
workloads have a great home on Azure.  I have seen irrefutable Azure
revenue numbers that prove the Java EE app server is far from dead.
I’m looking forward to an outside perspective from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dirkweil&quot;&gt;Dirk Weil&lt;/a&gt; on this same question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1300---1340---wintergarten---die-all-stars-der-software-bugs--und-was-wir-von-ihnen-lernen-können&quot;&gt;13:00 - 13:40 - Wintergarten - Die All-Stars der Software-Bugs – und was wir von ihnen lernen können&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen many different anthropomorphisms for software bugs, but “all star team” is a new one. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/perdian_de&quot;&gt;Christian Seifert&lt;/a&gt; brings this entertaining perspective on a fact of life for practicing developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1400---1440---schauspielhaus---feminism-for-geeks--a-gentle-introduction&quot;&gt;14:00 - 14:40 - Schauspielhaus - Feminism for Geeks – A Gentle Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vehemently challenge anyone who asserts that being “woke” or
“anti-fascist” is a bad thing.  The same thing goes for anyone who
feels that masculinity is somehow under attack. It’s not, and if you
believe it is, you believe so in spite of reams of empirical evidence.
I applaud the conference committee for accepting this talk from Wenny
Susanto-Berky and urge you not to miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1500---1540---silverado---hilfe-ich-will-meinen-monolithen-zurück&quot;&gt;15:00 - 15:40 - Silverado - Hilfe, ich will meinen Monolithen zurück!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are, roughly seven years since Sam Newman’s seminal book
“Building Microservices” and I’m starting to see talks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mobilelarson&quot;&gt;Lars Röwekamp’s&lt;/a&gt; “Help, I want my
monolith back”.  This view is not mere contrarianism. There are
definitely aspects of the monolith that should be preserved, even in a
microservices based architecture.  I’m sure Lars will break it down
for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1600---1640---schauspielhaus---der-java-werkzeugkasten--die-praktischen-kommandozeilentools-des-jdk&quot;&gt;16:00 - 16:40 - Schauspielhaus - Der Java-Werkzeugkasten – Die praktischen Kommandozeilentools des JDK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us have been installing JDKs on machines for years and years, but how many know about all the command line tools that get installed in that package? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mesirii&quot;&gt;Michael Hunger&lt;/a&gt; shows you how to get more from what you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1700---1740---quantum-34---im-dutzend-billiger-kanns-eine-assertion-mehr-sein-mit-assertj-zum-testerfolg&quot;&gt;17:00 - 17:40 - Quantum 3+4 - Im Dutzend billiger. Kann’s eine Assertion mehr sein? Mit AssertJ zum Testerfolg&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a whole track on testing at JavaLand, but this is only the second testing talk I’ve selected. I assure you, this is not because testing is unimportant. Rather, my role as Principal Architect at Microsoft has me working at a higher level of abstraction.  However, I am fascinated by the journey of the humble assertion over time.  The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; keyword was added to Java in 2002, but since then the entire practice of CI/CD has evolved.  This talk from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bikratz&quot;&gt;Birgit Kratz&lt;/a&gt; shows how the concept of assertions is compatible with our contemporary highly-automated development practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thursday-17-march-2022&quot;&gt;Thursday, 17 March 2022&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;0900---1700----bambuti-matamba---modern-jakarta-ee-and-microprofile-on-azure-open-liberty-jboss-eap-and-weblogic&quot;&gt;09:00 - 17:00 -  Bambuti (Matamba) - Modern Jakarta EE and Microprofile on Azure: Open Liberty, JBoss EAP, and WebLogic&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just going to recommend my own workshop with Sandra Ahlgrimm.
Here’s the snappy abstract I wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You may have heard of the saying, “software is eating the
world”. You may have heard of the concept of “digital
transformation”.  You may be, or know, someone who must implement
both of these things by moving an existing system to a public cloud.
Talk about a full stack job! Join Java veteran Ed Burns and Senior
Developor Advocate Sandra Ahlgrimm for an educational and
informative deep dive into how to build for Microsoft Azure. This
workshop will teach Azure concepts by the example of how to easily
stand up an Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS) and run a Java EE
application inside of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Participants will explore Oracle WebLogic Server, IBM Open Liberty
and JBoss EAP as the Java EE runtimes.  We will run the first two of
these Java EE environments on AKS and the third on Azure App
Service. As we go along, we will look under the hood at the
Microsoft, Oracle IBM and Red Hat technologies that enable it all to
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cross posted at dev.to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Innovation, Gratitude, Compassion and the Cloud - Workshop-Tage Keynote Summary Document</title><link href="/blog/2021/11/22/workshoptage-keynote-summary-document.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Innovation, Gratitude, Compassion and the Cloud - Workshop-Tage Keynote Summary Document" /><published>2021-11-22T08:40:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-22T08:40:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2021/11/22/workshoptage-keynote-summary-document</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2021/11/22/workshoptage-keynote-summary-document.html">&lt;p&gt;This document captures the essence of my keynote talk, “Innovation,
Gratitude, Compassion and the Cloud”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20211119-keynote-summary-03.jfif&quot; alt=&quot;Layers upon layers of software&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every one of us hearing this speech is fortunate enough to work in the
IT industry and can improve the quality of our individual and group
innovations by being thankful for prior innovations and aware of the
tradeoffs that made them succeed over time.  Let’s go through each
section of the speech and see how I expanded on that theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introspection&quot;&gt;Introspection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I set the message: “take some time to think about how we got to
where we are and be thankful for it, and find a way to give back”.  I
used a Global -&amp;gt; Local progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thankful to be here, especially in the face of COVID-19.  Yes, I
want to say the usual, and appropriate, thanks to Marcus and the team,
and I’m honored to help celebrate 30 years of Workshoptage.  Let’s
take a moment to recognize some big things that had to happen to bring
us to this point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;mRNA vaccines: an idea more than 30 years in the making. If you are
suspicious about how such a big idea can be developed so quickly,
rest assured it hasn’t been developed quickly.  The mRNA vaccine
technique started being worked on in earnest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uab.edu/news/youcanuse/item/12059-covid-19-mrna-vaccines-how-could-anything-developed-this-quickly-be-safe&quot;&gt;in the late 1990s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Moderna was not the only one working on an mRNA approach to
 vaccines. BioNTech is a German company established to work on
 immunotherapies in 2008 by a Turkish couple, who immigrated to
 Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;On top of this, insights from the fight against flu and HIV were
 crucial creating an effective vaccine for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It is also important to recognize the brave human volunteers who
 accepted the call when governments took the &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.northeastern.edu/2020/10/23/are-covid-19-vaccine-trials-ethical/&quot;&gt;unprecedented action&lt;/a&gt; of
 relaxing the pace at which human trials &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/health-56097088&quot;&gt;can take place&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Functioning government based on expertise: The indisputable fact
 that viruses do not respect national borders demonstrated the
 importance of nation-states having functional government based on
 expertise, rather than just political expedience. In addition to
 providing fiscal and legal accelerators for vaccine development and
 distribution, governments also took historically unprecedented
 fiscal stimulus actions.  I argued that these were and are helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Businesses adapting to life with COVID-19: In-person conferences are
 business-travel.  International conferences interact with all
 sectors of the travel industry, all of whom have had major
 adjustments due to COVID-19.  For example, consider the airline I
 always fly to visit Europe:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;“Lufthansa’s €9bn ($9.8bn) bail-out allows it to buy 80 new fuel-efficient planes, but it took more money than it needed to preserve its position as a global airline.”&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/leaders/2020/08/01/airlines-have-a-chance-to-emerge-from-the-crisis-leaner-and-greener&quot;&gt;The Economist 2021-08-01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commemoration is also a kind of thankfulness.  Let us remember those
 who died due to COVID-19, even as we are fortunate to be here at
 this event.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;“The standard method of tracking changes in total mortality is “excess deaths”. This number is the gap between how many people died in a given region during a given time period, regardless of cause, and how many deaths would have been expected if a particular circumstance (such as a natural disaster or disease outbreak) had not occurred. Although the official number of deaths caused by covid-19 is now 4.5m, our single best estimate is that the actual toll is 15.2m people. We find that there is a 95% chance that the true value lies between 9.3m and 18.1m additional deaths.”&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/graphic-detail/coronavirus-excess-deaths-estimates&quot;&gt;The Economist 2021-10-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reflection&quot;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle section, I looked at a few technology domains that
enable today’s public cloud and asked about the tradeoffs that were
consciously made by the stewards of that domain to bring the
technology to its present state.  Here are some points that guide the
examination of each domain and its tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Making the technology gain popularity, but often at the expense of
correctness and quality&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider technologies that solve the harder problems, problems that
most users don’t have or don’t know they have. The complexity
required to solve these harder problems often limits reach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simpler technologies usually win, even if they don’t solve the
harder problems.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But after they win, is too late to revise the technology to fix the
harder problems.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Security&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vulnerability to ransomeware&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Spam&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Phishing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I mention my former colleague at Sun Microsystems Dick Gabriel,
and his brief essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dreamsongs.com/WorseIsBetter.html&quot;&gt;Worse is Better&lt;/a&gt;.
Very interestingly, he mentions the legendary Jamie Zawinski, whom I have always 
esteemed but never managed to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My premise for the middle section is that the technologies that enable
the cloud were built and are continually developed using “Worse is
Better”, but we insiders have a responsibility to question that way
and try to at least understand the tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;networking&quot;&gt;Networking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The packet switched networking underpins the entire Internet and all
public clouds was a radical idea when it first emerged.  You must
remember that the telephone industry came from telegrams, then
switchboards for voice, but all of it was connection oriented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of breaking a message up into little chunks and then putting
them back together when all of them arrive was a radical idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Networks, and the companies that ran them, were accustomed to
connection-oriented designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practical capitalism, the kind one which one can build a stable
career, tends to have a problem with radical ideas: They would rather
not be disrupted by them.  Even so, the benefits of packet switched
networking, in terms of cost, resiliency, and flexibility could not be
denied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Networking is where the idea of interoperability is essential. For
that you need standards.  This gives me an opportunity to riff on the
heroes of standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Working on standards bodies is thankless work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Company shareholders want to maximize their investment. Sharing is
anathema to maximizing profit.  Standards are formalized sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Individuals that work for corporations, but which support standards,
often have to fight to prove the business case for standards.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because networking is so fundamental to the cloud, many of the terms
from networking have seeped into general IT usage, such as “control
plane” “Day minus one, day zero, day one, day two, day N operations”,
“North-south” “East-west” on diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended the section with a survey of WAN, LAN, and Consumer services,
showing the winners and losers in each section, and also having an
opportunity to drop some fun old names that no-one hears about any
more.  BITNet, DECnet, Toekn Ring, Minitel and Prodigy for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some assorted links of interest for this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://networkencyclopedia.com/networking-history-1970/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.wired.com/2012/09/what-do-the-h-bomb-and-the-internet-have-in-common-paul-baran/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://spectrum.ieee.org/osi-the-internet-that-wasnt#toggle-gdpr&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://kb.iu.edu/d/aaso&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://bit.net/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;information-representation&quot;&gt;Information representation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section I talked about how information is represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as with the networking world, there was a lot of debate about how
responsibilities should be broken down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier attempts were informed by our existing thinking of information
being in centralized libraries that are indexed and connected.  This
lead to the creation of distributed index technologies such as Archie
and Gopher. Each node was responsible for indexing the information it
hosted, and sharing the ability to search that index with other nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Tim Berners Lee comes along and says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YAGNI (you ain’t gonna need it), just give me two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ability to fetch a text file from one computer to another
without authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;HTTP GET. The whole method, noun, verb, thing came later.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some way to look through that text file to find other text files.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centralized indexing and imparting semantics to larger collections of
text files is outside the scope of his problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With centralized indexing, Each server had to know about the others.
When you say YAGNI to this idea, lots of magic happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This turned out to be really popular. It lowered the barriers to
entry, and also discarded a lot of the semantic richness of the other
systems.  In the end mass market wins.  Worse is better, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, notice that since the early Web deprioritized the semantic
richness of centralized indexing in favor of ease of authoring and
hosting, there have been numerous efforts to put it back.  Remember
“the semantic web”?  Technorati tags?  One could argue that Google
Page Rank, &lt;strong&gt;utm&lt;/strong&gt; tags, and SEO is a way to associate semantic
richness with web pages, but it does so in a completely propietary
way, optimized more for revenue creation than user value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;much-older-historical-aside-minitel&quot;&gt;Much older historical aside: Minitel&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;https://www.computerhistory.org/timeline/networking-the-web/#169ebbe2ad45559efbc6eb35720e1b49&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 1981, France Telecom offers free Minitel terminals to every phone subscriber, launching the first mass “Web.” Minitel will have tens of millions of users by 1990 and online services such as newspapers, train schedules, tax filing, and erotic classified ads as well as email and chat. The ‘80s Minitel boom heavily foreshadows the dot-com boom. But the business model is different. Customers pay by the minute for access to Minitel services (sites), charged on their phone bills; France Telecom keeps about a third and passes on the rest to the service provider. As in the later Web, Minitel service providers run their own servers. But they also pay France Telecom a fee to connect to its network. Despite major efforts in the US, Canada, and Europe, similar videotex systems will fizzle outside France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minitel and other systems needed to have some kind of system to author
content on the system.  Such systems had many of the attributes of
early HTML, but were propietary and did not benefit from economic
network effects for tools and talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monetization&quot;&gt;Monetization&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section I recounted my early direct experiences with the web
and two important developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the invention of the &amp;lt;IMG&amp;gt; tag: NCSA Mosaic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the invention of CGI-BIN.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20211119-keynote-summary-05.png&quot; alt=&quot;Layers upon layers of software&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two inventions, combined with the ease of authoring for
cross-device reach, even in the early web, attracted the attention of
venture capital. When VC gets involved, the pressure to follow “Worse
is Better” becomes even stronger.  The growth boom of the early Web
spilled over to other technologies as well.  Consider UNIX SMTP based
email.  The protocols that enabled UNIX email to grow and become
widespread did not have any strong concept of aggregated
authentication. The absence of such capability haunts us to this day,
and has created the SPAM and phishing industries.  Perhaps if more
time had been invested making email more authenticated and secure when
email was new, we would not have had as many hacks as we have that
started with phishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cloud-economics-forces-on-computing-hardware&quot;&gt;Cloud economics forces on computing hardware.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time at Sun Microsystems coincided with the introduction of
“Utility Computing”, in 2004. This was an idea before its time, and
also at the wrong home. As I explore in the next section, cloud scale
can only be possible with commodity everything, and Sun was a boutique
hardware company.  The early efforts at cloud were also stymied by the
lack of a concept of containers, though Solaris did have Zones. Docker
itself started in a similar way, with LXC, but now using
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;libcontainer&lt;/code&gt;.  Happily, the best parts of Solaris are now in
GNU/Linux, such as ZFS and DTrace (shout out to Brian Cantrill).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these economic forces, we can now have an enormously powerful and
encompassing IT estate managed by a single pane of glass, as shown in
this prophetic video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/wal5pt2bgqj6is2/eb-719-blade-runner-zoom-in-finished.mp4?raw=1&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;commoditization-of-all-aspects-of-it-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Commoditization of all aspects of IT infrastructure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the forces building in the preceding sections created the
conditions for the public clouds to emerge. The commoditization of
these aspects, are particularly important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Networking (software defined and otherwise)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compute&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Persistent storage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Platform services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also observed that the ability for new innovations to build on (with
gratitude) old ones has accelerated.  Consider the anology of
archeology. New cities are built on top of old ones, that’s why
archeologists always have to dig to find the old stuff.  We do the
same thing with the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the layer upon layer of software alone that now exists to run
your Java servlet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20211119-keynote-summary-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Layers upon layers of software&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example, the design of HTTP/2. It borrows ideas from the
session, transport and network layers of the OSI protocol stack, but
is itself an application layer protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20211119-keynote-summary-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;HTTP/2 takes a cue from OSI&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I pause to ask the audience to take some time to look
into the history of the technologies you are using now? What are the
ideas on which it is built? What ideas did your current thing reject
as YAGNI?  Was there any part of that rejected idea that you wish had
not been rejected?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;projection&quot;&gt;Projection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I closed the keynote with a look forward, taking Philip Armour’s five
item list of knowledge representation media as a jumping off point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DNA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardware design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Books/Photos/Videos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I asked what’s next after software?  Perhaps it is just more
software, but this time software that explains itself.  Indeed, this
is at the heart of &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/an-overview-of-model-explainability-in-modern-machine-learning-fc0f22c8c29a&quot;&gt;machine learning model
explainability&lt;/a&gt;. For
more on this topic see &lt;a href=&quot;https://christophm.github.io/interpretable-ml-book/&quot;&gt;Interpretable Machine
Learning&lt;/a&gt; by
Christoph Molnar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I ask the audience a final question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is Worse is Better driving the development of today’s world changing technologies, such as AI and nano technology, as it did for the Web, Email, and Social networks?
If you were in the position to make a Worse is better choice, which would you choose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This document captures the essence of my keynote talk, “Innovation, Gratitude, Compassion and the Cloud”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keynote Summary Documents: Is Paul Hughes right?</title><link href="/blog/2021/11/19/keynote-summary-documents.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keynote Summary Documents: Is Paul Hughes right?" /><published>2021-11-19T17:45:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-19T17:45:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2021/11/19/keynote-summary-documents</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2021/11/19/keynote-summary-documents.html">&lt;p&gt;I was blessed with the opportunity to take full advantage of the brief
window of COVID-19 pandemic relaxation in early September 2021 and
accepted the opportunity to &lt;a href=&quot;https://workshoptage.ch/jubilaeumsfeier&quot;&gt;deliver the
keynote&lt;/a&gt; at the 30th
Anniversary of Workshop-Tage in Zürich, Switzerland.  I decided to
follow the advice of this guy, Paul Hughes.  He advises: After a
Keynote Speech: Avoid this Common Mistake: &lt;a href=&quot;https://paulhugheslive.com/after-a-keynote-speech-avoid-this-common-mistake/&quot;&gt;Do not share
slides&lt;/a&gt;.
Mr. Hughes’s blog post is targeted at the party hiring the keynote
speaker, but with the keynote speaker themselves as a secondary
target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life being what it is, I’m still working on the summary document,
three months later, but have the second draft up at &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/edburns/cc938e58a4d42edcccb2061be071a916&quot;&gt;my
gist&lt;/a&gt;.
I intend to post the actual summary document as my next post here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was blessed with the opportunity to take full advantage of the brief window of COVID-19 pandemic relaxation in early September 2021 and accepted the opportunity to deliver the keynote at the 30th Anniversary of Workshop-Tage in Zürich, Switzerland. I decided to follow the advice of this guy, Paul Hughes. He advises: After a Keynote Speech: Avoid this Common Mistake: Do not share slides. Mr. Hughes’s blog post is targeted at the party hiring the keynote speaker, but with the keynote speaker themselves as a secondary target.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ed’s Microsoft Build May 2021 Session Picks</title><link href="/blog/2021/05/19/build-picks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ed’s Microsoft Build May 2021 Session Picks" /><published>2021-05-19T18:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-19T18:30:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2021/05/19/build-picks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2021/05/19/build-picks.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross posted at &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/edburns00/ed-s-microsoft-build-may-2021-session-picks-2l9e&quot;&gt;dev.to&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the end of in-person events I have not bothered to do my traditional “Ed’s session picks” posts, as I have so often in the past.  (These posts are a ride through memory lane: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2008/04/25/javaone-2008-picks.html&quot;&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2011/06/14/jazoon-2011-picks.html&quot;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2011/09/28/updated-20110930-1357-ed-burns-javaone-2011-session-picks.html&quot;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/02/18/eds-devnexus-2014-picks.html&quot;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/03/03/eds-javaland-2014-picks.html&quot;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/01/15/javaland-2015-conference-picks.html&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/02/21/devnexus-2017-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/02/27/javaland-2017-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/03/20/devoxx-us-2017-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/04/19/goto-chicago-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/03/11/javaland-2019-picks.html&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/08/26/oracle-code-one-2019-picks.html&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/11/20/jvm-con-picks.html&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt; ).  Now that Microsoft is focusing so heavily on making Java run great on Azure, it’s time to survey what Build 2021 has to offer Java developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traditional audience for Microsoft Build is less technical and
more business focused than the audience for the conferences I usually
attend.  But at this point in my career, I’m ok with that.  I am aware
that success with Java on Azure means influencing that audience.  So
I’m very excited to highlight these exciting Java related sessions at
Microsoft Build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: if you go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions&quot;&gt;Session scheduler&lt;/a&gt; and enter “java not javascript” you will see the Java related sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tuesday-25-may-2021&quot;&gt;Tuesday, 25 May 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;0500-edt-java-champions-talk-java-at-microsoft-interstitial-programming&quot;&gt;05:00 EDT Java Champions talk Java at Microsoft: Interstitial Programming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/juliendubois&quot;&gt;Julien Dubois&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JonathanGiles&quot;&gt;Jonathan Giles&lt;/a&gt; and I for a sevin minute
interstitial programming segment talking about high velocity cloud
native Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gFRbTWS32EA&quot;&gt;Watch on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1800-edt-kroger-joins-customer-tech-talks-to-discuss-how-they-are-using-java-on-azure-to-manage-stock-levels-across-their-stores&quot;&gt;18:00 EDT Kroger joins Customer Tech Talks to discuss how they are using Java on Azure to manage stock levels across their stores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success at Microsoft is all about impact.  How much impact does your
work have?  How does it achieve our vision of empowering every person
and every organization on the planet to achieve more?  This 30 minute
customer success focused session shows the impact Java has at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kroger&quot;&gt;Kroger&lt;/a&gt;, one of
the leading grocery retailers in the US.  They also own &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Fred_Meyer&quot;&gt;Fred Meyer&lt;/a&gt;. My colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/asirselvasingh&quot;&gt;Asir Selvasingh&lt;/a&gt; is instrumental in the Java work done with Kroger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/db6c0213-d07f-4ee1-8d5c-26154d7632b6?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wednesday-26-may-2021&quot;&gt;Wednesday, 26 May 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1800-edt-ask-the-java-at-microsoft-experts&quot;&gt;18:00 EDT Ask the Java at Microsoft Experts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reza_rahman&quot;&gt;Reza Rahman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/brunoborges&quot;&gt;Bruno Borges&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/karianna&quot;&gt;Martijn Verburg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/asirselvasingh&quot;&gt;Asir Selvasingh&lt;/a&gt; and I are
in the virtual booth and are excited to take your questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/aded32d6-b9e3-486c-a208-9ebcece1fbdd?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AIc6rdEe3Ys&quot;&gt;Watch on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thursday-26-may-2021&quot;&gt;Thursday, 26 May 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1000-edt-ask-the-experts-whats-new-for-developers-for-building-dual-screen-apps-for-the-surface-duo&quot;&gt;10:00 EDT Ask the Experts: What’s new for Developers for building Dual Screen Apps for the Surface Duo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the Nintendo DS (dual screen)?  The Surface Duo also has two screens, but it’s a Microsoft device and it runs Android.  That means, you can code for it using Java or Kotlin.  This one sounds really fun.  I look forward to seeing what &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gmerin&quot;&gt;Guy Merin&lt;/a&gt; has to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/19b093c6-6718-4114-87f0-861baafefa65?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-demand-sessions&quot;&gt;On Demand Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accelerating-enterprise-java-workloads-on-azure&quot;&gt;Accelerating enterprise Java workloads on Azure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where we get to show off all the things we are doing with Java EE related technologies on Azure.  It’s presented by my colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reza_rahman&quot;&gt;Reza Rahman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/2ce6782a-a7e4-4bcf-b4b6-1c9fd5d3e58a?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-linux-web-apps-easily-and-securely-on-azure-app-service&quot;&gt;Run Linux web apps easily and securely on Azure App Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Azure App Service and Azure Kubernetes Service are the two workhorse
services of Azure compute.  This talk is about the former, which
provides a much easier to understand model of the cloud to users than
what is offered by AKS.  App Service offers a wide variety of
pre-configured solution stacks on Java, .NET Core, Python, and Node,
including Tomcat and Java EE JBoss EAP.  I’m not sure how much Java
will be covered, but App Service definitely supports Java vere well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presented by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AzureWeekly/status/1322878013739065346&quot;&gt;Stefan Schackow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/77d6c20f-6b37-4643-9e31-6bcd6da4dad0?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cross posted at dev.to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blurring parts of the screen in OBS Studio, other tips</title><link href="/blog/2021/04/02/obs-blur.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blurring parts of the screen in OBS Studio, other tips" /><published>2021-04-02T16:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T16:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2021/04/02/obs-blur</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2021/04/02/obs-blur.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog posts captures some learning I did about OBS recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently invested a little time in learning the basics of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/obsproject/obs-studio&quot;&gt;OBS Studio&lt;/a&gt;.  OBS is one of
those programs that seems enormously powerful, has a vast user base,
and a correspondingly vast amount of content about it on YouTube.
There is so much content about OBS it’s hard to tell what’s good.
Thankfully, I stumbled upon 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ySENWFIkL7c&quot;&gt;this 27 minute tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
from Kevin Stratvert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to Mr. Stratvert’s tutorial, there are some other
essential tips I want to capture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blurring-during-recording&quot;&gt;Blurring during recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5zM3xvkb8dY&quot;&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt;, from a much
more gamer-focused perspective, did give a practical tip for how
selectively blur arbitrary portions of the screen.  I’ll outline the
process next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a new &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt; source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arrange it above your “main” &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt; source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a &lt;strong&gt;Scaling/Aspect Ratio&lt;/strong&gt; filter to it.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scale Filtering&lt;/strong&gt; Point.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolution&lt;/strong&gt; 640x360&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Drag the red grabber handles so that the new &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt;
source completely covers the “main” display capture source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE IS THE IMPORTANT STEP&lt;/strong&gt;: Hold down the alt key and re-size
the grabbers to cover the area you want to blur.  &lt;strong&gt;It is very
important you don’t move the region by dragging it.&lt;/strong&gt; Use the
alt-resize technique to effectively move the blur zone.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This works because of the low resolution you set.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repeat this process for whatever other parts of the screen you want
to blur.  Note that you can blur/un-blur easily with the “eye” icon
for htat &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt; source in the &lt;strong&gt;Sources&lt;/strong&gt; screen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bluring-after-recording&quot;&gt;Bluring after recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found I missed some things on my first recording and needed to do
additional blurring.  No problem, add a &lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt; source and select
the file from the first recording.  You can then play the first recording
into another recording and add more blurring as desired. I found this
reminded me of some of the performance aspect of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sqz5YaHx26g&quot;&gt;real time analog audio mixing&lt;/a&gt; because I had to take cues from the media source for when to blur/un-blur certain parts of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, when you add &lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt; source, by default you cannot hear the
audio. Turn it on with these steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Audio Mixer&lt;/strong&gt; panel, in the row for &lt;strong&gt;Media Source&lt;/strong&gt; select the cog icon and select &lt;strong&gt;Advanced Audio Properties&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the row for &lt;strong&gt;Media Source&lt;/strong&gt;, in the column for &lt;strong&gt;Audio Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;, ensure &lt;strong&gt;Monitor and Output&lt;/strong&gt; is selected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;removing-click-sounds-from-your-mic-while-recording&quot;&gt;Removing click sounds from your mic while recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add these filters to your &lt;strong&gt;Mic/Aux&lt;/strong&gt; source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noise Suppression&lt;/strong&gt;: RNNoise&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noise Gate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Close Threshold: -54.00 dB&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Open Threshold: -39.00 dB&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Remainder at defaults.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog posts captures some learning I did about OBS recently.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">File Explorer and WSL2 PWD</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/30/wslpwd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="File Explorer and WSL2 PWD" /><published>2020-10-30T13:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-30T13:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/30/wslpwd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/30/wslpwd.html">&lt;p&gt;I had long been used to doing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;open .&lt;/code&gt; on macOS to get finder window
open on the current directory in the shell.  I wanted something similar
under WSL2, but this is the best I could come up with.  It copies the
current working directory to the clipboard such that you can press
“ctrl-l crtl-v ret” in the File Explorer and get the same effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function &lt;/span&gt;wslpwd&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; //wsl&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$/&lt;/span&gt;Ubuntu&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$PWD&lt;/span&gt; | &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;sed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'s:/:\\:g'&lt;/span&gt; | pbcopy
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assumptions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pbcopy is installed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WSL distro name is Ubuntu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It prepends the special &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;//wsl$/Ubuntu&lt;/code&gt; string to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$PWD&lt;/code&gt;, then uses &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt;
to transform the forward slashes to backslashes, then uses &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pbcopy&lt;/code&gt; to put
the result on the system clipboard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had long been used to doing open . on macOS to get finder window open on the current directory in the shell. I wanted something similar under WSL2, but this is the best I could come up with. It copies the current working directory to the clipboard such that you can press “ctrl-l crtl-v ret” in the File Explorer and get the same effect.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Public Key Infrastructure</title><link href="/blog/2020/08/28/public-key-infrastructure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Public Key Infrastructure" /><published>2020-08-28T15:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-28T15:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/08/28/public-key-infrastructure</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/08/28/public-key-infrastructure.html">&lt;p&gt;I needed to remind myself of how public key cryptography worked so I
looked up this excerpt I remembered writing in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Ed-Burns/e/B001ILO9Y8&quot;&gt;JSF The Complete Reference&lt;/a&gt;.  I’m saving it here for the next time I forget how this works and need to remind myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to share data securely is to encrypt it using some scheme and share the password with the party with whom you want to share the data. Of course, the matter of sharing the password securely is a problem, but let’s just say you can tell the person directly. While the shared password scheme is easy to understand and implement, it doesn’t scale to large numbers of users without compromising security. Public key cryptography, also called public key infrastructure, or PKI, solves the problem by breaking the concept of a password into two parts, a “public key” and a “private key.” The archetypal analogy to describe PKI involves two peopleAlice and Bobwho want to send messages to each other through the postal mail. In order for Alice to send a message to Bob securely, Alice asks Bob to send her his open padlock, to which only Bob has the key. Alice then puts the message in the box and locks it with Bob’s padlock, sending it in the mail. When Bob receives the box he can open the box with his key and see the message. Conversely, when Bob wants to send a message to Alice, he needs Alice’s open padlock. In PKI, the padlock is the public key, and the key for the padlock is the private key. This situation is depicted in Figure 14-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to share data with someone, you need their public key and your private key; therefore, it is desirable to distribute your public key as widely as possible. That’s where the “infrastructure” in public key infrastructure really comes in. When padlocks (public keys) are freely distributed, the problem is verifying that Alice’s padlock really belongs to Alice and not some malicious postman who opened the mail and replaced Alice’s padlock with his own, only to intercept the return package and open the box. The authenticity of a public key is determined using an “identity certificate.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200828-pki.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alice and Bob exchange a secret message&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When speaking of Internet security, an “identity certificate” is an electronic document originating from a trusted source that vouches for the authenticity of a public key. The source from which the certificate originates is known as the certificate authority (CA), and there are a handful of such bodies in business around the world today. CACert, Thawte, and VeriSign are three popular CAs. To bring the matter back to Web applications, servers and clients may possess their own public keys, and identity certificates to vouch for them, to encrypt all the traffic between client and server. Because Web applications are by nature interactive, clients must authenticate themselves to servers as well as servers to clients. This is known as two-way authentication and is the standard practice when using client certificate authentication. Once the certificates have been authenticated, the public keys are used to establish a secure transport connection, such as with the Transport Level Security (TLS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from JavaServer Faces 2.0: The Complete Reference, McGraw-Hill November 23, 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISBN 978-0071625098&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I needed to remind myself of how public key cryptography worked so I looked up this excerpt I remembered writing in JSF The Complete Reference. I’m saving it here for the next time I forget how this works and need to remind myself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WSL2 az login xdg-open and Microsoft Edge (or any other browser)</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/29/wsl2-xdg-open-edge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WSL2 az login xdg-open and Microsoft Edge (or any other browser)" /><published>2020-07-29T15:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-29T15:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/29/wsl2-xdg-open-edge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/29/wsl2-xdg-open-edge.html">&lt;p&gt;If you ever run into a problem with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az login&lt;/code&gt; opening a Windows browser
to complete the login, this blog post may help.  I ran into this today.
When I did &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az logout&lt;/code&gt; followed by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az login&lt;/code&gt; I saw the following, and
the login did not complete succesfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: firefox: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: iceweasel: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: seamonkey: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: mozilla: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: epiphany: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: konqueror: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: chromium: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: chromium-browser: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: google-chrome: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: www-browser: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: links2: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: elinks: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: links: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: lynx: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: w3m: not found
xdg-open: no method available for opening 'https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/authorize?response_type=code&amp;amp;client_id=04b07795-8ddb-461a-bbee-02f9e1bf7b46&amp;amp;redirect_uri=http://localhost:8400&amp;amp;state=jq29agg65cx8xmh3axhv&amp;amp;resource=https://management.core.windows.net/&amp;amp;prompt=select_account'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;¯\_(ツ)_/¯
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After poking around a bit, I arrived at the following solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-make-an-executable-script-in-my-bin-directory-that-runs-the-browser-on-the-windows-side&quot;&gt;1. Make an executable script in my bin directory that runs the browser on the windows side&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See step 5 in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/blog/2019/08/14/emacs-edge-dev.html&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;.
Modify the script to reference your preferred browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-create-an-edgedesktop-file-in-the-correct-place&quot;&gt;2. Create an edge.desktop file in the correct place&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it so this file exists: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/.local/share/applications/edge.desktop&lt;/code&gt;
and has the following content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Desktop Entry]
Encoding=UTF-8
Version=1.0
Type=Application
NoDisplay=true
Exec=/home/edburns/bin/runedge.sh %u
Name=Edge
Comment=Custom definition for Edge Beta
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to modify the value of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Exec&lt;/code&gt; line accordingly.  Also,
if you are using a different browser, you’ll need to change the name of
the file to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;whaterYourBrowser.desktop&lt;/code&gt;.  Close the file when done editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-use-xdg-settings-to-set-the-default-web-browser&quot;&gt;3. Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xdg-settings&lt;/code&gt; to set the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;default-web-browser&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have created &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;edge.desktop&lt;/code&gt; in the correct place, you can
tell &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xdg-settings&lt;/code&gt; that it is the default browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xdg-settings set default-web-browser edge.desktop
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I ran this, it took a while, and I observed it added this
line to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;edge.desktop&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;MimeType=x-scheme-handler/unknown;x-scheme-handler/about;x-scheme-handler/https;x-scheme-handler/http;text/html;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can verify the setting with the following command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xdg-settings get default-web-browser
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-az-login-should-pop-up-the-browser&quot;&gt;4. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az login&lt;/code&gt; should pop up the browser.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;az logout
az login
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you ever run into a problem with az login opening a Windows browser to complete the login, this blog post may help. I ran into this today. When I did az logout followed by az login I saw the following, and the login did not complete succesfully.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter to the Editor: Economist 2020-07-11: Leader: The New Ideology of Race</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/12/economist-race-leader-letter-to-editor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter to the Editor: Economist 2020-07-11: Leader: The New Ideology of Race" /><published>2020-07-12T12:50:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-12T12:50:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/12/economist-race-leader-letter-to-editor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/12/economist-race-leader-letter-to-editor.html">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your leader “&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/20200711-economist-leader-new-ideology-of-race.pdf&quot;&gt;The New Ideology of Race&lt;/a&gt;” asserts, “Liberalism thrives on a marketplace of ideas…[and] uses facts and evidence, tested in debate, to help the weak take on the strong.”  Unfortunately, the corresponding new ideology of the American right has subverted liberalism, successfully equating it with ill-defined labels such as Antifa, and completely destroying the very concept of “facts and evidence”.  As for “debate”, that requires good faith, and the American right has defined good faith as weakness.  The proponents of the “New Ideology of Race” understand this reality.  To slow the slide toward irrelevance, “Liberalism” must understand it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Burns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altamonte Springs, FL USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Access WSL2 .vhdx on External Drive Within a Windows 10 System Image</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/07/wsl2-external-vhdx.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Access WSL2 .vhdx on External Drive Within a Windows 10 System Image" /><published>2020-07-07T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-07T08:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/07/wsl2-external-vhdx</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/07/wsl2-external-vhdx.html">&lt;p&gt;This post documents how to hack a Windows registry entry to gain access
to the contents of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://aka.ms/install-wsl&quot;&gt;WSL2&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt; volume
which resides within a Windows 10 System Image on an external disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scenario&quot;&gt;Scenario&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone should have a backup strategy that works for them in terms of
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hassle factor&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;capability&lt;/code&gt;: your strategy should have &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;no more hassle&lt;/code&gt;
than you are willing to put up with to give you a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;daily backup
capability&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On macOS, I use the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://bombich.com/&quot;&gt;Carbon Copy
Cloner&lt;/a&gt;.  On Windows 10 I use the built-in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.howtogeek.com/howto/4241/how-to-create-a-system-image-in-windows-7/&quot;&gt;Create
a system
image&lt;/a&gt;.
In both cases, I store the backup on an external drive.  Yesterday, due
to a stupid git rebase user error, I lost some commits on a repo that was
stored within my WSL2 Ubuntu machine.  “No worries,” I thought.  “I’ll
just grab the commits from my backup”.  I followed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.logicbig.com/how-to/windows/mount-windows-10-backup.html&quot;&gt;these
steps&lt;/a&gt;
to mount the System Image as a local drive and navigate to the
file…“oh wait.  The file is within the WSL image. [:sad trombone:]”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With help from WSL2 Twitter celebrity &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/craigaloewen&quot;&gt;Craig
Loewen&lt;/a&gt; I used this process to get my
lost commits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t already have WSL2, you should totally get it.  Get started at 
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aka.ms/install-wsl&quot;&gt;https://aka.ms/install-wsl&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;.  I was a Mac
user from 2007 until I joined Microsoft in June 2019.  If not for WLS2,
I’d still be a Mac user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-access-wsl2-vhdx-on-external-drive-within-a-windows-10-system-image&quot;&gt;How to Access WSL2 .vhdx on External Drive Within a Windows 10 System Image&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will edit the Windows registry to point a new Debian WSL2
distribution to the .vhdx file on the external drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-the-fully-qualified-path-to-the-vhdx-file&quot;&gt;Get the fully qualified path to the .vhdx file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount the System Image that contains the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt; file and capture its
fully qualified path.  In my case this is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;K:\Users\edburns\AppData\Local\Packages\CanonicalGroupLimited.UbuntuonWindows_79rhkp1fndgsc\LocalState
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;create-a-fresh-wsl2-debian-distribution-so-you-can-edit-its-windows-registry-entry-without-fear-of-damaging-anything&quot;&gt;Create a fresh WSL2 Debian distribution so you can edit its Windows Registry entry without fear of damaging anything&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make it so when you do &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wsl -l -v&lt;/code&gt; in Windows PowerShell you do
&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; see a distribution named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Debian&lt;/code&gt;.  If you do see one, figure
out how to save it aside.  We want to install a fresh Debian
distribution.  If you already have one, you’ll need to move it aside
so you don’t damage it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install a fresh Debian (RIP Ian Murdock) distribution from the
Windows store.  Create a userid when asked.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exit the Debian and shut down WSL2 with the command &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wsl --shutdown&lt;/code&gt;
in PowerShell.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;edit-the-windows-registry-entry-for-the-vhdx-file-of-the-fresh-debian-distribution&quot;&gt;Edit the Windows Registry entry for the .vhdx file of the fresh Debian distribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the secret sauce!  I use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;regedt32&lt;/code&gt;, but you can use any other
registry editor.  In your registry editor, navigate to this entry and
expand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Computer\HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Lxss&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This image shows what I see under the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lxss&lt;/code&gt; entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200707-wsl2-registry.png&quot; alt=&quot;Entries within Lxss&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carefully select each entry until you find the one whose
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DistributionName&lt;/code&gt; sub-entry is exactly &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Debian&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;BasePath&lt;/code&gt; sub-entry and Modify its value.  Set the value to
be exactly the fully qualified path to your external &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt; file, not
including the filename or trailing slash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exit the Windows Registry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-the-debian-image-and-get-your-files&quot;&gt;Run the “Debian” image and get your files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Windows PowerShell, run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wsl -d Debian&lt;/code&gt;.  This should boot up the
WSL2 into the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt;, allowing you to get the missing files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;PRO TIP!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The super handy &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\wsl$\&amp;lt;distroname&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; usage in Windows File Explorer
should work also.  In my case I was able to get the files by visiting
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\wsl$\Debian\home\edburns\workareas&lt;/code&gt; in Windows Explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/craigaloewen&quot;&gt;Craig Loewen&lt;/a&gt; for
this tip.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post documents how to hack a Windows registry entry to gain access to the contents of a WSL2 .vhdx volume which resides within a Windows 10 System Image on an external disk.</summary></entry></feed>