<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/blog/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-02-16T08:42:28-05:00</updated><id>/blog//</id><title type="html">Ed Burns Blog</title><subtitle>Ed Burns blogs here, mostly about Java and software, but sometimes about other random things.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Webinar Notes: Typesafe William Hill Omnia Patrick Di Loreto Blog</title><link href="/blog/2015/07/01/webinar-notes-typesafe-william-hill-omnia-patrick-di-loreto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Webinar Notes: Typesafe William Hill Omnia Patrick Di Loreto Blog" /><published>2015-07-01T08:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-07-01T08:28:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2015/07/01/webinar-notes-typesafe-william-hill-omnia-patrick-di-loreto</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/07/01/webinar-notes-typesafe-william-hill-omnia-patrick-di-loreto.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Webinar Notes: Typesafe William Hill Omnia Patrick Di Loreto&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My friend &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheOTown&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Oliver White&lt;/a&gt; is doing his usual bang-up job in his new gig at &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/typesafe&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;TypeSafe&lt;/a&gt;. One aspect is the humble webinar. Here are my notes for one that caught my eye, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.typesafe.com/blog/using-spark-kafka-cassandra-and-akka-on-mesos-for-real-time-personalization&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Using Spark, Kafka, Cassandra and Akka on Mesos for Real-Time Personalization&lt;/a&gt;. This is a very dense but well delivered presentation by &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/patricknoir&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Patrick Di Loreto&lt;/a&gt; who helped develop a new platform for his employer, the online gambling service, William Hill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Morally,
 I am sensitive to the real damage done to real lives and families that 
is caused by gambling, so I will include a link to an organization that 
offers help: &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.calpg.org/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;1-800-GAMBLER&lt;/a&gt;.
 That said, this is just another instance of the ancient tradition of 
technology development being driven by something that traditionally is 
seen as vice. (For a humorous, NSFW and prophetic Onion article, search 
google for “theonion internet andreessen viewing device”. I’m old enough
 to have first read that on an actual physical newspaper!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, on
 to the raw notes. YMMV of course, but if nothing else this will help 
you overcome the annoying problem of the slide advancing not being 
synched to the audio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt; Context: presentation by Patrick Di Loreto (@patricknoir) R&amp;amp;D Engineering lead for William Hill online betting. The presenation was done for Typesafe as a Webinar on 14 June 2015. They have a new betting platform they call Omnia. - Need to handle massive amount of data - Based on Lambda Architecture from Nathan Marz &amp;lt;http://lambda-architecture.net/&amp;gt;. - Omnia is a platform that includes four different components * Chronos - Data Source * Fates - Batch Layer * NeoCortex - Speed layer * Hermes - Serving layer 03:47 definition of Lambda Architecture “All the data must come from a unique place (data source) They separate access to the data source into two different modes based on timeliness requirements. NeoCortex (Speed Layer) is to access the data in real time, but without some consistency and correctness guarantees. Optimized for speed. It has only recent data. Fates (Batch Layer) is to access the data not in real time, but with more (complete?) consistency. 05:00 Reactive Manifesto slide 06:15 importance of elasticty for them 06:47 Chronos Data Source: “It’s nothing else than a container for active streams” “Chronos is a sort of middleware. It can talk to the outside world and bring the data into their system.” Organize the data into a stream of observable events, called “incidents”. Can have different viewpoints for different concerns * Internal (stuff they need to implement the system itself) * Product centric (which of the WH products such as “sports” “tweets” “news”. * External (“social media sharing”) * Customer centric 10:12 Chronos streams connect to the external system and bring it into Chronos Adapter: Understand all the possible protocols that other systems implement. Connect to the other system. Converter: Transform the incoming data into their internal format Persistence Manager: Make the converted data durable. 11:22 Chronos clustering Benefits from the Akka Framework. Distributes the streams across the cluster. When failover happens, stream connection to outside source is migrated to another node via Akka. Keeps referential transparency. Each stream is an Actor which “supervises” its children: adapter, converter, persistence manager. 12:41 Supervising (Slides diverged from audio) (Slide 12) Supervision is key to allowing “error kernel pattern”. &amp;lt;http://danielwestheide.com/blog/2013/03/20/the-neophytes-guide-to-scala-part-15-dealing-with-failure-in-actor-systems.html&amp;gt; Basically, it is just a simple guideline you should always try to follow, stating that if an actor carries important internal state, then it should delegate dangerous tasks to child actors, so as to prevent the state-carrying actor from crashing. Sometimes, it may make sense to spawn a new child actor for each such task, but that&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">Webinar Notes: Typesafe William Hill Omnia Patrick Di LoretoMy friend Oliver White is doing his usual bang-up job in his new gig at TypeSafe. One aspect is the humble webinar. Here are my notes for one that caught my eye, Using Spark, Kafka, Cassandra and Akka on Mesos for Real-Time Personalization. This is a very dense but well delivered presentation by Patrick Di Loreto who helped develop a new platform for his employer, the online gambling service, William Hill.Morally,
 I am sensitive to the real damage done to real lives and families that 
is caused by gambling, so I will include a link to an organization that 
offers help: 1-800-GAMBLER.
 That said, this is just another instance of the ancient tradition of 
technology development being driven by something that traditionally is 
seen as vice. (For a humorous, NSFW and prophetic Onion article, search 
google for “theonion internet andreessen viewing device”. I’m old enough
 to have first read that on an actual physical newspaper!)Now, on
 to the raw notes. YMMV of course, but if nothing else this will help 
you overcome the annoying problem of the slide advancing not being 
synched to the audio. Context: presentation by Patrick Di Loreto (@patricknoir) R&amp;amp;D Engineering lead for William Hill online betting. The presenation was done for Typesafe as a Webinar on 14 June 2015. They have a new betting platform they call Omnia. - Need to handle massive amount of data - Based on Lambda Architecture from Nathan Marz &amp;lt;http://lambda-architecture.net/&amp;gt;. - Omnia is a platform that includes four different components * Chronos - Data Source * Fates - Batch Layer * NeoCortex - Speed layer * Hermes - Serving layer 03:47 definition of Lambda Architecture “All the data must come from a unique place (data source) They separate access to the data source into two different modes based on timeliness requirements. NeoCortex (Speed Layer) is to access the data in real time, but without some consistency and correctness guarantees. Optimized for speed. It has only recent data. Fates (Batch Layer) is to access the data not in real time, but with more (complete?) consistency. 05:00 Reactive Manifesto slide 06:15 importance of elasticty for them 06:47 Chronos Data Source: “It’s nothing else than a container for active streams” “Chronos is a sort of middleware. It can talk to the outside world and bring the data into their system.” Organize the data into a stream of observable events, called “incidents”. Can have different viewpoints for different concerns * Internal (stuff they need to implement the system itself) * Product centric (which of the WH products such as “sports” “tweets” “news”. * External (“social media sharing”) * Customer centric 10:12 Chronos streams connect to the external system and bring it into Chronos Adapter: Understand all the possible protocols that other systems implement. Connect to the other system. Converter: Transform the incoming data into their internal format Persistence Manager: Make the converted data durable. 11:22 Chronos clustering Benefits from the Akka Framework. Distributes the streams across the cluster. When failover happens, stream connection to outside source is migrated to another node via Akka. Keeps referential transparency. Each stream is an Actor which “supervises” its children: adapter, converter, persistence manager. 12:41 Supervising (Slides diverged from audio) (Slide 12) Supervision is key to allowing “error kernel pattern”. &amp;lt;http://danielwestheide.com/blog/2013/03/20/the-neophytes-guide-to-scala-part-15-dealing-with-failure-in-actor-systems.html&amp;gt; Basically, it is just a simple guideline you should always try to follow, stating that if an actor carries important internal state, then it should delegate dangerous tasks to child actors, so as to prevent the state-carrying actor from crashing. Sometimes, it may make sense to spawn a new child actor for each such task, but that</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GeekOut 2015 Summary Blog</title><link href="/blog/2015/06/16/geekout-2015-summary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GeekOut 2015 Summary Blog" /><published>2015-06-16T09:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-06-16T09:28:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2015/06/16/geekout-2015-summary</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/06/16/geekout-2015-summary.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h1&gt;GeekOut 2015 Summary&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;I
 last had the pleasure of visiting the lovely Baltic city of Tallinn in 
2012, when I presented JSF 2.2 and the Rockstar talk at GeekOut 2012. 
Now that I've got something new (for me anyway) to talk about I made the
 cut and was invited back to present Servlet 4.0 at &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://2015.geekout.ee/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;GeekOut 2015&lt;/a&gt;.
 Attendence was capped at 400, giving this conference a very exclusive 
feel. Indeed, 99% of those that registered for the conference actually 
did attend. This was the 5th installment of the GeekOut conference, 
hosted by &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://zeroturnaround.com/software/xrebel/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ZeroTurnaround&lt;/a&gt;.
 This was the first time the conference had two tracks, so my report 
here only covers the sessions I actually attended. All of the sessions 
were video recorded, and I expect the sessions will be made available 
soon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Day One&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Day one started with back-to-back plenary sessions offering two different perspectives on the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23java20&amp;amp;src=typd&amp;amp;customTheme=otn&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;#java20&lt;/a&gt; theme. &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/steveonjava&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Stephen Chin&lt;/a&gt;
 gave a historically rich but technically light session featuring lots 
of freshly recorded video clips with Java luminaries. Of course there 
was ample content from James Gosling, who I would like to congratulate 
for winning the 2015 &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.ieee.org/about/awards/bios/vonneumann_recipients.html#sect1&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;IEEE John von Neumann Medal&lt;/a&gt;.
 This puts James in the company of such titans as Leslie Lamport, Donald
 Knuth, Ivan Sutherland, and Fred Brooks. I was happy to see that 
Stephen dove deeper and offered the perspectives of John Rose and 
Georges Saab on more fundamental aspects of the history of Java. &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mjpt777&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Martin Thompson&lt;/a&gt;
 followed Steven with a very complimentary session. The session was so 
complimentary I'd almost say they coordinated. Martin's session gave his
 personal perspective on Java over the years, with some very interesting
 stories from his work on making Java perform well. I liked his 
perspective on the causes and challenges of bloat in a long-lived 
software ecosystem. Another very interesting perspective was the extent 
to which high frequency trading drives advances in performance (in Java 
and in the entire industry). Martin's talk piqued my desire for a 
#java20 talk about all the companies that have been spawned directly or 
indirectly by the Java ecosystem. I'm thinking Interface21, Tangosol, 
JBoss, NoFluffJustStuff, ZeroTurnaround, Atlassian, Parleys and there 
are many others. Hey, I'm pretty sure there's an interesting talk in 
there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the plenary sessions, we broke out into the
 two tracks, starting with my session on Servlet 4.0 and a session on 
Cassandra. My session was quite well attended, and it went pretty 
smoothly. We'll see how the feedback shows up, however! After my 
session, I went down to see &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/myfear&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Markus Eisele&lt;/a&gt;
 talk about Apache Camel. I hadn't followed the progress in the Camel 
community and I'm happy to see it is doing well since. Also nice to see 
my old pal &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ghohpe&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Gregor Hohpe&lt;/a&gt; represented virtually, as his book is represented in spirit in Camel itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was very keen to see the Vaadin talk from &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/peter_lehto&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Peter Lehto&lt;/a&gt;.
 I had long been perplexed at Vaadin's ability to decouple itself from 
GWT, particularly as GWT's popularity has dwindled. This talk, at last, 
promised to lay bare the secret at the heart of Vaadin: its runtime is 
dependent on GWT. I was not disappointed, but I was also very pleasantly
 surprised. Mr. Lehto directly addressed the question of the relevance 
of server side UI frameworks, including Vaadin (and JSF, though he 
didn't name it specifically) in an HTML5 JavaScript framework world. He 
did so by pointing out the importance of abstraction, which I've long 
been pointing out when presenting on JSF. In the case of Vaadin and JSF,
 their core value add is the authoring experience. With Vaadin, it's 
Java programmers who want to treat the world like Swing. With JSF it's 
&quot;page developers&quot; who want to treat the world like some form of 
VisualBasic environment. For Vaadin, its existing abstraction allows 
their underlying runtime to leverage W3C Web Components (or the polymer 
implementation of the same) for some Vaadin components while relying on 
GWT for others. Peter put a strong stake in the ground and predicted 
that W3C Web Components are the future for web development. I don't 
disagree, but JSF is well positioned to leverage W3C Web Components 
because it fits in nicely with the JSF abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Day Two&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Day two started out with &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/asz&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Attila Szegedi's&lt;/a&gt;
 highly technical Rhino talk. This was the first talk of the day, after 
the party night, so it was a little lightly attended. However, those 
that made it there were rewarded with an in-depth understanding of the 
rationale for some performance related design decisions in the 
implementation of Nashorn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 10:30 slot was another effectively plenary session, but out in the demo area. Stephen Chin's highly effective &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://nighthacking.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;NIGHTHACKING&lt;/a&gt; brand came to GeekOut with a panel discussion on the #java20 theme. The video is &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://nighthacking.com/20-years-of-java-panel/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;on the NIGHTHACKING website&lt;/a&gt;. This was a lot of fun, and I got to put my &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://news.cnet.com/Netscape-sharpens-Javagator-plans/2100-1001_3-206700.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Javagator&lt;/a&gt; old-timer test out there. I also had the pleasure of a brief chat with Stephen regarding &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://nighthacking.com/ed-burns-on-jsf-2-3-and-servlet-4-0/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSF 2.3 and Servlet 4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was really looking forward to &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/tnurkiewicz&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Tomasz Nurkiewicz's&lt;/a&gt; session about CompletableFuture, particularly because of its use in the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://openjdk.java.net/jeps/110&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Java SE9 HTTP/2 client&lt;/a&gt;.
 Thomas managed to pack a whole lot into a short, well constructed, code
 powered session. It's not easy to explain the differences between 
thenApply(), thenCombine(), thenCompose() and many other methods in the 
API, but Tomasz succeeded. He even surfaced an important naming 
inconsistency between the CompletableFuture API and the 
java.util.Optional API: thenCompose() == flatMap(). For more on this 
topic from Tomasz, check out his blog entry &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.nurkiewicz.com/2013/05/java-8-definitive-guide-to.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;The Definitive Guide to Completable Future&lt;/a&gt;.
 Personally, I think it's a bit bold to give a single blog entry such a 
lofty title, but you can't argue that it does indeed cover the topic 
very well. I meant to ask Tomasz if his code samples from the talk were 
taken from an upcoming book. Tomasz, if you happen to see this little 
blog entry, please plug the book if there is one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had high hopes for the next talk, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/gvsmirnov&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Gleb Smirnov's&lt;/a&gt;
 concurrency talk. It was probably a great talk, but sadly this is when 
my jetlag hit hard and I was struggling to keep up. I'll look for the 
video!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I took a pass for the 15:00 slot due to the afore mentioned jetlag and opted to save my energy for one final session, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/ags313&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Andrzej Grzesik's&lt;/a&gt;
 Go. I'd taken a quick look at Go before the session, so I was in a good
 position to enjoy it. This session made no excuses about having nothing
 to do with Java and instead just tried to give a quick tour of the Go 
language and programming environment, with a view towards lowering the 
barriers to entry to give it a try. Go succeeds because it rules several
 fundamental things as simply out of scope. There is no dynamic linking.
 There is no UI. There is no API to the threading model. There is no 
inheritance. I'm glad Go is out there because sometimes you don't need 
that stuff. For what it's worth, here's a nice post on Go &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://spf13.com/post/is-go-object-oriented/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;from the Docker guy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, there were some brief and tasteful closing remarks from ZeroTurnaround founders and my good friends &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ekabanov&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Jevgeni Kabanov&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/toomasr&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Toomas Römer&lt;/a&gt;. I'm glad to see these guys doing well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">GeekOut 2015 SummaryI
 last had the pleasure of visiting the lovely Baltic city of Tallinn in 
2012, when I presented JSF 2.2 and the Rockstar talk at GeekOut 2012. 
Now that I've got something new (for me anyway) to talk about I made the
 cut and was invited back to present Servlet 4.0 at GeekOut 2015.
 Attendence was capped at 400, giving this conference a very exclusive 
feel. Indeed, 99% of those that registered for the conference actually 
did attend. This was the 5th installment of the GeekOut conference, 
hosted by ZeroTurnaround.
 This was the first time the conference had two tracks, so my report 
here only covers the sessions I actually attended. All of the sessions 
were video recorded, and I expect the sessions will be made available 
soon.Day OneDay one started with back-to-back plenary sessions offering two different perspectives on the #java20 theme. Stephen Chin
 gave a historically rich but technically light session featuring lots 
of freshly recorded video clips with Java luminaries. Of course there 
was ample content from James Gosling, who I would like to congratulate 
for winning the 2015 IEEE John von Neumann Medal.
 This puts James in the company of such titans as Leslie Lamport, Donald
 Knuth, Ivan Sutherland, and Fred Brooks. I was happy to see that 
Stephen dove deeper and offered the perspectives of John Rose and 
Georges Saab on more fundamental aspects of the history of Java. Martin Thompson
 followed Steven with a very complimentary session. The session was so 
complimentary I'd almost say they coordinated. Martin's session gave his
 personal perspective on Java over the years, with some very interesting
 stories from his work on making Java perform well. I liked his 
perspective on the causes and challenges of bloat in a long-lived 
software ecosystem. Another very interesting perspective was the extent 
to which high frequency trading drives advances in performance (in Java 
and in the entire industry). Martin's talk piqued my desire for a 
#java20 talk about all the companies that have been spawned directly or 
indirectly by the Java ecosystem. I'm thinking Interface21, Tangosol, 
JBoss, NoFluffJustStuff, ZeroTurnaround, Atlassian, Parleys and there 
are many others. Hey, I'm pretty sure there's an interesting talk in 
there somewhere.After the plenary sessions, we broke out into the
 two tracks, starting with my session on Servlet 4.0 and a session on 
Cassandra. My session was quite well attended, and it went pretty 
smoothly. We'll see how the feedback shows up, however! After my 
session, I went down to see Markus Eisele
 talk about Apache Camel. I hadn't followed the progress in the Camel 
community and I'm happy to see it is doing well since. Also nice to see 
my old pal Gregor Hohpe represented virtually, as his book is represented in spirit in Camel itself.I was very keen to see the Vaadin talk from Peter Lehto.
 I had long been perplexed at Vaadin's ability to decouple itself from 
GWT, particularly as GWT's popularity has dwindled. This talk, at last, 
promised to lay bare the secret at the heart of Vaadin: its runtime is 
dependent on GWT. I was not disappointed, but I was also very pleasantly
 surprised. Mr. Lehto directly addressed the question of the relevance 
of server side UI frameworks, including Vaadin (and JSF, though he 
didn't name it specifically) in an HTML5 JavaScript framework world. He 
did so by pointing out the importance of abstraction, which I've long 
been pointing out when presenting on JSF. In the case of Vaadin and JSF,
 their core value add is the authoring experience. With Vaadin, it's 
Java programmers who want to treat the world like Swing. With JSF it's 
&quot;page developers&quot; who want to treat the world like some form of 
VisualBasic environment. For Vaadin, its existing abstraction allows 
their underlying runtime to leverage W3C Web Components (or the polymer 
implementation of the same) for some Vaadin components while relying on 
GWT for others. Peter put a strong stake in the ground and predicted 
that W3C Web Components are the future for web development. I don't 
disagree, but JSF is well positioned to leverage W3C Web Components 
because it fits in nicely with the JSF abstraction.Day TwoDay two started out with Attila Szegedi's
 highly technical Rhino talk. This was the first talk of the day, after 
the party night, so it was a little lightly attended. However, those 
that made it there were rewarded with an in-depth understanding of the 
rationale for some performance related design decisions in the 
implementation of Nashorn.The 10:30 slot was another effectively plenary session, but out in the demo area. Stephen Chin's highly effective NIGHTHACKING brand came to GeekOut with a panel discussion on the #java20 theme. The video is on the NIGHTHACKING website. This was a lot of fun, and I got to put my Javagator old-timer test out there. I also had the pleasure of a brief chat with Stephen regarding JSF 2.3 and Servlet 4.0.I was really looking forward to Tomasz Nurkiewicz's session about CompletableFuture, particularly because of its use in the Java SE9 HTTP/2 client.
 Thomas managed to pack a whole lot into a short, well constructed, code
 powered session. It's not easy to explain the differences between 
thenApply(), thenCombine(), thenCompose() and many other methods in the 
API, but Tomasz succeeded. He even surfaced an important naming 
inconsistency between the CompletableFuture API and the 
java.util.Optional API: thenCompose() == flatMap(). For more on this 
topic from Tomasz, check out his blog entry The Definitive Guide to Completable Future.
 Personally, I think it's a bit bold to give a single blog entry such a 
lofty title, but you can't argue that it does indeed cover the topic 
very well. I meant to ask Tomasz if his code samples from the talk were 
taken from an upcoming book. Tomasz, if you happen to see this little 
blog entry, please plug the book if there is one.I had high hopes for the next talk, Gleb Smirnov's
 concurrency talk. It was probably a great talk, but sadly this is when 
my jetlag hit hard and I was struggling to keep up. I'll look for the 
video!I took a pass for the 15:00 slot due to the afore mentioned jetlag and opted to save my energy for one final session, Andrzej Grzesik's
 Go. I'd taken a quick look at Go before the session, so I was in a good
 position to enjoy it. This session made no excuses about having nothing
 to do with Java and instead just tried to give a quick tour of the Go 
language and programming environment, with a view towards lowering the 
barriers to entry to give it a try. Go succeeds because it rules several
 fundamental things as simply out of scope. There is no dynamic linking.
 There is no UI. There is no API to the threading model. There is no 
inheritance. I'm glad Go is out there because sometimes you don't need 
that stuff. For what it's worth, here's a nice post on Go from the Docker guy.Finally, there were some brief and tasteful closing remarks from ZeroTurnaround founders and my good friends Jevgeni Kabanov and Toomas Römer. I'm glad to see these guys doing well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recent Ripple of JSF Extensions Blog</title><link href="/blog/2015/06/01/recent-ripple-jsf-extensions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recent Ripple of JSF Extensions Blog" /><published>2015-06-01T10:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-06-01T10:30:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2015/06/01/recent-ripple-jsf-extensions</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/06/01/recent-ripple-jsf-extensions.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Recent Ripple of JSF Extensions&lt;/h1&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;My colleague &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.java.net/blogs/mriem&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Manfred Riem&lt;/a&gt; tipped me off to a new framework built on JSF, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.butterfaces.org/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ButterFaces&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;
 This whimsical name started an amusing Twitter thread, but also, and 
much more importantly brought several other new JSF extensions to light.
 This is the sort of thing that I used to look to Kito Mann's &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.jsfcentral.com/products/frameworks/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSF Central Frameworks Page&lt;/a&gt;
 for, but it seems that needs an update.&amp;nbsp; So, in addition to 
ButterFaces, here are several other JSF extensions that are definitely 
worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.bootsfaces.net/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;BootsFaces&lt;/a&gt; focuses on Twitter Bootstrap 3 and jQuery UI.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.materialprime.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Material Prime&lt;/a&gt; is a PrimeFaces extension that lets you build web apps that conform to Google's &quot;Material&quot; design language.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.generjee.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Generjee&lt;/a&gt;
 is a Java EE application generator that outputs JSF+JavaEE 7+CDI 
code.&amp;nbsp; FWIW, I would be remiss if I didn't point out that &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://java.net/projects/javaee-spec/pages/JEE&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;there is nothing named JEE&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; So, I suggest this project rename itself to generee.&amp;nbsp; I think that's snappier anyway.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;This
 recent flurry of activity shows two things.&amp;nbsp; First, the continuing
 vitality of the JSF ecosystem.&amp;nbsp; By now I think we all know that 
the ecosystem around the technology is just as important as the 
technology itself.&amp;nbsp; It's like this.&amp;nbsp; A technology has to be 
&quot;good enough&quot; to get the job done.&amp;nbsp; That's a given.&amp;nbsp; Heck, it 
could even be excellent technology.&amp;nbsp; But without an ecosystem 
around it, even the best technologies will not survive.&amp;nbsp; Second, 
there is still interest and value in server side state UI 
frameworks.&amp;nbsp; My recent work with HTTP/2 in Servlet 4 has shown me 
that such frameworks are very well positioned to take advantage of the 
optimizations in the HTTP/2 protocol, as well as other performance 
optimizations shown in &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/igrigorik&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Ilya Grigorik's&lt;/a&gt; excellent &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1230000000545&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;High Performance Browser Networking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;So, check out these new frameworks and don't be afraid to question conventional wisdom.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">Recent Ripple of JSF Extensions&amp;nbsp; My colleague Manfred Riem tipped me off to a new framework built on JSF, ButterFaces.&amp;nbsp;
 This whimsical name started an amusing Twitter thread, but also, and 
much more importantly brought several other new JSF extensions to light.
 This is the sort of thing that I used to look to Kito Mann's JSF Central Frameworks Page
 for, but it seems that needs an update.&amp;nbsp; So, in addition to 
ButterFaces, here are several other JSF extensions that are definitely 
worth a look.&amp;nbsp; BootsFaces focuses on Twitter Bootstrap 3 and jQuery UI.&amp;nbsp; Material Prime is a PrimeFaces extension that lets you build web apps that conform to Google's &quot;Material&quot; design language.&amp;nbsp; Generjee
 is a Java EE application generator that outputs JSF+JavaEE 7+CDI 
code.&amp;nbsp; FWIW, I would be remiss if I didn't point out that there is nothing named JEE.&amp;nbsp; So, I suggest this project rename itself to generee.&amp;nbsp; I think that's snappier anyway.&amp;nbsp; This
 recent flurry of activity shows two things.&amp;nbsp; First, the continuing
 vitality of the JSF ecosystem.&amp;nbsp; By now I think we all know that 
the ecosystem around the technology is just as important as the 
technology itself.&amp;nbsp; It's like this.&amp;nbsp; A technology has to be 
&quot;good enough&quot; to get the job done.&amp;nbsp; That's a given.&amp;nbsp; Heck, it 
could even be excellent technology.&amp;nbsp; But without an ecosystem 
around it, even the best technologies will not survive.&amp;nbsp; Second, 
there is still interest and value in server side state UI 
frameworks.&amp;nbsp; My recent work with HTTP/2 in Servlet 4 has shown me 
that such frameworks are very well positioned to take advantage of the 
optimizations in the HTTP/2 protocol, as well as other performance 
optimizations shown in Ilya Grigorik's excellent High Performance Browser Networking.&amp;nbsp; So, check out these new frameworks and don't be afraid to question conventional wisdom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ConFESS 2015 Wrap Up Blog</title><link href="/blog/2015/05/18/confess-2015-wrap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ConFESS 2015 Wrap Up Blog" /><published>2015-05-18T10:02:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-05-18T10:02:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2015/05/18/confess-2015-wrap</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/05/18/confess-2015-wrap.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h1&gt;ConFESS 2015 Wrap Up&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hard on the heels of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://weblogs.java.net/blog/edburns/archive/2015/03/30/javaland-2015-wrap&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaLand&lt;/a&gt; was &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://2015.con-fess.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ConFESS&lt;/a&gt;. This was the eighth installment of the conference that started life in 2008 as &lt;a class=&quot;&quot; href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/blog/http%20]]%3E%3C%21[CDATA[%20s:/matthiaswessendorf.wordpress.com/2008/02/14/jsfdays-2008-in-vienna&quot;&gt;JSF Days&lt;/a&gt;,
 switching to the name &quot;ConFESS&quot; in 2011. The name stands for the 
&quot;Conference for Enterprise Software Solutions&quot;. Last year, ConFESS was 
held as a partnership with JavaLand in Brühl Germany. Neither party was 
satisfied with how that turned out and in 2015 ConFESS returned to its 
home in Vienna, where it will stay. It was a relatively small event, 
with just over 200 participants. It nicely filled out the venue, the C3 
event center in the 3rd district. In my opinion, its small size is a 
large asset. The ability to have the entire event schedule on two sides 
of a 4x5 inch card is very convenient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/blog/20150415-confess-2015.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;403&quot; src=&quot;20150518_files/20150415-confess-2015.html&quot; style=&quot;float: right;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;150&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My
 overall impression of the conference was very positive. There was a 
wide variety of talks from speakers I hadn't seen before on the 
conference circuit. There was a good breadth of coverage in diverse 
tracks ranging from agile/methods to Java EE to tools to client side 
technologies, and there was an excellent band on Tuesday night, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.fsgcompany.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Florian Braun and FSG Company&lt;/a&gt;. There was also a Lego Mindstorms EV3 competition that got rave reviews, but I didn't attend that portion of the event.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/blog/20150414_confess-2015.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;404&quot; src=&quot;20150518_files/20150414_confess-2015.html&quot; style=&quot;float: left;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;150&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The full set of abstracts from the conference are available at the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.regonline.com/builder/site/tab2.aspx?EventID=1619724&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;regonline site for the event&lt;/a&gt;.
 You can use that site to learn more about the sessions for which I will
 give my brief impressions in the remainder of this blog entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tuesday Keynote was from Oracle Labs's &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thomaswue&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Thomas Wuerthinger&lt;/a&gt;. Thomas presented his exciting work on the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/oracle-labs/program-languages/overview/index-2301583.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Graal VM&lt;/a&gt;. First off, I'm glad to see that Oracle has continued Sun's tradition of funding long-term research in the spirit of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_Microsystems_Laboratories&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Sun Labs&lt;/a&gt;,
 founded by computing pioneer Ivan Sutherland (yep, just checked, he 
still works for Oracle). The basic idea of Graal appears to be: take the
 abstract syntax tree concept from compiler design and make it a first 
class part of the JIT process, allowing the runtime to rewrite itself as
 the program runs to achieve greater performance without sacrificing 
agility. Cool stuff, and great for a keynote.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sticking with the JSF heritage of the conference, next up was &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cagataycivici&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Cagatay Civici's&lt;/a&gt;
 talk about PrimeFaces. Cagatay introduced the new &quot;layouts&quot; concept, 
built on JSF 2.2 Resource Library Contracts. The base offering consists 
of two new layouts, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.primefaces.org/layouts/sentinel.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Sentinel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.primefaces.org/layouts/spark.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Spark&lt;/a&gt;.
 One thing I've always liked about PrimeFaces is how they take the base 
concepts of the core JSF specification and use them to maximum effect, 
taking full advantage of new features, large and small.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diving down a level, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pbouillaud/status/588552316594302976&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Johannes Tuchscherer&lt;/a&gt;
 from CloudFoundry talked about Docker and how it relates to offerings 
from Pivotal. Johannes put the hype into perspective, showing how you 
still need other technologies to actually create value with Docker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sticking in the Pivotal realm, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/springjuergen&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Jürgen Höller&lt;/a&gt;
 gave the Spring 4.1 overview talk. It was nice to see that they were 
able to leverage Java SE 8 features while producing a binary that runs 
on Java SE 6. I was happy to have the opportunity to ask Juergen how 
pulled that trick off and the answer is basically build-time static code
 analysis. They compile with Java SE 8 with -source and -target 1.6, and
 have a build-time tool that looks for usages of Java SE 8 only idioms 
and APIs, and flags them as failures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next talk I attended was a really practical hands on session about Java Flight Recorder from &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/johanjanssen42&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Johan Janssen&lt;/a&gt;. I'm a big fan of learning to get more out of tools I already have. JFR has been a part of the JDK for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I
 was happy to see my good friend and fellow Oracle employee Mike Keith 
given the Wednesday keynote slot. Mike is a veteran of the conference 
trail, author of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Pro-JPA-Experts-Voice-Java/dp/1430249269&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Pro JPA2&lt;/a&gt;
 and former JPA spec lead. Mike was talking about an exciting new 
product from Oracle: Mobile Back End As A Service (MBaaS). In a 
nutshell, this product packages up everything enterprises need to deploy
 mobile based applications that are built on their existing 
infrastructure. Mike's slides are &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://2015.con-fess.com/TJeBJK74/ConFESS_2015_Day2_0900_R1_R2_Mike_Keith-EnterpriseMobilePlatform.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;available for download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My
 own session was up next, at which I gave a status update on JSF 2.3. 
Briefly, it's a community driven release aimed at preserving your 
existing investment in JSF. I've uploaded my slides to &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/edburns/burns-jsfconfess2015&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;slideshare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a counterpart to Johan Janssen's session yesterday I attended &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/antonarhipov&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Anton Arhipov&lt;/a&gt;'s session about ZeroTurnaround's &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://zeroturnaround.com/software/xrebel/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;XRebel&lt;/a&gt;
 product. I liked his straightforward pitch: most applications receive 
very little profiling attention, let's make a super simple product that 
lets you get the low hanging fruit with maximum performance gain. 
Indeed, the slick browser based UI is very easy to use. When asked about
 various corner cases, Anton was honest and answered the current state 
of the product is very narrowly focused on where the most value can be 
easily extracted. This focus is a key success factor for ZT, in my 
opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've always talked up the importance of maintainability, 
and sold that as a strong suit of the Java EE stack, so it was with 
great interest that I attended &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bernhard_keprt/status/588278982245818369&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Bernhard Keprt&lt;/a&gt;'s session about maintenance. One reason I like attending conferences is to remove my &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.safaribooksonline.com/library/view/secrets-of-the/9780071490832/apb.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;3rd order ignorance&lt;/a&gt; by exposing me to technologies I otherwise would not encounter. During Bernhard's talk, he introduced me to &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.versioneye.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;VersionEye&lt;/a&gt;.
 The value-add of this tool is easy to perceive: given that you have 
lots of dependencies, let's have a tool that keeps an eye on them and 
lets you know when they update.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stefan Schuster gave a session 
from his experiences in developing apps for the three big flavors of 
mobile deployment platforms: native, Apache Cordova, and mobile web app.
 I liked this session for its first-hand perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To close out my 2015 ConFESS session attendance I viewed &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/alexgoeschl&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Alex Göschl&lt;/a&gt;'s session on AngularJS. Alex shared his experiences in deployng Angular 1 for the jobs portal for conference sponsor &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://willhaben.at/jobs/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Willhaben&lt;/a&gt;.
 FWIW, I found nine job postings for JSF on the site and four for 
Angular. This was an enjoyable talk and Alex did a great job explaining 
the extremely heterogeneous set of tools and technologies used in the 
project. Prior to switching the jobs portal to Angular 1, they were 
using GWT. It was pretty much a complete rewrite. The most useful aspect
 of the talk to me was the ease with which such an apparently complex 
tool chain is now accepted and leveraged by your average front end team.
 For example, the following nine step dev time build process was rattled
 off as if it were no big deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;clean build targets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;compile less to css&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;copy vendor libraries&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;copy assets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;compile and optimize angular templates&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;compile and check typescript&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;copy to tomcat&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;inject velocity templates&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;It
 must just be my Java EE roots that makes me feel that the preceding 
list is a lot more complex than a similar build process in a Java EE 
stack. I need to spend more time getting to know the workflow in current
 front end shops. Can anyone recommend a user group or meetup in 
Orlando, FL?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the two day conference was my full day of 
workshops. I had a small but dedicated room of students and I hope they 
enjoyed the sessions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">ConFESS 2015 Wrap UpHard on the heels of JavaLand was ConFESS. This was the eighth installment of the conference that started life in 2008 as JSF Days,
 switching to the name &quot;ConFESS&quot; in 2011. The name stands for the 
&quot;Conference for Enterprise Software Solutions&quot;. Last year, ConFESS was 
held as a partnership with JavaLand in Brühl Germany. Neither party was 
satisfied with how that turned out and in 2015 ConFESS returned to its 
home in Vienna, where it will stay. It was a relatively small event, 
with just over 200 participants. It nicely filled out the venue, the C3 
event center in the 3rd district. In my opinion, its small size is a 
large asset. The ability to have the entire event schedule on two sides 
of a 4x5 inch card is very convenient.My
 overall impression of the conference was very positive. There was a 
wide variety of talks from speakers I hadn't seen before on the 
conference circuit. There was a good breadth of coverage in diverse 
tracks ranging from agile/methods to Java EE to tools to client side 
technologies, and there was an excellent band on Tuesday night, Florian Braun and FSG Company. There was also a Lego Mindstorms EV3 competition that got rave reviews, but I didn't attend that portion of the event.The full set of abstracts from the conference are available at the regonline site for the event.
 You can use that site to learn more about the sessions for which I will
 give my brief impressions in the remainder of this blog entry.TuesdayThe Tuesday Keynote was from Oracle Labs's Thomas Wuerthinger. Thomas presented his exciting work on the Graal VM. First off, I'm glad to see that Oracle has continued Sun's tradition of funding long-term research in the spirit of Sun Labs,
 founded by computing pioneer Ivan Sutherland (yep, just checked, he 
still works for Oracle). The basic idea of Graal appears to be: take the
 abstract syntax tree concept from compiler design and make it a first 
class part of the JIT process, allowing the runtime to rewrite itself as
 the program runs to achieve greater performance without sacrificing 
agility. Cool stuff, and great for a keynote.Sticking with the JSF heritage of the conference, next up was Cagatay Civici's
 talk about PrimeFaces. Cagatay introduced the new &quot;layouts&quot; concept, 
built on JSF 2.2 Resource Library Contracts. The base offering consists 
of two new layouts, Sentinel and Spark.
 One thing I've always liked about PrimeFaces is how they take the base 
concepts of the core JSF specification and use them to maximum effect, 
taking full advantage of new features, large and small.Diving down a level, Johannes Tuchscherer
 from CloudFoundry talked about Docker and how it relates to offerings 
from Pivotal. Johannes put the hype into perspective, showing how you 
still need other technologies to actually create value with Docker.Sticking in the Pivotal realm, Jürgen Höller
 gave the Spring 4.1 overview talk. It was nice to see that they were 
able to leverage Java SE 8 features while producing a binary that runs 
on Java SE 6. I was happy to have the opportunity to ask Juergen how 
pulled that trick off and the answer is basically build-time static code
 analysis. They compile with Java SE 8 with -source and -target 1.6, and
 have a build-time tool that looks for usages of Java SE 8 only idioms 
and APIs, and flags them as failures.The next talk I attended was a really practical hands on session about Java Flight Recorder from Johan Janssen. I'm a big fan of learning to get more out of tools I already have. JFR has been a part of the JDK for quite some time.WednesdayI
 was happy to see my good friend and fellow Oracle employee Mike Keith 
given the Wednesday keynote slot. Mike is a veteran of the conference 
trail, author of Pro JPA2
 and former JPA spec lead. Mike was talking about an exciting new 
product from Oracle: Mobile Back End As A Service (MBaaS). In a 
nutshell, this product packages up everything enterprises need to deploy
 mobile based applications that are built on their existing 
infrastructure. Mike's slides are available for download.My
 own session was up next, at which I gave a status update on JSF 2.3. 
Briefly, it's a community driven release aimed at preserving your 
existing investment in JSF. I've uploaded my slides to slideshare.As a counterpart to Johan Janssen's session yesterday I attended Anton Arhipov's session about ZeroTurnaround's XRebel
 product. I liked his straightforward pitch: most applications receive 
very little profiling attention, let's make a super simple product that 
lets you get the low hanging fruit with maximum performance gain. 
Indeed, the slick browser based UI is very easy to use. When asked about
 various corner cases, Anton was honest and answered the current state 
of the product is very narrowly focused on where the most value can be 
easily extracted. This focus is a key success factor for ZT, in my 
opinion.I've always talked up the importance of maintainability, 
and sold that as a strong suit of the Java EE stack, so it was with 
great interest that I attended Bernhard Keprt's session about maintenance. One reason I like attending conferences is to remove my 3rd order ignorance by exposing me to technologies I otherwise would not encounter. During Bernhard's talk, he introduced me to VersionEye.
 The value-add of this tool is easy to perceive: given that you have 
lots of dependencies, let's have a tool that keeps an eye on them and 
lets you know when they update.Stefan Schuster gave a session 
from his experiences in developing apps for the three big flavors of 
mobile deployment platforms: native, Apache Cordova, and mobile web app.
 I liked this session for its first-hand perspective.To close out my 2015 ConFESS session attendance I viewed Alex Göschl's session on AngularJS. Alex shared his experiences in deployng Angular 1 for the jobs portal for conference sponsor Willhaben.
 FWIW, I found nine job postings for JSF on the site and four for 
Angular. This was an enjoyable talk and Alex did a great job explaining 
the extremely heterogeneous set of tools and technologies used in the 
project. Prior to switching the jobs portal to Angular 1, they were 
using GWT. It was pretty much a complete rewrite. The most useful aspect
 of the talk to me was the ease with which such an apparently complex 
tool chain is now accepted and leveraged by your average front end team.
 For example, the following nine step dev time build process was rattled
 off as if it were no big deal.clean build targetscompile less to csscopy vendor librariescopy assetscompile and optimize angular templatescompile and check typescriptcopy to tomcatinject velocity templatesIt
 must just be my Java EE roots that makes me feel that the preceding 
list is a lot more complex than a similar build process in a Java EE 
stack. I need to spend more time getting to know the workflow in current
 front end shops. Can anyone recommend a user group or meetup in 
Orlando, FL?Following the two day conference was my full day of 
workshops. I had a small but dedicated room of students and I hope they 
enjoyed the sessions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JavaLand 2015 Wrap-Up Blog</title><link href="/blog/2015/03/30/javaland-2015-wrap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JavaLand 2015 Wrap-Up Blog" /><published>2015-03-30T09:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-30T09:32:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2015/03/30/javaland-2015-wrap</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/03/30/javaland-2015-wrap.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h1&gt;JavaLand 2015 Wrap Up&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;After
 months of preparation, it all came down to three days of intense 
execution, and I was just one speaker. I can only marvel at the 
logistical acumen that was on display from the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/team/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaLand&lt;/a&gt; and DOAG team. I had an action , capably coodinated by &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/personenseiten/andreas-badelt/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Andreas Badelt&lt;/a&gt;.
 Because of the high level of activity on my personal agenda, I was not 
able to attend as many sessions as I would have liked. In any case, this
 blog entry is my place to share my overall impressions of the 
conference, and of the sessions I did get a chance to attend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day One&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/blog/20150324-lagergren-keynote-hassle.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;401&quot; src=&quot;20150330_files/20150324-lagergren-keynote-hassle.html&quot; style=&quot;float: right;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;148&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Right off the bat, I want to tip my cap to &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lagergren&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Marcus Lagergren&lt;/a&gt;
 for remaining calm in the face of some AV problems. Even with all that,
 and the 45 minute session duration, Marcus managed to give a compelling
 whirlwind tour of his personal experience with Java from the beginning.
 More photos like the one on the right are available from &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hildebrandttk&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Stefan Hildebrandt&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/130465085@N06/sets/72157651139135557/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;flickr photo stream&lt;/a&gt;.
 I think there is a lot more room in the &quot;20 year's of Java meme&quot;, 
however, and I applaud Marcus for wisely not attempting to speak for all
 of it and drawing from his own experiences. That's one great thing 
about the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23java20&amp;amp;src=typd&amp;amp;customTheme=otn&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;#java20&lt;/a&gt; meme, everyone has their own story. Maybe at &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.oracle.com/javaone/call-for-proposals.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaOne 2015&lt;/a&gt; they will have some sort of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://storycorps.org/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Story Corps&lt;/a&gt;
 type thing where people can give their stories. Come to think of it, if
 someone wants to build Story Corps as a Service (SCAAS), perpahs they 
can sell it to Oracle for use at the show.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shortly after Marcus's session, I presented with my good friend &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SourceKnights&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Oliver Szymanzki&lt;/a&gt; a 45 minute capsule of our full day training session about &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/edburns/java-ee-7-from-an-html5-perspective-javaland-2015&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Java EE 7 from an HTML5 Perspective&lt;/a&gt;.
 It was tough to make a meaningful abstraction from a full day session 
to just 45 minutes, but I hope at least people could take something 
useful away from it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then came my first exposure to the EAA, which was my only chance to present JSF content here at JavaLand. I gave a &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/edburns/jsf-22-input-output-javaland-2015&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;quick presentation&lt;/a&gt;
 and had an informal meeting with several JSF EG members who were at 
JavaLand. We covered f:socket, multi-component validation, and URL 
mapping.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evening community event was really not to be missed. 
If you ever have a chance to attend JavaLand, I really recommend you 
participate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day Two&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started out the day by presenting a modified version of my &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/edburns/http2-comes-to-java-what-servlet-40-means-to-you-devnexus-2015&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;DevNexus session about Servlet 4.0 and HTTP/2&lt;/a&gt;. I basically dropped the demo and moved the Java SE 9 content to an EAA session in order to fit into the 45 minute window.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following my session I was able to enjoy &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nmcl&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Mark Little's&lt;/a&gt; keynote about Java &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.doag.org/konferenz/konferenzplaner/konferenzplaner_details.php?id=483801&amp;amp;locS=0&amp;amp;vid=491907&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Enterprise and Internet of Things&lt;/a&gt;.
 This session put out some hard-won truths of problems we have solved in
 Java as cautionary tales for newer stacks that seem intent on 
re-inventing wheels rather than standing on the shoulders of others. I 
must admit it was a feel-good session, but still realistic and largely &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drinking_the_Kool-Aid&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;kool aid free&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, I supported &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dblevins&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;David Blevins&lt;/a&gt; during his &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.doag.org/konferenz/konferenzplaner/konferenzplaner_details.php?id=483801&amp;amp;locS=0&amp;amp;vid=491386&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;session about the new Security JSR&lt;/a&gt;. This was a very informative session that got a whole lot done in only 45 minutes. I hope it encouraged some people to &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=375&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;get involved in JSR-375&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Running back to the EAA, I presented the exciting work being done by &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/OpenJDK&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Michael McMahon&lt;/a&gt;
 to bring a new Http Client to Java SE 9, including HTTP/2 support. I 
can't post the slides, but I'm sure we'll have something on this at 
JavaOne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My last engagment of the conference proper was to participate in a joint vJUG/NightHacking session regarding &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://nighthacking.com/adopt-a-jsr-nighthackingvjug-sessions/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Adopt-a-JSR&lt;/a&gt;. This was lots of fun, and I thank &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/steveonjava&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Stephen Chin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sjmaple&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Simon Maple&lt;/a&gt; for providing a vehicle for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As
 a nice wind-down from the conference, and a bit of chill before the 
training day, I was invited by DOAG boss Fried Saacke to attend the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dasniko/status/580831517418618883&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;5 year celebration dinner&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.ijug.eu/java-aktuell/das-magazin.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Java Aktuell&lt;/a&gt;
 magazine. I didn't know it at the time, but the invitation included an 
opportunity to give a short speech, in German, on the importance of JCP 
to the Java Community. I hope I didn't mangle my words too badly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/blog/20150326-tastykakes-and-usb.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;402&quot; src=&quot;20150330_files/20150326-tastykakes-and-usb.html&quot; style=&quot;float: left;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;150&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
 After being blessed with many years of German conference opportunities 
at which I invariably bring home lots of chocolate, I felt it was time 
to give the Germans a taste of American-style sweets along with their 
pre-loaded VM usb sticks. These Tasty Kakes or a specialty of my 
home-town of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.tastykake.com/history&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/a&gt;, and each attendee of the session &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/programm/vertiefe-schulungstag/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Java EE aus einer HTML5-Perspektive&lt;/a&gt; received some along with a full day of instruction and a USB stick with a VM containing the workshop materials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In summary, JavaLand has lots to recommend it. Come for the content, stay for the fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">JavaLand 2015 Wrap UpAfter
 months of preparation, it all came down to three days of intense 
execution, and I was just one speaker. I can only marvel at the 
logistical acumen that was on display from the JavaLand and DOAG team. I had an action , capably coodinated by Andreas Badelt.
 Because of the high level of activity on my personal agenda, I was not 
able to attend as many sessions as I would have liked. In any case, this
 blog entry is my place to share my overall impressions of the 
conference, and of the sessions I did get a chance to attend.Day One Right off the bat, I want to tip my cap to Marcus Lagergren
 for remaining calm in the face of some AV problems. Even with all that,
 and the 45 minute session duration, Marcus managed to give a compelling
 whirlwind tour of his personal experience with Java from the beginning.
 More photos like the one on the right are available from Stefan Hildebrandt's flickr photo stream.
 I think there is a lot more room in the &quot;20 year's of Java meme&quot;, 
however, and I applaud Marcus for wisely not attempting to speak for all
 of it and drawing from his own experiences. That's one great thing 
about the #java20 meme, everyone has their own story. Maybe at JavaOne 2015 they will have some sort of Story Corps
 type thing where people can give their stories. Come to think of it, if
 someone wants to build Story Corps as a Service (SCAAS), perpahs they 
can sell it to Oracle for use at the show.Shortly after Marcus's session, I presented with my good friend Oliver Szymanzki a 45 minute capsule of our full day training session about Java EE 7 from an HTML5 Perspective.
 It was tough to make a meaningful abstraction from a full day session 
to just 45 minutes, but I hope at least people could take something 
useful away from it.Then came my first exposure to the EAA, which was my only chance to present JSF content here at JavaLand. I gave a quick presentation
 and had an informal meeting with several JSF EG members who were at 
JavaLand. We covered f:socket, multi-component validation, and URL 
mapping.The evening community event was really not to be missed. 
If you ever have a chance to attend JavaLand, I really recommend you 
participate.Day TwoI started out the day by presenting a modified version of my DevNexus session about Servlet 4.0 and HTTP/2. I basically dropped the demo and moved the Java SE 9 content to an EAA session in order to fit into the 45 minute window.Following my session I was able to enjoy Mark Little's keynote about Java Enterprise and Internet of Things.
 This session put out some hard-won truths of problems we have solved in
 Java as cautionary tales for newer stacks that seem intent on 
re-inventing wheels rather than standing on the shoulders of others. I 
must admit it was a feel-good session, but still realistic and largely kool aid free.In the afternoon, I supported David Blevins during his session about the new Security JSR. This was a very informative session that got a whole lot done in only 45 minutes. I hope it encouraged some people to get involved in JSR-375.Running back to the EAA, I presented the exciting work being done by Michael McMahon
 to bring a new Http Client to Java SE 9, including HTTP/2 support. I 
can't post the slides, but I'm sure we'll have something on this at 
JavaOne.My last engagment of the conference proper was to participate in a joint vJUG/NightHacking session regarding Adopt-a-JSR. This was lots of fun, and I thank Stephen Chin and Simon Maple for providing a vehicle for it.As
 a nice wind-down from the conference, and a bit of chill before the 
training day, I was invited by DOAG boss Fried Saacke to attend the 5 year celebration dinner for Java Aktuell
 magazine. I didn't know it at the time, but the invitation included an 
opportunity to give a short speech, in German, on the importance of JCP 
to the Java Community. I hope I didn't mangle my words too badly.
 After being blessed with many years of German conference opportunities 
at which I invariably bring home lots of chocolate, I felt it was time 
to give the Germans a taste of American-style sweets along with their 
pre-loaded VM usb sticks. These Tasty Kakes or a specialty of my 
home-town of Philadelphia, and each attendee of the session Java EE aus einer HTML5-Perspektive received some along with a full day of instruction and a USB stick with a VM containing the workshop materials.In summary, JavaLand has lots to recommend it. Come for the content, stay for the fun.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JavaLand 2015 Early Adopter’s Area Preview Blog</title><link href="/blog/2015/02/15/javaland-2015-early-adopters-area-preview.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JavaLand 2015 Early Adopter's Area Preview Blog" /><published>2015-02-15T10:48:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-02-15T10:48:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2015/02/15/javaland-2015-early-adopters-area-preview</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/02/15/javaland-2015-early-adopters-area-preview.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h1&gt;JavaLand 2015 Early Adopter's Area&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;With only 25 business days to go until JavaLand 2015, now's a good time to share the plans for the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/index.php?id=1786&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Early Adopter's area&lt;/a&gt;
 and Hackergarten. As at many other Java community conferences, this is a
 space where anyone can visit and meet with leaders of different parts 
of the Java ecosystem to see first hand what's new in their own little 
patch of the Java world. The detail page for this space on the JavaLand 
website: &amp;lt; &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/index.php?id=1786&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.javaland.eu/index.php?id=1786&lt;/a&gt;
 &amp;gt; lists the individuals who have committed to spend some time in the
 space. I've been participating in these kinds of spaces &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://weblogs.java.net/blog/edburns/archive/2006/08/im_lucy_van_pel.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;for nearly ten years now&lt;/a&gt; and it's always very worthwhile for me to interact with the community in this way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The
 schedule of mini-presentations is still not yet finalized, but the 
detail page will have the final schedule when it is. In the meantime, I 
can share an alphabetical snapshot of the current set of individuals and
 their topics. If I have any commentary to add for each entry, I'll add 
it. As I prepared the commentary, a theme emerged. Every one of these 
individuals is passionately advocating for their ideas in the face of 
some form of challenge. I see individuals who are trying to displace an 
incumbent technology, trying to overcome some part of the community &quot;not
 getting&quot; their idea, and fighting the old bugbear of 
complexity/indifference. This passion makes it worth your time to stop 
by the early adopter's area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Alex Snaps, Peter Lawrey&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alex and Peter are talking about JCache and Data Grids&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;min-height: 8pt; padding: 0px;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Anatole Tresch&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apache Tamaya, Java Configuration, and Money and Currency&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anatole
 has been super determined to make progress on the configuration for 
Java effort. This effort started out as an Oracle-lead JSR proposal, was
 transferred to Anatole's employer, Credit Suisse, was declined for 
consideration in both EE and SE JCP executive committees, and Anatole 
finally decided to make progress as an Apache Incubator Project. I 
applaud his tenacity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Andres Almiray&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Andres is 
most famous for his involvement in the Griffon desktop application 
framework, but his passion for this space has lead him to propose &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=377&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSR-377: A Desktop Application API&lt;/a&gt;.
 Now, I've been around long enough to know that this is a difficult 
space to occupy, with several attempts at standardization having come 
and gone (see &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=295&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSR-295&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=296&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSR-296&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=143&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSR-143&lt;/a&gt;). I wish you the best of success with this one, Andres, but it's obviously a tough nut to crack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Dan Allen&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I
 know Dan from his productive involvement in JSF 2.0. These days I see 
him frequently tweeting about Asciidoctor. After having just made a &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/edburns/http2-spec/commit/08c4b1376354801f9e5abfe144b3696191b4194e&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;trivial pull request to the HTTP/2 spec&lt;/a&gt; and using &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;xml2rfc&lt;/a&gt; to do it, I can say there is room for improvement in this space, and I know that Dan can tell you all about it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Ed Burns&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'll be here talking about JSF, Servlet, and HTTP/2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Heather Vancura&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heather
 is the heart of the JCP, and therefore has her finger on the pulse of 
what is happening across the evolution of the entire Java platform.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Ivar Grimnstad&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I
 don't know Ivar, but he is on the MVC Expert Group, and is thus a great
 conduit to the development efforts of one of only two new JSRs in Java 
EE 8.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Mani Sarkar, Daniel Bryant&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've seen Mani 
at several conferences over the past couple years, and he epitomizes the
 passionate Java developer. As the late night tech conversations would 
dwindle off, he'd always be one of the last ones still talking hard core
 tech. Mani's the real deal. Mani is talking about OpenJDK, among other 
things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;Roland Huss&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Roland is talking about JMX and Java EE Management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please drop by the Early Adopter's Area to catch up with these and other Java community leaders!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">JavaLand 2015 Early Adopter's AreaWith only 25 business days to go until JavaLand 2015, now's a good time to share the plans for the Early Adopter's area
 and Hackergarten. As at many other Java community conferences, this is a
 space where anyone can visit and meet with leaders of different parts 
of the Java ecosystem to see first hand what's new in their own little 
patch of the Java world. The detail page for this space on the JavaLand 
website: &amp;lt; http://www.javaland.eu/index.php?id=1786
 &amp;gt; lists the individuals who have committed to spend some time in the
 space. I've been participating in these kinds of spaces for nearly ten years now and it's always very worthwhile for me to interact with the community in this way.The
 schedule of mini-presentations is still not yet finalized, but the 
detail page will have the final schedule when it is. In the meantime, I 
can share an alphabetical snapshot of the current set of individuals and
 their topics. If I have any commentary to add for each entry, I'll add 
it. As I prepared the commentary, a theme emerged. Every one of these 
individuals is passionately advocating for their ideas in the face of 
some form of challenge. I see individuals who are trying to displace an 
incumbent technology, trying to overcome some part of the community &quot;not
 getting&quot; their idea, and fighting the old bugbear of 
complexity/indifference. This passion makes it worth your time to stop 
by the early adopter's area.Alex Snaps, Peter LawreyAlex and Peter are talking about JCache and Data Grids&amp;nbsp;Anatole TreschApache Tamaya, Java Configuration, and Money and CurrencyAnatole
 has been super determined to make progress on the configuration for 
Java effort. This effort started out as an Oracle-lead JSR proposal, was
 transferred to Anatole's employer, Credit Suisse, was declined for 
consideration in both EE and SE JCP executive committees, and Anatole 
finally decided to make progress as an Apache Incubator Project. I 
applaud his tenacity.Andres AlmirayAndres is 
most famous for his involvement in the Griffon desktop application 
framework, but his passion for this space has lead him to propose JSR-377: A Desktop Application API.
 Now, I've been around long enough to know that this is a difficult 
space to occupy, with several attempts at standardization having come 
and gone (see JSR-295, and JSR-296, and JSR-143). I wish you the best of success with this one, Andres, but it's obviously a tough nut to crack.Dan AllenI
 know Dan from his productive involvement in JSF 2.0. These days I see 
him frequently tweeting about Asciidoctor. After having just made a trivial pull request to the HTTP/2 spec and using xml2rfc to do it, I can say there is room for improvement in this space, and I know that Dan can tell you all about it.Ed BurnsI'll be here talking about JSF, Servlet, and HTTP/2.Heather VancuraHeather
 is the heart of the JCP, and therefore has her finger on the pulse of 
what is happening across the evolution of the entire Java platform.Ivar GrimnstadI
 don't know Ivar, but he is on the MVC Expert Group, and is thus a great
 conduit to the development efforts of one of only two new JSRs in Java 
EE 8.Mani Sarkar, Daniel BryantI've seen Mani 
at several conferences over the past couple years, and he epitomizes the
 passionate Java developer. As the late night tech conversations would 
dwindle off, he'd always be one of the last ones still talking hard core
 tech. Mani's the real deal. Mani is talking about OpenJDK, among other 
things.Roland HussRoland is talking about JMX and Java EE Management.Please drop by the Early Adopter's Area to catch up with these and other Java community leaders!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JavaLand 2015 Conference Picks Blog</title><link href="/blog/2015/01/15/javaland-2015-conference-picks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JavaLand 2015 Conference Picks Blog" /><published>2015-01-15T10:12:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-01-15T10:12:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2015/01/15/javaland-2015-conference-picks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2015/01/15/javaland-2015-conference-picks.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h1&gt;JavaLand 2015 Conference Picks&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;With
 only 44 business days to go until JavaLand 2015, I’d like to share my 
conference picks. I’m including my sessions for completeness, and 
naturally I recommend you attend them, but I’ll also include an 
alternate that I’d attend ]]&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday, 24 March 2015&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;0900, Wintergarden, Welcome Keynote: 20 Years of Java&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I like to attend the plenary sessions of a conference if they are at all interesting, and Oracle Java engineer &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lagergren&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Marcus Lagergren’s&lt;/a&gt; looks great. It will be on the big stage. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.java.net/sites/default/files/big-room.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;398&quot; src=&quot;20150115_files/big-room.html&quot; style=&quot;float: right;&quot; width=&quot;100&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;This year I’m celebrating my own 20 year anniversary with Java, since &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flux.utah.edu/%7Ekwright/paper_summs/network_papers/mweb-w3c96.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;I was present&lt;/a&gt; at the German debut of Java at the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/19980214105213/http://www.igd.fhg.de/www/www95/www95.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;The Third International World-Wide Web Conference in Darmstadt, Germany&lt;/a&gt; in April 1995. I vividly remember someone (&lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/avh&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Arthur van Hoff&lt;/a&gt; I think) typing, as root &lt;code&gt;rm -rf /*&lt;/code&gt;, at the end of the demo on a Sun UNIX workstation. What flair!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;1000, Schauspielhaus, Praktisches API-Design&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dieser Vortrag wird auf Deutsch gegeben, aber trotzdem empfehle sie ich weil das Thema nebem meinem Hertz liegt. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.java.net/sites/default/files/schauspielhaus.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;399&quot; src=&quot;20150115_files/schauspielhaus.html&quot; style=&quot;float: left;&quot; width=&quot;100&quot; height=&quot;134&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Hopefully I’ll get some tips for design in JSF and Servlet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;p&gt;1200, Quantum 1, Java EE 7 from an HTML5 Perspective: WebSocket, JSON, &amp;amp; JSF&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This
 is my first session, and it is an overview of JavaEE 7 from the 
perspective of technologies useful to those developing JavaEE 7 backed 
apps with HTML5 user interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I wasn’t speaking myself, I’d attend my pal &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/monacotoni&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Anton Epple’s 1200, Quantum 2, Wie programmiert man JavaScript in Java.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1300, Schauspielhaus, The (not so) Dark Art of Performance Tuning&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My good friend &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kcpeppe&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Kirk Pepperdine&lt;/a&gt; is a global expert in this topic, and a great and entertaining speaker as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1400, Wintergarden, JBatch mit Apache BatchEE&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Batch
 is one of those unglamorous yet essential technologies, and also one 
with a very vibrant JCP community. I remember meeting &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/michaelminella&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Michael Minella&lt;/a&gt; of Spring Batch at &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://devnexus.com/s/index&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;DevNexus 2014&lt;/a&gt; and he was so excited about passing the TCK. The session speaker, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/struberg&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Mark Struberg&lt;/a&gt;, is a tech titan and one of the sharpest guys I’ve had the pleasure of working with. He’s also a great speaker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1500, Wintergarden, Where Are We At with MVC in Java EE 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I work very closely with my co-spec lead on JSF, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mnriem&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Manfred Riem&lt;/a&gt;, so I’m biased, but this session is sure to be great. MVC is one of the most talked about technologies in Java EE 8.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1600, Quantum 4, Confessions of an Automation Addict&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit of an automation addict myself, but the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.mhprofessional.com/product.php?isbn=0071804285&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;horse I picked to ride&lt;/a&gt; has fallen out of favor. Nonetheless, I still use it heavily.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1700, Schauspielhaus, Speed up Your Java by Turning it into Binary&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;John is a great speaker and industry veteran, and this talk has a provocative topic, so it is sure to be worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;min-height: 8pt; padding: 0px;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One
 unique aspect of this conference is its location: a top-tier amusmement
 park. Think of it as a smaller mashup of Disney’s Epcot and Magic 
Kingdom, with German sensibilities. After the first day of the 
conference, some of the rides will be open to conference attendees. My 
favorite was Winja’s force. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.java.net/sites/default/files/winjas-force.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;20150115_files/winjas-force.html&quot; style=&quot;float: right;&quot; width=&quot;134&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This is a relatively mellow roller coaster with a twist, literally. The car you sit in can rotate as it glides along the rails.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday, 25 March 2015&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;0900, Quantum 3, Developing Native Mobile Apps Using JavaScript&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a bit outside of my bailiwick, but my friend &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hazems&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Hazem Saleh&lt;/a&gt; is a great speaker and strong proponent of Open Source. He’s also a JSF Expert Group member.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;1000, Schauspielhaus, HTTP 2.0 Comes to Java EE&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is my second session, and I’ll explain what’s in store for Servlet 4.0, with a special view towards HTTP/2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I wasn’t speaking, I’d definitely attend &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/svenpet&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Sven Peters’s&lt;/a&gt;
 Coding Culture session in Wintergarden. First off, Atlassian makes much
 better products than GitHub. Second, Sven is an excellent speaker, and 
third the talk is likely to be keynote worthy. I’m not glad to be up 
against him in the schedule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;1100, Wintergarden, Enterprise and Internet of Things&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tuesday plenary is by &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nmcl&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Dr. Mark Little&lt;/a&gt;,
 who is doing a great job driving Java EE forward at JBoss. I normally 
don’t go in for IoT sessions, but Mark is sure to make it interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;1300, Schauspielhaus, Java EE Security: Let’s Make Something Useful&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dblevins&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;David Blevins&lt;/a&gt;
 is a strong community voice for improving Java EE, and security is one 
of the most challenging areas to improve. You can tell it’s hard just by
 how long it’s taken for the community to get up enough steam to tackle 
it in a proper JSR. Well, we have one now: &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=375&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSR-375&lt;/a&gt;, and David will tell us how we can make the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;1400, Quantum 4, Productive, Effective Development? You Weak Minded fool!&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sjmaple&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Simon Maple&lt;/a&gt; has done a great job building the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/virtualJUG&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Virtual JUG&lt;/a&gt;
 into a force for good in the Java Community. He is well positioned to 
deliver this kind of talk thanks to his role at ZeroTurnaround.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;1500, Quantum 1, Softwarequalität steigern&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;This
 appears to be a survey talk about how to effectively use some popular 
tools in practice to improve software quality. I’ve never seen &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/leichtundkross&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Andreas G¨nzel&lt;/a&gt; talk, but the topic is interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;dt&gt;1600, Quantum 4, Puppet für Entwickler&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now
 that Docker is all the rage, I’ll be interested to see what’s new with 
Puppet, or at least learn how these two popular sysadmin technologies 
relate to eachother. As with the previous talk, I’ve not seen &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ithempel&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Sebastian Hempel&lt;/a&gt; speak before this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Thursday, 26 March 2015&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://weblogs.java.net/blog/edburns/archive/2014/12/26/javaland-2015-training-day-teaser&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;in my previous entry&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SourceKnights&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Oliver Szymanski&lt;/a&gt; and I are presenting an entry in the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/programm/vertiefe-schulungstag.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;training day&lt;/a&gt;: Java EE 7 from an HTML5 Perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JavaLand
 was great fun and very professionally enriching last year. This year 
promises to be even more so. I hope to see you there!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">JavaLand 2015 Conference PicksWith
 only 44 business days to go until JavaLand 2015, I’d like to share my 
conference picks. I’m including my sessions for completeness, and 
naturally I recommend you attend them, but I’ll also include an 
alternate that I’d attend ]]&amp;gt;Tuesday, 24 March 20150900, Wintergarden, Welcome Keynote: 20 Years of JavaI like to attend the plenary sessions of a conference if they are at all interesting, and Oracle Java engineer Marcus Lagergren’s looks great. It will be on the big stage. This year I’m celebrating my own 20 year anniversary with Java, since I was present at the German debut of Java at the The Third International World-Wide Web Conference in Darmstadt, Germany in April 1995. I vividly remember someone (Arthur van Hoff I think) typing, as root rm -rf /*, at the end of the demo on a Sun UNIX workstation. What flair!1000, Schauspielhaus, Praktisches API-DesignDieser Vortrag wird auf Deutsch gegeben, aber trotzdem empfehle sie ich weil das Thema nebem meinem Hertz liegt.  Hopefully I’ll get some tips for design in JSF and Servlet.1200, Quantum 1, Java EE 7 from an HTML5 Perspective: WebSocket, JSON, &amp;amp; JSFThis
 is my first session, and it is an overview of JavaEE 7 from the 
perspective of technologies useful to those developing JavaEE 7 backed 
apps with HTML5 user interfaces.If I wasn’t speaking myself, I’d attend my pal Anton Epple’s 1200, Quantum 2, Wie programmiert man JavaScript in Java.1300, Schauspielhaus, The (not so) Dark Art of Performance TuningMy good friend Kirk Pepperdine is a global expert in this topic, and a great and entertaining speaker as well.1400, Wintergarden, JBatch mit Apache BatchEEBatch
 is one of those unglamorous yet essential technologies, and also one 
with a very vibrant JCP community. I remember meeting Michael Minella of Spring Batch at DevNexus 2014 and he was so excited about passing the TCK. The session speaker, Mark Struberg, is a tech titan and one of the sharpest guys I’ve had the pleasure of working with. He’s also a great speaker.1500, Wintergarden, Where Are We At with MVC in Java EE 8I work very closely with my co-spec lead on JSF, Manfred Riem, so I’m biased, but this session is sure to be great. MVC is one of the most talked about technologies in Java EE 8.1600, Quantum 4, Confessions of an Automation AddictI’m a bit of an automation addict myself, but the horse I picked to ride has fallen out of favor. Nonetheless, I still use it heavily.1700, Schauspielhaus, Speed up Your Java by Turning it into BinaryJohn is a great speaker and industry veteran, and this talk has a provocative topic, so it is sure to be worthwhile.&amp;nbsp;One
 unique aspect of this conference is its location: a top-tier amusmement
 park. Think of it as a smaller mashup of Disney’s Epcot and Magic 
Kingdom, with German sensibilities. After the first day of the 
conference, some of the rides will be open to conference attendees. My 
favorite was Winja’s force.  This is a relatively mellow roller coaster with a twist, literally. The car you sit in can rotate as it glides along the rails.Wednesday, 25 March 20150900, Quantum 3, Developing Native Mobile Apps Using JavaScriptThis is a bit outside of my bailiwick, but my friend Hazem Saleh is a great speaker and strong proponent of Open Source. He’s also a JSF Expert Group member.1000, Schauspielhaus, HTTP 2.0 Comes to Java EEThis is my second session, and I’ll explain what’s in store for Servlet 4.0, with a special view towards HTTP/2.If I wasn’t speaking, I’d definitely attend Sven Peters’s
 Coding Culture session in Wintergarden. First off, Atlassian makes much
 better products than GitHub. Second, Sven is an excellent speaker, and 
third the talk is likely to be keynote worthy. I’m not glad to be up 
against him in the schedule.1100, Wintergarden, Enterprise and Internet of ThingsThe Tuesday plenary is by Dr. Mark Little,
 who is doing a great job driving Java EE forward at JBoss. I normally 
don’t go in for IoT sessions, but Mark is sure to make it interesting.1300, Schauspielhaus, Java EE Security: Let’s Make Something UsefulDavid Blevins
 is a strong community voice for improving Java EE, and security is one 
of the most challenging areas to improve. You can tell it’s hard just by
 how long it’s taken for the community to get up enough steam to tackle 
it in a proper JSR. Well, we have one now: JSR-375, and David will tell us how we can make the most of it.1400, Quantum 4, Productive, Effective Development? You Weak Minded fool!Simon Maple has done a great job building the Virtual JUG
 into a force for good in the Java Community. He is well positioned to 
deliver this kind of talk thanks to his role at ZeroTurnaround.1500, Quantum 1, Softwarequalität steigernThis
 appears to be a survey talk about how to effectively use some popular 
tools in practice to improve software quality. I’ve never seen Andreas G¨nzel talk, but the topic is interesting to me.1600, Quantum 4, Puppet für EntwicklerNow
 that Docker is all the rage, I’ll be interested to see what’s new with 
Puppet, or at least learn how these two popular sysadmin technologies 
relate to eachother. As with the previous talk, I’ve not seen Sebastian Hempel speak before this.Thursday, 26 March 2015As mentioned in my previous entry, Oliver Szymanski and I are presenting an entry in the training day: Java EE 7 from an HTML5 Perspective.JavaLand
 was great fun and very professionally enriching last year. This year 
promises to be even more so. I hope to see you there!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JavaLand 2015 Training Day Teaser Blog</title><link href="/blog/2014/12/26/javaland-2015-training-day-teaser.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JavaLand 2015 Training Day Teaser Blog" /><published>2014-12-26T08:03:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-12-26T08:03:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2014/12/26/javaland-2015-training-day-teaser</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2014/12/26/javaland-2015-training-day-teaser.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;h1&gt;JavaLand Training Day Teaser&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;With
 only 61 days to go until JavaLand 2015, it's high time for a preview of
 the Training Day session I am pleased to offer with my friend Oliver 
Szymanksi. Briefly, this session is a full day treatment of the parts of
 Java EE 7 that intersect with the world of HTML5 web development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the session is an update of the successful class we offered at &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://www.oracle.com/javaone/java-university/index.html#JavaEE7&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaOne San Francisco 2014&lt;/a&gt;, it is not a simple repeat. Some major things have happened in the world of HTML5 since JavaOne 2014. Most notably, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2014/10/html5-rec.html.en&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;HTML5 has gone final&lt;/a&gt;. In case you missed it, many things that were slated for inclusion in HTML5 have been descoped, as detailed in the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://dev.w3.org/html5/decision-policy/html5-2014-plan.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Plan 2014&lt;/a&gt;
 document from W3C. The idea is to reduce HTML5 spec size by splitting 
things into seperate specification efforts. Formerly core ideas such as 
the 2D Canvas, Web Storafe, WebSocket, Server Sent Events and WebRTC 
either already had their own specification effort or now have one. The 
Plan 2014 document justifes this move with some compelling anecdotal 
data, summing it up with this defensive statement, “The evidence shows 
that placing technologies in their own extension specifications, while 
initially controversial in some cases, has proven to be a long-term 
benefit for peace and harmony in the end.” Peace and harmony? I hope so.
 In any case, Oliver and I will break this down and show you what it 
means for developers using Java EE 7.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is the basic outline of the session.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Morning session WebSocket, JSON, JSF&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;mondo-grey listicons&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;JSON&lt;br&gt; - Why is this important? JSON is to HTML5 what XML was to web services&lt;br&gt; - JSON-P is for parsing&lt;br&gt; - What about binding to Java Objects?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;WebSocket&lt;br&gt;- Three specs: JavaScript API, IETF transport protocol, Java API&lt;br&gt; - Java API details: Usage from a browser, Usage from standalone client&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;JSF: The good parts&lt;br&gt; - Composite components&lt;br&gt; - HTML 5–friendly markup&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afternoon session: HTML 5 Deep Dive&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;mondo-grey listicons&quot;&gt;&lt;li style=&quot;line-height: 1.3em;&quot;&gt;HTML 5: Why all the fuss?&lt;br&gt; - What's in a name?&lt;br&gt; - Is it really a big deal?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;HTML 5: High-level perspective&lt;br&gt; - Design goals&lt;br&gt; - How does it differ from HTML 4&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;HTML 5: Subspecifications&lt;br&gt; - Browser contexts&lt;br&gt; - Microdata&lt;br&gt; - Canvas context&lt;br&gt; - Offline apps&lt;br&gt; - Messaging&lt;br&gt; - Events&lt;br&gt; - Cross-document messaging&lt;br&gt; - Server-sent events&lt;br&gt; - WebSocket&lt;br&gt; - Drag and drop&lt;br&gt; - Web storage&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaLand 2015&lt;/a&gt; has much to offer aside from just this training day, so please consider attending!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">JavaLand Training Day TeaserWith
 only 61 days to go until JavaLand 2015, it's high time for a preview of
 the Training Day session I am pleased to offer with my friend Oliver 
Szymanksi. Briefly, this session is a full day treatment of the parts of
 Java EE 7 that intersect with the world of HTML5 web development.While the session is an update of the successful class we offered at JavaOne San Francisco 2014, it is not a simple repeat. Some major things have happened in the world of HTML5 since JavaOne 2014. Most notably, HTML5 has gone final. In case you missed it, many things that were slated for inclusion in HTML5 have been descoped, as detailed in the Plan 2014
 document from W3C. The idea is to reduce HTML5 spec size by splitting 
things into seperate specification efforts. Formerly core ideas such as 
the 2D Canvas, Web Storafe, WebSocket, Server Sent Events and WebRTC 
either already had their own specification effort or now have one. The 
Plan 2014 document justifes this move with some compelling anecdotal 
data, summing it up with this defensive statement, “The evidence shows 
that placing technologies in their own extension specifications, while 
initially controversial in some cases, has proven to be a long-term 
benefit for peace and harmony in the end.” Peace and harmony? I hope so.
 In any case, Oliver and I will break this down and show you what it 
means for developers using Java EE 7.Here is the basic outline of the session.Morning session WebSocket, JSON, JSFJSON - Why is this important? JSON is to HTML5 what XML was to web services - JSON-P is for parsing - What about binding to Java Objects?WebSocket- Three specs: JavaScript API, IETF transport protocol, Java API - Java API details: Usage from a browser, Usage from standalone clientJSF: The good parts - Composite components - HTML 5–friendly markupAfternoon session: HTML 5 Deep DiveHTML 5: Why all the fuss? - What's in a name? - Is it really a big deal?HTML 5: High-level perspective - Design goals - How does it differ from HTML 4HTML 5: Subspecifications - Browser contexts - Microdata - Canvas context - Offline apps - Messaging - Events - Cross-document messaging - Server-sent events - WebSocket - Drag and drop - Web storageJavaLand 2015 has much to offer aside from just this training day, so please consider attending!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JavaOne 2014 Day Four Notes Blog</title><link href="/blog/2014/10/28/javaone-2014-day-four-notes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JavaOne 2014 Day Four Notes Blog" /><published>2014-10-28T08:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-10-28T08:35:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2014/10/28/javaone-2014-day-four-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2014/10/28/javaone-2014-day-four-notes.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;With
 all of my formal JavaOne conference obligations satisfied, day four was
 dedicated to listening. Another day, another hotel. The community 
keynote had a little bit of everything and was in the San Francisco 
Marriott, bringing to four the total number of separate buildings I had 
to visit for ]]&amp;gt;is available at Oracle. The room was full, and Intel 
VP Michael Greene had an attentive audience for his portion of the 
keynote. The keynote quickly moved on to showcasing some highlights from
 the Java community over the last year. There was a great selection of 
awards, demos, and product announcements. I was happy to see Scratch 
style programming return to the Java platform in the form of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.reportmill.com/snap/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;SnapCode&lt;/a&gt;, demonstrated by its creator &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DonaldOJDK/status/517731602328453120/photo/1&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Jeff Martin&lt;/a&gt;. I feel that Scratch is the gold standard in this sort of environment, and I was very disappointed when they dropped &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://scratchforums.blob8108.net/forums/viewtopic.php?id=57148&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Java in favor of Flash&lt;/a&gt;
 (as part of a broader move to an entirely cloud-based development 
environment, which I also didn't appreciate). If you had some of the 
same reservations, consider giving SnapCode a try. There were some other
 nifty demos all of which combined to give the attendees a positive 
impression about how fun and cool it is to develop on the Java Platform.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark
 Reinhold re-appeared and gave the rest of the technical keynote, 
allowing Brian Goetz to finish his interrupted content from Sunday. 
Oracle has helpfully produced a &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://medianetwork.oracle.com/video/player/3811045975001&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;single streaming file with the content from both days&lt;/a&gt;. Mark and Brian's presentation was followed by a question and answer panel, facilitated by the twitter hashtag &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/j1qa?src=hash&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;#j1qa&lt;/a&gt;
 and adding James Gosling, Brian Oliver and Charles Nutter as panelists.
 Perhaps we should have done this approach during the web framework 
smackdown. The most humorous question was regarding a suggestion to move
 OpenJDK to GitHub. Mark's satisfyingly definitive answer was &quot;no&quot;. As 
usual with large-scale Q&amp;amp;A panels, there was not much depth and the 
questions bounced around a lot. It's always great to have James Gosling 
on hand for some part of JavaOne, and this year he pointed out that Java
 has come full circle, having been intended for &quot;Internet of Things&quot; 
from the start. I'll point out that Sun had a mass-market IoT device &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.sunspotworld.com/about.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ten years ago&lt;/a&gt; in theform of the SunSPOT. Did you know that Oracle Labs continues the work on SunSPOT and you can &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://shop.oracle.com/pls/ostore/product?p1=sunspotjavadevelopmentkit&amp;amp;p2=&amp;amp;p3=&amp;amp;p4=&amp;amp;sc=sunspotsite&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;still buy them&lt;/a&gt; for $399? The panel closed out with the traditional t-shirt cannon distribution. I give a special thanks to my old pal &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vsenger&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Vinicius Senger&lt;/a&gt; for catching one for me. In a nod to a more TED-style talk, (but a mere shadow of the glory days of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.discovery.org/a/3488&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Douglas Adams' JavaOne keynote&lt;/a&gt;)
 Andra Keay gave a nice talk about the dynamics of robot/human 
interactions. Sadly missing from the talk was any mention about my pet 
peeve in the whole robot revolution: the need to change how society 
values the output of human work in a world where robots do most of the 
work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conference orgnizers thoughtfully delayed the start of 
the rest of the sessions by 30 minutes to accomodate the lengthened 
keynote. This gave me time to get back over to Parc55 for CON2131: Java 
EE Community Update and Panel. &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/brunoborges&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Bruno Borges&lt;/a&gt; moderated. On the panel were my (skiplevels) boss &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cpurdy&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Cameron Purdy&lt;/a&gt;, John Clingan, GlassFish Product Manager at Oracle, Kevin Sutter, Java EE Architect at IBM, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nmcl&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Mark Little&lt;/a&gt;, RedHat VP, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AdamBien&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Adam Bien&lt;/a&gt;, famous Java EE consultant, and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dblevins&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;David Blevins&lt;/a&gt;
 founder of Tomitribe. Sadly missing from this year's panel was any 
representative from Pivotal. Bruno lead off the session with some slides
 and allowed the panelists to introduce themselves. Interestingly, the 
slides in the content catalog for this session are &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://oracleus.activeevents.com/2014/connect/fileDownload/session/22EFE7168EEF4D32387C88483F9FEA81/CON2131_Little-JavaEE.next.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Mark Little's&lt;/a&gt;,
 not Bruno's. Nonetheless, Mark's slides are very informative, do check 
them out. The discussion rapidly focused on some current trends in 
enterprise Java software and how Java EE has responded to and will 
respond to these trends. Mark Little, in typical dry British fashion, 
observed that what we now call microservices is really just the latest 
name for SOA. This observation lead to an acknowledgement that the idea 
of a WAR file being deployed in a container is starting to give way to 
the idea of a deployable application that contains an executable 
runtime. I hope they post the audio for this session because there was a
 lot more that I'm not recalling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It turned out that the next 
session I attended was the only purely technical Java EE based session I
 could make, but it was a good one. It was CON3389: Migrating a 
JSF-Based Web application from Spring 3 to Java EE 7 and CDI. The slides
 are &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://oracleus.activeevents.com/2014/connect/fileDownload/session/38D170F17A082C3A2A7D213C6D498CD0/CON3389_Reimer-Migrating%20a%20JSF-Based%20Web%20Application%20from%20Spring%203%20to%20Java%20EE%207%20and%20CDI.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;in the content catalog&lt;/a&gt;. This session by &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LeanderReimer&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Leander Reimer&lt;/a&gt;
 was an excellent case-study of how an existing JSF based web 
application that was built on Spring was migrated to a pure Java EE 
stack. It is common knowledge that Spring has risen to prominence by 
positioning itself as an alternative to Java EE. What is not so common 
knowledge is that there has always been significant interplay and 
cross-polination of ideas between Spring and Java EE. For example, did 
you know that JSF 1.0 had its own, XML based dependency injection 
mechanism way back in 2004, right around the time that Spring 1.0 was 
released? This sort of thing is not surprising since both stacks have 
been trying to solve the same kinds of problems, for the same kinds of 
developers, and there are only so many ways to skin a cat. This fact 
enabled Mr. Reimer and his team to successfully and quickly complete the
 migration. The main idea of the talk was to show that for every thing 
they had in their app using Spring, there was a corresponding way to do 
it in Java EE. This traversal of migration tasks served as a vehicle for
 pointing out several pitfalls they had to safely navigate to get to 
production. During the Q&amp;amp;A I asked Mr. Reimer a two part question. 
First, I asked why did they use JSF in the first place when many Spring 
shops just go with the built-in Spring MVC? His answer: &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.primefaces.org/showcase/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;PrimeFaces&lt;/a&gt;.
 Next, I asked him to speculate how much harder would the task have been
 had the UI been in Spring MVC instead of JSF. I was hoping the 
discussion might give my colleague Manfred Riem, also in the audience, a
 chance to bring up &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://java.net/projects/mvc-spec/pages/Home&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;MVC 1.0&lt;/a&gt;.
 Instead, Mr. Reimer observed it wouldn't be that hard to write an 
integration layer on top of JSF that allows its use in an 
action-oriented manner. This was a skillfully executed talk with a 
compelling topic given from an in-the-trenches perspective. Bravo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Way back in March when I attended &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javaland.eu/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaLand&lt;/a&gt;
 I saw an excellent session from my old pals Manfred Geiler and Thomas 
Spiegl from Irian. The session was about their new UI technology called &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://ankor.io/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Ankor&lt;/a&gt;. I requested they submit this session to JavaOne, and thankfully it was accepted as &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://oracleus.activeevents.com/2014/connect/fileDownload/session/E2A49CD1203FD3DFA9D7C751D78AB76A/CON2403_Geiler-Ankor%20Presentation%20-%20JavaOne%20SanFrancisco%202014-09.pptx&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CON2403 - Reactive UIs with the MVVM Pattern&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;img alt=&quot;Ed Burns and Manfred Geiler&quot; class=&quot;jive-external-image&quot; style=&quot;float: right;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;136&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Ed Burns and Manfred Geiler&quot; class=&quot;jive-external-image&quot; style=&quot;float: left;&quot; width=&quot;152&quot; height=&quot;136&quot;&gt;I
 was unable to attend the talk as it conflicted with Mr. Reimer's but I 
did catch up with Manfred and Thomas after their session for a beer in 
Duke's cafe. This was a special anniversary for Manfred and I. Ten years
 ago, at JavaOne 2004, Manfred and I met when he attended my session on 
JSF 1.0. Manfred approached me and said, &quot;Hey, I have an independent 
implementation of JSF,&quot; and I was thrilled. This, of course, was &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://myfaces.apache.org/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;MyFaces&lt;/a&gt;.
 To commemorate these two meetings separated by ten years, at left you 
see Manfred and I at JavaOne 2004, and at right, with Thomas Spiegl, at 
JavaOne 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My final session, in the final slot, was &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mjduigou&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Mike Duigou's&lt;/a&gt; excellent &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://oracleus.activeevents.com/2014/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=6309&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CON6309 New Tricks for Old Dogs: Collections in Java 8&lt;/a&gt;. The slides haven't been posted yet, but do get them when they become available. &lt;img alt=&quot;http://ridingthecrest.com/scratch/20141002-stuart-marks-edburns-checkup.jpg&quot; class=&quot;jive-external-image&quot; style=&quot;float: right;&quot; width=&quot;120&quot; height=&quot;195&quot;&gt;Talks
 like this are really useful to expose you to the new features you 
really need in practice. Mike's session was really useful because he 
gave the perspective behind the design choices in these fundamental 
library classes that have contributed so much to the success of Java 
over the years. Sadly, I see that Mike has recently &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mjduigou/status/520360658869579776&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;left Oracle&lt;/a&gt;
 but he's now working with James Gosling directly at his Liquid Robotics
 outfit. I wish you the best, Mike, but I'm sure we'll see you at &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://blogs.oracle.com/javaone/entry/15_off_your_javaone_2015&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaOne next year&lt;/a&gt;. I ran into &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stuartmarks&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Stuart Marks&lt;/a&gt; after Mike's session and he gave me a checkup on the knowledge I had absorbed, as seen at left.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To
 sum up JavaOne 2014, Oracle's consistent investment in promoting the 
Java Developer community is very evident. Though firmly in legacy 
territory, Java is still very vibrant and very new. The priorities 
behind the design choices in Java itself (innovation packaged in an 
enterprise ready programming environment) are on display in the 
community as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">With
 all of my formal JavaOne conference obligations satisfied, day four was
 dedicated to listening. Another day, another hotel. The community 
keynote had a little bit of everything and was in the San Francisco 
Marriott, bringing to four the total number of separate buildings I had 
to visit for ]]&amp;gt;is available at Oracle. The room was full, and Intel 
VP Michael Greene had an attentive audience for his portion of the 
keynote. The keynote quickly moved on to showcasing some highlights from
 the Java community over the last year. There was a great selection of 
awards, demos, and product announcements. I was happy to see Scratch 
style programming return to the Java platform in the form of SnapCode, demonstrated by its creator Jeff Martin. I feel that Scratch is the gold standard in this sort of environment, and I was very disappointed when they dropped Java in favor of Flash
 (as part of a broader move to an entirely cloud-based development 
environment, which I also didn't appreciate). If you had some of the 
same reservations, consider giving SnapCode a try. There were some other
 nifty demos all of which combined to give the attendees a positive 
impression about how fun and cool it is to develop on the Java Platform.Mark
 Reinhold re-appeared and gave the rest of the technical keynote, 
allowing Brian Goetz to finish his interrupted content from Sunday. 
Oracle has helpfully produced a single streaming file with the content from both days. Mark and Brian's presentation was followed by a question and answer panel, facilitated by the twitter hashtag #j1qa
 and adding James Gosling, Brian Oliver and Charles Nutter as panelists.
 Perhaps we should have done this approach during the web framework 
smackdown. The most humorous question was regarding a suggestion to move
 OpenJDK to GitHub. Mark's satisfyingly definitive answer was &quot;no&quot;. As 
usual with large-scale Q&amp;amp;A panels, there was not much depth and the 
questions bounced around a lot. It's always great to have James Gosling 
on hand for some part of JavaOne, and this year he pointed out that Java
 has come full circle, having been intended for &quot;Internet of Things&quot; 
from the start. I'll point out that Sun had a mass-market IoT device ten years ago in theform of the SunSPOT. Did you know that Oracle Labs continues the work on SunSPOT and you can still buy them for $399? The panel closed out with the traditional t-shirt cannon distribution. I give a special thanks to my old pal Vinicius Senger for catching one for me. In a nod to a more TED-style talk, (but a mere shadow of the glory days of Douglas Adams' JavaOne keynote)
 Andra Keay gave a nice talk about the dynamics of robot/human 
interactions. Sadly missing from the talk was any mention about my pet 
peeve in the whole robot revolution: the need to change how society 
values the output of human work in a world where robots do most of the 
work.The conference orgnizers thoughtfully delayed the start of 
the rest of the sessions by 30 minutes to accomodate the lengthened 
keynote. This gave me time to get back over to Parc55 for CON2131: Java 
EE Community Update and Panel. Bruno Borges moderated. On the panel were my (skiplevels) boss Cameron Purdy, John Clingan, GlassFish Product Manager at Oracle, Kevin Sutter, Java EE Architect at IBM, Mark Little, RedHat VP, Adam Bien, famous Java EE consultant, and David Blevins
 founder of Tomitribe. Sadly missing from this year's panel was any 
representative from Pivotal. Bruno lead off the session with some slides
 and allowed the panelists to introduce themselves. Interestingly, the 
slides in the content catalog for this session are Mark Little's,
 not Bruno's. Nonetheless, Mark's slides are very informative, do check 
them out. The discussion rapidly focused on some current trends in 
enterprise Java software and how Java EE has responded to and will 
respond to these trends. Mark Little, in typical dry British fashion, 
observed that what we now call microservices is really just the latest 
name for SOA. This observation lead to an acknowledgement that the idea 
of a WAR file being deployed in a container is starting to give way to 
the idea of a deployable application that contains an executable 
runtime. I hope they post the audio for this session because there was a
 lot more that I'm not recalling.It turned out that the next 
session I attended was the only purely technical Java EE based session I
 could make, but it was a good one. It was CON3389: Migrating a 
JSF-Based Web application from Spring 3 to Java EE 7 and CDI. The slides
 are in the content catalog. This session by Leander Reimer
 was an excellent case-study of how an existing JSF based web 
application that was built on Spring was migrated to a pure Java EE 
stack. It is common knowledge that Spring has risen to prominence by 
positioning itself as an alternative to Java EE. What is not so common 
knowledge is that there has always been significant interplay and 
cross-polination of ideas between Spring and Java EE. For example, did 
you know that JSF 1.0 had its own, XML based dependency injection 
mechanism way back in 2004, right around the time that Spring 1.0 was 
released? This sort of thing is not surprising since both stacks have 
been trying to solve the same kinds of problems, for the same kinds of 
developers, and there are only so many ways to skin a cat. This fact 
enabled Mr. Reimer and his team to successfully and quickly complete the
 migration. The main idea of the talk was to show that for every thing 
they had in their app using Spring, there was a corresponding way to do 
it in Java EE. This traversal of migration tasks served as a vehicle for
 pointing out several pitfalls they had to safely navigate to get to 
production. During the Q&amp;amp;A I asked Mr. Reimer a two part question. 
First, I asked why did they use JSF in the first place when many Spring 
shops just go with the built-in Spring MVC? His answer: PrimeFaces.
 Next, I asked him to speculate how much harder would the task have been
 had the UI been in Spring MVC instead of JSF. I was hoping the 
discussion might give my colleague Manfred Riem, also in the audience, a
 chance to bring up MVC 1.0.
 Instead, Mr. Reimer observed it wouldn't be that hard to write an 
integration layer on top of JSF that allows its use in an 
action-oriented manner. This was a skillfully executed talk with a 
compelling topic given from an in-the-trenches perspective. Bravo.Way back in March when I attended JavaLand
 I saw an excellent session from my old pals Manfred Geiler and Thomas 
Spiegl from Irian. The session was about their new UI technology called Ankor. I requested they submit this session to JavaOne, and thankfully it was accepted as CON2403 - Reactive UIs with the MVVM Pattern. I
 was unable to attend the talk as it conflicted with Mr. Reimer's but I 
did catch up with Manfred and Thomas after their session for a beer in 
Duke's cafe. This was a special anniversary for Manfred and I. Ten years
 ago, at JavaOne 2004, Manfred and I met when he attended my session on 
JSF 1.0. Manfred approached me and said, &quot;Hey, I have an independent 
implementation of JSF,&quot; and I was thrilled. This, of course, was MyFaces.
 To commemorate these two meetings separated by ten years, at left you 
see Manfred and I at JavaOne 2004, and at right, with Thomas Spiegl, at 
JavaOne 2014.My final session, in the final slot, was Mike Duigou's excellent CON6309 New Tricks for Old Dogs: Collections in Java 8. The slides haven't been posted yet, but do get them when they become available. Talks
 like this are really useful to expose you to the new features you 
really need in practice. Mike's session was really useful because he 
gave the perspective behind the design choices in these fundamental 
library classes that have contributed so much to the success of Java 
over the years. Sadly, I see that Mike has recently left Oracle
 but he's now working with James Gosling directly at his Liquid Robotics
 outfit. I wish you the best, Mike, but I'm sure we'll see you at JavaOne next year. I ran into Stuart Marks after Mike's session and he gave me a checkup on the knowledge I had absorbed, as seen at left.To
 sum up JavaOne 2014, Oracle's consistent investment in promoting the 
Java Developer community is very evident. Though firmly in legacy 
territory, Java is still very vibrant and very new. The priorities 
behind the design choices in Java itself (innovation packaged in an 
enterprise ready programming environment) are on display in the 
community as well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JavaOne 2014 Day Three Notes Blog</title><link href="/blog/2014/10/16/javaone-2014-day-three-notes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JavaOne 2014 Day Three Notes Blog" /><published>2014-10-16T12:08:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-10-16T12:08:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2014/10/16/javaone-2014-day-three-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2014/10/16/javaone-2014-day-three-notes.html">&lt;div class=&quot;jive-rendered-content&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Day
 three was definitely the high point of the conference for me.&amp;nbsp; As 
anyone who has spoken at tech conferences knows, the point in time when 
all of one's sessions have been given is the turning point between 
tempered enjoyment and pure enjoyment of the conference.&amp;nbsp; I was 
blessed with the scheduling this year; I was all done after 
Wednesday.&amp;nbsp; This put me in a great frame of mind to enjoy the 
Oracle Appreciation Event.&amp;nbsp; Day three also saw the culmination of a
 long running project: the Web Framework Smackdown 2014 edition.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;My friend and colleague &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.rahmannet.net/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Reza Rahman&lt;/a&gt; asked me to keep the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://weblogs.java.net/blog/edburns/archive/2014/06/22/web-framework-smackdown-2014-edition?force=485&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;web framework smackdown meme&lt;/a&gt;
 going for another year.&amp;nbsp; This year I called in quite a few favors 
to pull together a diverse group of celebrity panelists: &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mhevery&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Miško Hevery&lt;/a&gt;, creator of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/angularjs&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; at Google, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/floydophone&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Pete Hunt&lt;/a&gt; creator of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reactjs&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ReactJS&lt;/a&gt; at Facebook, &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/servlet/JiveServlet/showImage/38-14345-149455/20141001-smackdown-prep.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;395&quot; alt=&quot;panelists preparing&quot; src=&quot;20141016_files/20141001-smackdown-prep.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;103&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joonaslehtinen&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Joonas Lehtinen&lt;/a&gt;, creator of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vaadin&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Vaadin&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; The panel was moderated by &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/neal4d&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Neal Ford&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thoughtworks&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ThoughtWorks&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; I rounded out the panel representing &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jsf_spec&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JSF&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;
 I've learned from previous smackdowns that a confident and comfortable 
moderator combined with a little prep time just before the panel are the
 keys to success.&amp;nbsp; We met at 11am for this purpose over Patxi's 
pizza. From the left you can see Neal Ford, Miško Hevery, myself, Joonas
 Lehtinen, and Pete Hunt.&amp;nbsp; I don't think Pete and Miško had met 
before, and it was interesting hearing them trade notes about their 
approaches to the performance of handling the model update side of their
 frameworks.&amp;nbsp; From what I gathered, they both see that feature as 
the most valuable aspect of their frameworks, and they both have spent 
significant time optimizing that part.&amp;nbsp; When it came time to take 
it on stage, we started by introducing our different approaches to the 
task of building a stateful and responsive user interface delivered in a
 web browser.&amp;nbsp; Angular and React are entirely client side, while 
JSF and Vaadin are entirely server side.&amp;nbsp; In spite of Neal's 
earlier recommendation that client side is the way of the future, Joonas
 and I made the case for where server side makes sense.&amp;nbsp; Briefly, 
reasons for favoring server side over client side include simplicity, 
security, integratability (such as mashups), and maintainability.&amp;nbsp; 
Client side is better when Facebook-sized scale is important, when 
JavaScript fluency is a non-issue, and when &quot;modern&quot; browsers are a 
given.&amp;nbsp; You'll have to check out the audio to get the full 
details.&amp;nbsp; My only complaint with the panel is that it really didn't
 get smackdown-ish at all.&amp;nbsp; I welcome comments about the 
client/server UI debate.&amp;nbsp; Perhaps we can get some smackdown action 
in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;My last official obligation of the 
conference was my final booth duty in the Java EE both.&amp;nbsp; This 
session closed out the JavaOne exhibition, and as such the traffic was a
 bit light.&amp;nbsp; I was able to take a tour around the exhibition to 
obtain some schwag for my kids.&amp;nbsp; This year it was novel to see &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://codewithtarget.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Target&lt;/a&gt;
 with a booth.&amp;nbsp; I've long been a fan (and shareholder) of Target, 
avoiding Wal*mart at all (unfortunately frequently too high) 
costs.&amp;nbsp; They were recruiting.&amp;nbsp; JavaOne is not a job fair, but 
it was still nice to see them representing Minneapolis, home of Facelets
 creator Jakob Hookom.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/servlet/JiveServlet/showImage/38-14345-149456/20141001-nullpointers-01.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;396&quot; alt=&quot;Geert and the NullPointers&quot; src=&quot;20141016_files/20141001-nullpointers-01.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;220&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/servlet/JiveServlet/showImage/38-14345-149457/20141001-nullpointers-02.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img __embedded_id=&quot;397&quot; alt=&quot;Freddy, Frank, and Ed&quot; src=&quot;20141016_files/20141001-nullpointers-02.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right;&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;123&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Booth duty done, it was on to a bit of fun in Duke's Cafe.&amp;nbsp; As I mentioned in my &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://weblogs.java.net/blog/edburns/archive/2014/10/07/javaone-2014-day-one-notes&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JavaOne 2014 Day One&lt;/a&gt; blog entry, Chicago JUG leader &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fguime&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Freddy Guime&lt;/a&gt;
 had put together a band of musician Java enthusiasts called the 
NullPointers. They allowed me to sit in with them for some songs during 
their set at 5pm Wednesday.&amp;nbsp; This was a real honor and a great 
blast.&amp;nbsp; At left, from the left you see &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/neuroph&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Zoran Severac&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/matkar&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Mattias Karlsson&lt;/a&gt;, of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.jfokus.se/jfokus/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;JFokus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gbevin&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Geert Bevin&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://zeroturnaround.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ZeroTurnaround&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JavaFXpert&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Jim Weaver&lt;/a&gt;, Java Developer Advocate for Oracle.&amp;nbsp; At right, from the right, you see Freddy, &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/frankgreco&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Frank Greco&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://www.javasig.com/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;New York Java Users Group&lt;/a&gt; and myself.&amp;nbsp; I think my keyboard stand was formerly in the Hackergarten.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;The fun kept on rolling, with the &lt;a class=&quot;jive-link-external-small&quot; href=&quot;http://home.java.net/sites/default/files/c12bg-openworld-bands-2264324.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Oracle Appreciation Event&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;
 This used to be called the Customer Appreciation Event.&amp;nbsp; I'm not 
sure why they renamed it.&amp;nbsp; I would probably have given it a pass 
this year but for my 11 year old who is a big Macklemore fan.&amp;nbsp; I'm 
glad I went because Macklemore was very entertaining, and Aerosmith put 
on a great show as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">Day
 three was definitely the high point of the conference for me.&amp;nbsp; As 
anyone who has spoken at tech conferences knows, the point in time when 
all of one's sessions have been given is the turning point between 
tempered enjoyment and pure enjoyment of the conference.&amp;nbsp; I was 
blessed with the scheduling this year; I was all done after 
Wednesday.&amp;nbsp; This put me in a great frame of mind to enjoy the 
Oracle Appreciation Event.&amp;nbsp; Day three also saw the culmination of a
 long running project: the Web Framework Smackdown 2014 edition.&amp;nbsp; My friend and colleague Reza Rahman asked me to keep the web framework smackdown meme
 going for another year.&amp;nbsp; This year I called in quite a few favors 
to pull together a diverse group of celebrity panelists: Miško Hevery, creator of AngularJS at Google, Pete Hunt creator of ReactJS at Facebook,  and Joonas Lehtinen, creator of Vaadin.&amp;nbsp; The panel was moderated by Neal Ford of ThoughtWorks.&amp;nbsp; I rounded out the panel representing JSF.&amp;nbsp;
 I've learned from previous smackdowns that a confident and comfortable 
moderator combined with a little prep time just before the panel are the
 keys to success.&amp;nbsp; We met at 11am for this purpose over Patxi's 
pizza. From the left you can see Neal Ford, Miško Hevery, myself, Joonas
 Lehtinen, and Pete Hunt.&amp;nbsp; I don't think Pete and Miško had met 
before, and it was interesting hearing them trade notes about their 
approaches to the performance of handling the model update side of their
 frameworks.&amp;nbsp; From what I gathered, they both see that feature as 
the most valuable aspect of their frameworks, and they both have spent 
significant time optimizing that part.&amp;nbsp; When it came time to take 
it on stage, we started by introducing our different approaches to the 
task of building a stateful and responsive user interface delivered in a
 web browser.&amp;nbsp; Angular and React are entirely client side, while 
JSF and Vaadin are entirely server side.&amp;nbsp; In spite of Neal's 
earlier recommendation that client side is the way of the future, Joonas
 and I made the case for where server side makes sense.&amp;nbsp; Briefly, 
reasons for favoring server side over client side include simplicity, 
security, integratability (such as mashups), and maintainability.&amp;nbsp; 
Client side is better when Facebook-sized scale is important, when 
JavaScript fluency is a non-issue, and when &quot;modern&quot; browsers are a 
given.&amp;nbsp; You'll have to check out the audio to get the full 
details.&amp;nbsp; My only complaint with the panel is that it really didn't
 get smackdown-ish at all.&amp;nbsp; I welcome comments about the 
client/server UI debate.&amp;nbsp; Perhaps we can get some smackdown action 
in the comments.&amp;nbsp; My last official obligation of the 
conference was my final booth duty in the Java EE both.&amp;nbsp; This 
session closed out the JavaOne exhibition, and as such the traffic was a
 bit light.&amp;nbsp; I was able to take a tour around the exhibition to 
obtain some schwag for my kids.&amp;nbsp; This year it was novel to see Target
 with a booth.&amp;nbsp; I've long been a fan (and shareholder) of Target, 
avoiding Wal*mart at all (unfortunately frequently too high) 
costs.&amp;nbsp; They were recruiting.&amp;nbsp; JavaOne is not a job fair, but 
it was still nice to see them representing Minneapolis, home of Facelets
 creator Jakob Hookom.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;  Booth duty done, it was on to a bit of fun in Duke's Cafe.&amp;nbsp; As I mentioned in my JavaOne 2014 Day One blog entry, Chicago JUG leader Freddy Guime
 had put together a band of musician Java enthusiasts called the 
NullPointers. They allowed me to sit in with them for some songs during 
their set at 5pm Wednesday.&amp;nbsp; This was a real honor and a great 
blast.&amp;nbsp; At left, from the left you see Zoran Severac, Mattias Karlsson, of JFokus, Geert Bevin of ZeroTurnaround, and Jim Weaver, Java Developer Advocate for Oracle.&amp;nbsp; At right, from the right, you see Freddy, Frank Greco of the New York Java Users Group and myself.&amp;nbsp; I think my keyboard stand was formerly in the Hackergarten.&amp;nbsp; The fun kept on rolling, with the Oracle Appreciation Event.&amp;nbsp;
 This used to be called the Customer Appreciation Event.&amp;nbsp; I'm not 
sure why they renamed it.&amp;nbsp; I would probably have given it a pass 
this year but for my 11 year old who is a big Macklemore fan.&amp;nbsp; I'm 
glad I went because Macklemore was very entertaining, and Aerosmith put 
on a great show as well.</summary></entry></feed>
