<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-19T22:50:52-04:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ed Burns Blog</title><subtitle>Ed Burns blogs here, mostly about Java and software, but sometimes about other random things.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ed’s Microsoft Build May 2021 Session Picks</title><link href="/blog/2021/05/19/build-picks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ed’s Microsoft Build May 2021 Session Picks" /><published>2021-05-19T18:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-19T18:30:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2021/05/19/build-picks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2021/05/19/build-picks.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross posted at &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/edburns00/ed-s-microsoft-build-may-2021-session-picks-2l9e&quot;&gt;dev.to&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the end of in-person events I have not bothered to do my traditional “Ed’s session picks” posts, as I have so often in the past.  (These posts are a ride through memory lane: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2008/04/25/javaone-2008-picks.html&quot;&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2011/06/14/jazoon-2011-picks.html&quot;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2011/09/28/updated-20110930-1357-ed-burns-javaone-2011-session-picks.html&quot;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/02/18/eds-devnexus-2014-picks.html&quot;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/03/03/eds-javaland-2014-picks.html&quot;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/01/15/javaland-2015-conference-picks.html&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/02/21/devnexus-2017-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/02/27/javaland-2017-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/03/20/devoxx-us-2017-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/04/19/goto-chicago-picks.html&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/03/11/javaland-2019-picks.html&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/08/26/oracle-code-one-2019-picks.html&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/11/20/jvm-con-picks.html&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt; ).  Now that Microsoft is focusing so heavily on making Java run great on Azure, it’s time to survey what Build 2021 has to offer Java developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traditional audience for Microsoft Build is less technical and
more business focused than the audience for the conferences I usually
attend.  But at this point in my career, I’m ok with that.  I am aware
that success with Java on Azure means influencing that audience.  So
I’m very excited to highlight these exciting Java related sessions at
Microsoft Build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note: if you go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions&quot;&gt;Session scheduler&lt;/a&gt; and enter “java not javascript” you will see the Java related sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tuesday-25-may-2021&quot;&gt;Tuesday, 25 May 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;0500-edt-java-champions-talk-java-at-microsoft-interstitial-programming&quot;&gt;05:00 EDT Java Champions talk Java at Microsoft: Interstitial Programming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join Julien Dubois, Jonathan Giles and I for a sevin minute
interstitial programming segment talking about high velocity cloud
native Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1800-edt-kroger-joins-customer-tech-talks-to-discuss-how-they-are-using-java-on-azure-to-manage-stock-levels-across-their-stores&quot;&gt;18:00 EDT Kroger joins Customer Tech Talks to discuss how they are using Java on Azure to manage stock levels across their stores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success at Microsoft is all about impact.  How much impact does your
work have?  How does it achieve our vision of empowering every person
and every organization on the planet to achieve more?  This 30 minute
customer success focused session show the impact Java has at one of
the leading grocery retailers in the US.  They also own Fred Meyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/db6c0213-d07f-4ee1-8d5c-26154d7632b6?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wednesday-26-may-2021&quot;&gt;Wednesday, 26 May 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1800-edt-ask-the-java-at-microsoft-experts&quot;&gt;18:00 EDT Ask the Java at Microsoft Experts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reza Rahman, Asir Selvasingh and I are in the virtual booth and are
excited to take your questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/aded32d6-b9e3-486c-a208-9ebcece1fbdd?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thursday-26-may-2021&quot;&gt;Thursday, 26 May 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1000-edt-ask-the-experts-whats-new-for-developers-for-building-dual-screen-apps-for-the-surface-duo&quot;&gt;10:00 EDT Ask the Experts: What’s new for Developers for building Dual Screen Apps for the Surface Duo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the Nintendo DS (dual screen)?  The Surface Duo also has two screens, but it’s a Microsoft device and it runs Android.  That means, you can code for it using Java or Kotlin.  This one sounds really fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/19b093c6-6718-4114-87f0-861baafefa65?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-demand-sessions&quot;&gt;On Demand Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accelerating-enterprise-java-workloads-on-azure&quot;&gt;Accelerating enterprise Java workloads on Azure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where we get to show off all the things we are doing with Java EE related technologies on Azure.  It’s presented by my colleague Reza Rahman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/2ce6782a-a7e4-4bcf-b4b6-1c9fd5d3e58a?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-linux-web-apps-easily-and-securely-on-azure-app-service&quot;&gt;Run Linux web apps easily and securely on Azure App Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Azure App Service and Azure Kubernetes Service are the two workhorse
services of Azure compute.  This talk is about the former, which
provides a much easier to understand model of the cloud to users than
what is offered by AKS.  App Service offers a wide variety of
pre-configured solution stacks on Java, .NET Core, Python, and Node,
including Tomcat and Java EE JBoss EAP.  I’m not sure how much Java
will be covered, but App Service definitely supports Java vere well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybuild.microsoft.com/sessions/77d6c20f-6b37-4643-9e31-6bcd6da4dad0?source=sessions&quot;&gt;Content catalog link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cross posted at dev.to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blurring parts of the screen in OBS Studio, other tips</title><link href="/blog/2021/04/02/obs-blur.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blurring parts of the screen in OBS Studio, other tips" /><published>2021-04-02T16:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T16:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2021/04/02/obs-blur</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2021/04/02/obs-blur.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog posts captures some learning I did about OBS recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently invested a little time in learning the basics of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/obsproject/obs-studio&quot;&gt;OBS Studio&lt;/a&gt;.  OBS is one of
those programs that seems enormously powerful, has a vast user base,
and a correspondingly vast amount of content about it on YouTube.
There is so much content about OBS it’s hard to tell what’s good.
Thankfully, I stumbled upon 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ySENWFIkL7c&quot;&gt;this 27 minute tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
from Kevin Stratvert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to Mr. Stratvert’s tutorial, there are some other
essential tips I want to capture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blurring-during-recording&quot;&gt;Blurring during recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5zM3xvkb8dY&quot;&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt;, from a much
more gamer-focused perspective, did give a practical tip for how
selectively blur arbitrary portions of the screen.  I’ll outline the
process next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a new &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt; source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arrange it above your “main” &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt; source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a &lt;strong&gt;Scaling/Aspect Ratio&lt;/strong&gt; filter to it.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scale Filtering&lt;/strong&gt; Point.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolution&lt;/strong&gt; 640x360&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Drag the red grabber handles so that the new &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt;
source completely covers the “main” display capture source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE IS THE IMPORTANT STEP&lt;/strong&gt;: Hold down the alt key and re-size
the grabbers to cover the area you want to blur.  &lt;strong&gt;It is very
important you don’t move the region by dragging it.&lt;/strong&gt; Use the
alt-resize technique to effectively move the blur zone.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This works because of the low resolution you set.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repeat this process for whatever other parts of the screen you want
to blur.  Note that you can blur/un-blur easily with the “eye” icon
for htat &lt;strong&gt;Display capture&lt;/strong&gt; source in the &lt;strong&gt;Sources&lt;/strong&gt; screen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bluring-after-recording&quot;&gt;Bluring after recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found I missed some things on my first recording and needed to do
additional blurring.  No problem, add a &lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt; source and select
the file from the first recording.  You can then play the first recording
into another recording and add more blurring as desired. I found this
reminded me of some of the performance aspect of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sqz5YaHx26g&quot;&gt;real time analog audio mixing&lt;/a&gt; because I had to take cues from the media source for when to blur/un-blur certain parts of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, when you add &lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt; source, by default you cannot hear the
audio. Turn it on with these steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Audio Mixer&lt;/strong&gt; panel, in the row for &lt;strong&gt;Media Source&lt;/strong&gt; select the cog icon and select &lt;strong&gt;Advanced Audio Properties&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the row for &lt;strong&gt;Media Source&lt;/strong&gt;, in the column for &lt;strong&gt;Audio Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;, ensure &lt;strong&gt;Monitor and Output&lt;/strong&gt; is selected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;removing-click-sounds-from-your-mic-while-recording&quot;&gt;Removing click sounds from your mic while recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add these filters to your &lt;strong&gt;Mic/Aux&lt;/strong&gt; source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noise Suppression&lt;/strong&gt;: RNNoise&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noise Gate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Close Threshold: -54.00 dB&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Open Threshold: -39.00 dB&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Remainder at defaults.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog posts captures some learning I did about OBS recently.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">File Explorer and WSL2 PWD</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/30/wslpwd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="File Explorer and WSL2 PWD" /><published>2020-10-30T13:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-30T13:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/30/wslpwd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/30/wslpwd.html">&lt;p&gt;I had long been used to doing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;open .&lt;/code&gt; on macOS to get finder window
open on the current directory in the shell.  I wanted something similar
under WSL2, but this is the best I could come up with.  It copies the
current working directory to the clipboard such that you can press
“ctrl-l crtl-v ret” in the File Explorer and get the same effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function &lt;/span&gt;wslpwd&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; //wsl&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$/&lt;/span&gt;Ubuntu&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$PWD&lt;/span&gt; | &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;sed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'s:/:\\:g'&lt;/span&gt; | pbcopy
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assumptions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pbcopy is installed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WSL distro name is Ubuntu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It prepends the special &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;//wsl$/Ubuntu&lt;/code&gt; string to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$PWD&lt;/code&gt;, then uses &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt;
to transform the forward slashes to backslashes, then uses &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pbcopy&lt;/code&gt; to put
the result on the system clipboard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had long been used to doing open . on macOS to get finder window open on the current directory in the shell. I wanted something similar under WSL2, but this is the best I could come up with. It copies the current working directory to the clipboard such that you can press “ctrl-l crtl-v ret” in the File Explorer and get the same effect.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Public Key Infrastructure</title><link href="/blog/2020/08/28/public-key-infrastructure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Public Key Infrastructure" /><published>2020-08-28T15:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-28T15:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/08/28/public-key-infrastructure</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/08/28/public-key-infrastructure.html">&lt;p&gt;I needed to remind myself of how public key cryptography worked so I
looked up this excerpt I remembered writing in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Ed-Burns/e/B001ILO9Y8&quot;&gt;JSF The Complete Reference&lt;/a&gt;.  I’m saving it here for the next time I forget how this works and need to remind myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to share data securely is to encrypt it using some scheme and share the password with the party with whom you want to share the data. Of course, the matter of sharing the password securely is a problem, but let’s just say you can tell the person directly. While the shared password scheme is easy to understand and implement, it doesn’t scale to large numbers of users without compromising security. Public key cryptography, also called public key infrastructure, or PKI, solves the problem by breaking the concept of a password into two parts, a “public key” and a “private key.” The archetypal analogy to describe PKI involves two peopleAlice and Bobwho want to send messages to each other through the postal mail. In order for Alice to send a message to Bob securely, Alice asks Bob to send her his open padlock, to which only Bob has the key. Alice then puts the message in the box and locks it with Bob’s padlock, sending it in the mail. When Bob receives the box he can open the box with his key and see the message. Conversely, when Bob wants to send a message to Alice, he needs Alice’s open padlock. In PKI, the padlock is the public key, and the key for the padlock is the private key. This situation is depicted in Figure 14-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to share data with someone, you need their public key and your private key; therefore, it is desirable to distribute your public key as widely as possible. That’s where the “infrastructure” in public key infrastructure really comes in. When padlocks (public keys) are freely distributed, the problem is verifying that Alice’s padlock really belongs to Alice and not some malicious postman who opened the mail and replaced Alice’s padlock with his own, only to intercept the return package and open the box. The authenticity of a public key is determined using an “identity certificate.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200828-pki.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alice and Bob exchange a secret message&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When speaking of Internet security, an “identity certificate” is an electronic document originating from a trusted source that vouches for the authenticity of a public key. The source from which the certificate originates is known as the certificate authority (CA), and there are a handful of such bodies in business around the world today. CACert, Thawte, and VeriSign are three popular CAs. To bring the matter back to Web applications, servers and clients may possess their own public keys, and identity certificates to vouch for them, to encrypt all the traffic between client and server. Because Web applications are by nature interactive, clients must authenticate themselves to servers as well as servers to clients. This is known as two-way authentication and is the standard practice when using client certificate authentication. Once the certificates have been authenticated, the public keys are used to establish a secure transport connection, such as with the Transport Level Security (TLS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from JavaServer Faces 2.0: The Complete Reference, McGraw-Hill November 23, 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISBN 978-0071625098&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I needed to remind myself of how public key cryptography worked so I looked up this excerpt I remembered writing in JSF The Complete Reference. I’m saving it here for the next time I forget how this works and need to remind myself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WSL2 az login xdg-open and Microsoft Edge (or any other browser)</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/29/wsl2-xdg-open-edge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WSL2 az login xdg-open and Microsoft Edge (or any other browser)" /><published>2020-07-29T15:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-29T15:10:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/29/wsl2-xdg-open-edge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/29/wsl2-xdg-open-edge.html">&lt;p&gt;If you ever run into a problem with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az login&lt;/code&gt; opening a Windows browser
to complete the login, this blog post may help.  I ran into this today.
When I did &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az logout&lt;/code&gt; followed by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az login&lt;/code&gt; I saw the following, and
the login did not complete succesfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: firefox: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: iceweasel: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: seamonkey: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: mozilla: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: epiphany: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: konqueror: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: chromium: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: chromium-browser: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: google-chrome: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: www-browser: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: links2: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: elinks: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: links: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: lynx: not found
/usr/bin/xdg-open: 851: /usr/bin/xdg-open: w3m: not found
xdg-open: no method available for opening 'https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/authorize?response_type=code&amp;amp;client_id=04b07795-8ddb-461a-bbee-02f9e1bf7b46&amp;amp;redirect_uri=http://localhost:8400&amp;amp;state=jq29agg65cx8xmh3axhv&amp;amp;resource=https://management.core.windows.net/&amp;amp;prompt=select_account'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;¯\_(ツ)_/¯
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After poking around a bit, I arrived at the following solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-make-an-executable-script-in-my-bin-directory-that-runs-the-browser-on-the-windows-side&quot;&gt;1. Make an executable script in my bin directory that runs the browser on the windows side&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See step 5 in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/blog/2019/08/14/emacs-edge-dev.html&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;.
Modify the script to reference your preferred browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-create-an-edgedesktop-file-in-the-correct-place&quot;&gt;2. Create an edge.desktop file in the correct place&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it so this file exists: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/.local/share/applications/edge.desktop&lt;/code&gt;
and has the following content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Desktop Entry]
Encoding=UTF-8
Version=1.0
Type=Application
NoDisplay=true
Exec=/home/edburns/bin/runedge.sh %u
Name=Edge
Comment=Custom definition for Edge Beta
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to modify the value of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Exec&lt;/code&gt; line accordingly.  Also,
if you are using a different browser, you’ll need to change the name of
the file to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;whaterYourBrowser.desktop&lt;/code&gt;.  Close the file when done editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-use-xdg-settings-to-set-the-default-web-browser&quot;&gt;3. Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xdg-settings&lt;/code&gt; to set the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;default-web-browser&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have created &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;edge.desktop&lt;/code&gt; in the correct place, you can
tell &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xdg-settings&lt;/code&gt; that it is the default browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xdg-settings set default-web-browser edge.desktop
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I ran this, it took a while, and I observed it added this
line to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;edge.desktop&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;MimeType=x-scheme-handler/unknown;x-scheme-handler/about;x-scheme-handler/https;x-scheme-handler/http;text/html;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can verify the setting with the following command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xdg-settings get default-web-browser
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-az-login-should-pop-up-the-browser&quot;&gt;4. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az login&lt;/code&gt; should pop up the browser.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;az logout
az login
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you ever run into a problem with az login opening a Windows browser to complete the login, this blog post may help. I ran into this today. When I did az logout followed by az login I saw the following, and the login did not complete succesfully.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter to the Editor: Economist 2020-07-11: Leader: The New Ideology of Race</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/12/economist-race-leader-letter-to-editor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter to the Editor: Economist 2020-07-11: Leader: The New Ideology of Race" /><published>2020-07-12T12:50:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-12T12:50:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/12/economist-race-leader-letter-to-editor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/12/economist-race-leader-letter-to-editor.html">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your leader “&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/20200711-economist-leader-new-ideology-of-race.pdf&quot;&gt;The New Ideology of Race&lt;/a&gt;” asserts, “Liberalism thrives on a marketplace of ideas…[and] uses facts and evidence, tested in debate, to help the weak take on the strong.”  Unfortunately, the corresponding new ideology of the American right has subverted liberalism, successfully equating it with ill-defined labels such as Antifa, and completely destroying the very concept of “facts and evidence”.  As for “debate”, that requires good faith, and the American right has defined good faith as weakness.  The proponents of the “New Ideology of Race” understand this reality.  To slow the slide toward irrelevance, “Liberalism” must understand it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Burns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altamonte Springs, FL USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Access WSL2 .vhdx on External Drive Within a Windows 10 System Image</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/07/wsl2-external-vhdx.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Access WSL2 .vhdx on External Drive Within a Windows 10 System Image" /><published>2020-07-07T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-07T08:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/07/wsl2-external-vhdx</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/07/wsl2-external-vhdx.html">&lt;p&gt;This post documents how to hack a Windows registry entry to gain access
to the contents of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://aka.ms/install-wsl&quot;&gt;WSL2&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt; volume
which resides within a Windows 10 System Image on an external disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scenario&quot;&gt;Scenario&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone should have a backup strategy that works for them in terms of
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hassle factor&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;capability&lt;/code&gt;: your strategy should have &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;no more hassle&lt;/code&gt;
than you are willing to put up with to give you a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;daily backup
capability&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On macOS, I use the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://bombich.com/&quot;&gt;Carbon Copy
Cloner&lt;/a&gt;.  On Windows 10 I use the built-in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.howtogeek.com/howto/4241/how-to-create-a-system-image-in-windows-7/&quot;&gt;Create
a system
image&lt;/a&gt;.
In both cases, I store the backup on an external drive.  Yesterday, due
to a stupid git rebase user error, I lost some commits on a repo that was
stored within my WSL2 Ubuntu machine.  “No worries,” I thought.  “I’ll
just grab the commits from my backup”.  I followed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.logicbig.com/how-to/windows/mount-windows-10-backup.html&quot;&gt;these
steps&lt;/a&gt;
to mount the System Image as a local drive and navigate to the
file…“oh wait.  The file is within the WSL image. [:sad trombone:]”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With help from WSL2 Twitter celebrity &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/craigaloewen&quot;&gt;Craig
Loewen&lt;/a&gt; I used this process to get my
lost commits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t already have WSL2, you should totally get it.  Get started at 
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aka.ms/install-wsl&quot;&gt;https://aka.ms/install-wsl&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;.  I was a Mac
user from 2007 until I joined Microsoft in June 2019.  If not for WLS2,
I’d still be a Mac user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-access-wsl2-vhdx-on-external-drive-within-a-windows-10-system-image&quot;&gt;How to Access WSL2 .vhdx on External Drive Within a Windows 10 System Image&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will edit the Windows registry to point a new Debian WSL2
distribution to the .vhdx file on the external drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-the-fully-qualified-path-to-the-vhdx-file&quot;&gt;Get the fully qualified path to the .vhdx file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount the System Image that contains the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt; file and capture its
fully qualified path.  In my case this is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;K:\Users\edburns\AppData\Local\Packages\CanonicalGroupLimited.UbuntuonWindows_79rhkp1fndgsc\LocalState
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;create-a-fresh-wsl2-debian-distribution-so-you-can-edit-its-windows-registry-entry-without-fear-of-damaging-anything&quot;&gt;Create a fresh WSL2 Debian distribution so you can edit its Windows Registry entry without fear of damaging anything&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make it so when you do &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wsl -l -v&lt;/code&gt; in Windows PowerShell you do
&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; see a distribution named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Debian&lt;/code&gt;.  If you do see one, figure
out how to save it aside.  We want to install a fresh Debian
distribution.  If you already have one, you’ll need to move it aside
so you don’t damage it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install a fresh Debian (RIP Ian Murdock) distribution from the
Windows store.  Create a userid when asked.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exit the Debian and shut down WSL2 with the command &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wsl --shutdown&lt;/code&gt;
in PowerShell.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;edit-the-windows-registry-entry-for-the-vhdx-file-of-the-fresh-debian-distribution&quot;&gt;Edit the Windows Registry entry for the .vhdx file of the fresh Debian distribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the secret sauce!  I use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;regedt32&lt;/code&gt;, but you can use any other
registry editor.  In your registry editor, navigate to this entry and
expand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Computer\HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Lxss&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This image shows what I see under the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lxss&lt;/code&gt; entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200707-wsl2-registry.png&quot; alt=&quot;Entries within Lxss&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carefully select each entry until you find the one whose
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DistributionName&lt;/code&gt; sub-entry is exactly &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Debian&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;BasePath&lt;/code&gt; sub-entry and Modify its value.  Set the value to
be exactly the fully qualified path to your external &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt; file, not
including the filename or trailing slash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exit the Windows Registry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-the-debian-image-and-get-your-files&quot;&gt;Run the “Debian” image and get your files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Windows PowerShell, run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wsl -d Debian&lt;/code&gt;.  This should boot up the
WSL2 into the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.vhdx&lt;/code&gt;, allowing you to get the missing files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;PRO TIP!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The super handy &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\wsl$\&amp;lt;distroname&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; usage in Windows File Explorer
should work also.  In my case I was able to get the files by visiting
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\wsl$\Debian\home\edburns\workareas&lt;/code&gt; in Windows Explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/craigaloewen&quot;&gt;Craig Loewen&lt;/a&gt; for
this tip.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post documents how to hack a Windows registry entry to gain access to the contents of a WSL2 .vhdx volume which resides within a Windows 10 System Image on an external disk.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">White Fragility by Robin DiAngelo: Highlights</title><link href="/blog/2020/06/09/white-fragility-highlights.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="White Fragility by Robin DiAngelo: Highlights" /><published>2020-06-09T09:20:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T09:20:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/06/09/white-fragility-highlights</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/06/09/white-fragility-highlights.html">&lt;p&gt;Cross posted at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/white-fragility-robin-diangelo-highlights-ed-burns/&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;,
if that’s your thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://robindiangelo.com/publications/&quot;&gt;White Fragility&lt;/a&gt;” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://robindiangelo.com/publications/&quot;&gt;Robin
DeAngelo&lt;/a&gt; is a great book about
racism.  You should read it.  This blog post tries to get you to read it
by extracting what I think are the best parts.  That’s why it’s so long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;details&quot;&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best indicator that a white person really needs to read “White
Fragility” by Robin DiAngelo (Beacon Press, 2018) is their first
response to the mere suggestion that they read it. This speaks to two
things: 1. a great title 2. the absolute necessity for more white people
to read the book. I have only suggested it to a few people, but
reactions range from indignation to scorn. One person told me they
thought I was “too smart to read a book like that”.  I hope this brief
moment of national awareness prompted by the murder of George Floyd by
an agent of the state might give such people a reason to read this blog
post, and then hopefully Ms. DiAngelo’s highly accessible 154 page book.
This blog post is my selection of highlights from the book, with
occasional thoughts mixed in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. DiAngelo has done many years of trainings and workshops about racism
to mostly white audiences.  If you work in corporate America, you
probably have been exposed to this kind of training.  You may even
resent having had to take it.  In my case it was web-delivered training
that really can’t offer the kind of growth an in-person class can offer.
If you had in-person training, this book may resonate even more with
you.  The in-person training done by Ms. DiAngelo and her company
produces real interactions and reactions from the participants.  These
reactions and related observations are the research corpus for this
book.  When Ms. DiAngelo says, “this is how white people respond when I
say X,” I trust her credibility.  I’m asking you to do the same, at
least while reading this blog post, and, hopefully, reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll take a really nice hook from the end of the book and try to set it
here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Imagine you go to the doctor, who tells you that you have an acoustic
neuroma.  Just as she is about to explain what this is and what your
options are, she gets an emergency call and must rush off, abruptly
ending your visit.  What would you do?  You would very likely go home,
get on the internet, and read everything you could find on the
subject...Bottom line: you would care enough to get informed.  So
consider racism a matter of life and death (as it is for people of
color), and do your homework.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading this blog post is a great start.  Reading the book would be a
great next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. DiAngelo starts out by showing the scope of the problem, and how
completely intractable it is, but somehow manages to make me able to
keep reading.  The hook is how she does it: not through some sugar
coated sense of hope, but through honesty and candor.  As I read the
book I get the sense: yes, I can do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;authors-note&quot;&gt;Author’s Note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. DiAngelo commences with an Author’s Note which sets the tone
with these facts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
The United States was founded on the principle that all people are
created equal.  Yet the nation began with the attempted genocide of
Indigenous people and the theft of their land.  American wealth was
built on the labor of kidnapped and enslaved Africans and their
descendants.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dispute these facts, or even the existence of facts themselves, then
any discussion about the content of this book or any other book is
futile unless the differences between your worldview and mine are taken
into account.  This article from the peer-reviewed journal “Systems” in
2018 is a good place to start:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/systems6030027&quot;&gt;A Systematic Framework for Exploring Worldviews and Its Generalization as a Multi-Purpose Inquiry Framework&lt;/a&gt;.
My epistemological worldview disclosure: I believe the scientific method
can progressively reveal the truth about all real phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
While implicit bias is always at play because all humans have bias,
inequity can occur simply through homogeneity; if I am not aware of the
barriers you face, then I won't see them, much less be motivated to
remove them.  Nor will I be motivated to remove the barriers if they
provide an advantage to which I feel entitled.


&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most succinct business case for a diverse workforce I have
personally ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-the-challenges-of-talking-to-white-people-about-racism&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: The Challenges of Talking to White People About Racism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White people need to be comfortable being seen as white. Racially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
In fact, when we try to talk openly and honestly about race, white
fragility quickly emerges as we are so often met with silence,
defensiveness, argumentation, certitude, and other forms of pushback.
These are not natural responses; they are social forces that prevent us
from attaining the racial knowledge we need to engage more productively,
and they function powerfully to hold the racial hierarchy in place.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, if you react in any of the above ways when talking about
whiteness, and what it means to be white, or blackness and what it means
to be black, you are showing white fragility.  Another term she uses is
“racial stamina”.  This is the ability to &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; react that way.  In my
opinion, the use of the term “stamina” is a nod to how even the most
racially aware white person must always exert effort to not react with
white fragility because of how thoroughly the social construct of race
is unavoidably encoded in civilizations thus far, including the one in
which I was raised and continue to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She calls out two key western ideologies which hinder white people’s
understanding of race.  I had trouble understanding this.  I probably
won’t capture it well, so read the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;individualism&quot;&gt;Individualism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Individualism is a story line that creates, communicates, reproduces,
and reinforces the concept that each of us is a unique individual and
that our group memberships, such as race, class, or gender, are
irrelevant to our opportunities.  Individualism claims that there are no
intrinsic barriers to individual success and that failure is not a
consequence of social structures but comes from individual
character...On some level, we know that Bill Gates's son was born into a
set of opportunities that will benefit him throughout his life, whether
he is mediocre or exceptional.  Yet even though Gates's son has clearly
been handed unearned advantage, we cling tightly to the ideology of
individualism when asked to consider our own unearned advantages.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cardinal rule of individualism is: don’t generalize, yet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;As a sociologist, I am quite comfortable generalizing; social life is
patterned and predictable in measurable ways.  But I understand my
generalizations may cause some defensiveness for the white people about
whom I am generalizing, given how cherished the ideology of
individualism is in our culture.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, if you think you’re special, you’re really not.  You are
completely formed by the system you grew up in and continue to live
in. Y’all ain’t that special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;objectivity&quot;&gt;Objectivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Aside: The Objectivity of Subjectivity scene from
&lt;a href=&quot;http://quietube7.com/v.php/http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X5cQcmAtjJ0&quot;&gt;Love and Death&lt;/a&gt; covers
objectivity also.  Yes, Woody Allen is implicated in #MeToo, but
Diane Keaton is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.refinery29.com/en-us/2018/09/210100/woody-allen-me-too-timeline#slide-4&quot;&gt;quoted here&lt;/a&gt;
supporting him.   It’s still a funny movie.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because individualism is a lie, you really can’t be objective, because
everything you observe is from your group perspective.  Stick with me
here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Rather than use what you see as unique about yourself as an exemption
from further examination, a more fruitful approach would be to ask
yourself, &quot;I am white and I have had X experience.  How did X shape me
as a result of *also being white?*&quot;  Setting aside your uniqueness is
a critical skill that will allow you to see the big picture of the
society in which we live; individualism will not.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;we-have-a-simplistic-understanding-of-racism&quot;&gt;We Have a Simplistic Understanding of Racism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now she gets to the problem with how white people define racism.  If you
take one thing away from this blog post, it’s this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
The final challenge we need to address is our definition of &quot;racist.&quot;
In the post-civil rights era, we have been taught that racists are mean
people who intentionally dislike others because of their race; racists
are immoral.  Therefore, if I am saying that my readers are racist or,
even worse, that all white people are racist, I am saying something
deeply offensive; I am questioning my readers' very moral character.
How can I make this claim when I don't even know my readers?  Many of
you have friends and loved ones of color, so how can you be racist?  In
fact, since it's racist to generalize about people according to race, I
am the one being racist!  So let me be clear: If your definition of a
racist is someone who holds conscious dislike of people because of race,
then I agree that it is offensive for me to suggest that you are racist
when I don't know you.  I also agree that if this is your definition of
racism, and you are against racism, then you are not racist....I am not
using this definition of racism, and I am not saying you are immoral.
If you can remain open as I lay out my argument, it should soon begin to
make sense.

In light of the challenges raised here, I expect that white readers will
have moments of discomfort reading this book.  This feeling may be a
sign that I've managed to unsettle the racial status quo, which is my
goal.  The racial status quo is comfortable for white people, and we
will not move forward in race relations if we remain comfortable.  The
key to moving forward is what we do with our discomfort.  We can use it
as a door out -- blame the messenger and disregard the message.  Or we
can use it as a door in by asking, Why does this unsettle me?  What
would it mean for me if this were true?

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-racism-and-white-supremacy&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: Racism and White Supremacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of being seen as white.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
[the American ideal is] once new immigrants learn English and adapt to 
American culture and customs, they become Americans.  In reality, only 
European immigrants were allowed to melt, or assimilate into dominant culture in 
the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, because...these immigrants were
perceived to be white and thus could belong.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Race and class&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
The poor and working classes, if united across race, could be a powerful
force.  But racial divisions have served to keep them from organizing
against the owning class who profits from their labor.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;racism&quot;&gt;Racism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand racism, distinguish it from prejudice and discrimination.
Prejudice: all humans have it.  It is unavoidable.  It is part of
cognition, so it is a mistake to call it bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discrimination is action based on prejudice.  Emphasis mine.  But here’s
the first occurrence of a succinct definition in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Prejudice always manifests itself in action because the way I see the
world drives my actions in the world.  Everyone has prejudice, and
everyone discriminates.  Given this reality, inserting the qualifier
&quot;reverse&quot; is nonsensical.

When a racial group's collective prejudice is backed by the power of
legal authority and institutional control, it is transformed into
racism, **a far-reaching system that functions independently from the
intentions or self-images of individual actors.**

...


People of color may also hold prejudices and discriminate against white
people, but they lack the social and institutional power that transforms
their prejudice and discrimination into racism; the impact of their
prejudice on whites is temporary and contextual.  Whites hold the social
and institutional positions in society to infuse their racial prejudice
into the laws, policies, practices, and norms of society in a way that
people of color do not.  A person of color may refuse to wait on me if I
enter a shop, but people of color cannot pass legislation that prohibits
me and everyone like me from buying a home in a certain neighborhood.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I can finally summarize her definition of being a racist: &lt;strong&gt;a
racist is someone who has been shaped by a racist system.&lt;/strong&gt;  You can see
a video with Ms. DiAngelo at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tolerance.org/magazine/summer-2019/whats-my-complicity-talking-white-fragility-with-robin-diangelo&quot;&gt;tolerance.org&lt;/a&gt;.
At 21:38 in that video she gives that definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accept this definition, and I acknowledge that by this definition I am
a racist.  Let me illustrate with a concrete personal example.  Richard
Rothstein’s 2017 book &lt;em&gt;The Color of Law&lt;/em&gt; examines the racial aspects of
federal lending and housing policies (including those of the Trump
family).  The house I grew up in was financed by a mortgage whose rate
was not accessible unless you were white.  So, in addition to all the
other ways in which I have been shaped by a racist system, this one very
concrete way is quantifiable and indisputable.  If you want learn more
about the housing aspects of racism, listen to this
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2017/05/03/526655831/a-forgotten-history-of-how-the-u-s-government-segregated-america&quot;&gt;interview with Richard Rothstein&lt;/a&gt;.
I like focusing on this aspect because it is factually defensible
(again, my epistemological worldview showing up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Racism is a society-wide dynamic that occurs at the group level.  When I
say that only whites can be racist, I mean that in the United States,
only whites have the collective social and institutional power and
privilege over people of color.  People of color do not have this power
and privilege over white people.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whiteness-as-a-position-of-status&quot;&gt;Whiteness as a Position of Status&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Whiteness rests upon a foundational premise: the definition of whites as
the norm or standard for human, and people of color as a deviation from
that norm.  Whiteness is not acknowledged by white people, and the white
reference point is assumed to be universal and is imposed on everyone.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;white-supremacy&quot;&gt;White Supremacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Race scholars use the term *white supremacy* to describe a
sociopolitical economic system of domination based on racial categories
that benefits those defined and perceived as white.  This system of
structural power privileges, centralizes, and elevates white people as a
group.  If, for example, we look at the racial breakdown of the people
who control our institutions, we see telling numbers in 2016-2017:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bullet list of people in power, with percentages that are white&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who doesn’t like trying to get to the root cause of problems?  I’ve long
fingered Republican strategist Lee Atwater as at least close to the root
cause for a lot of the problems I see.  Ms. DiAngelo does as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
In a 1981 interview, Lee Atwater, Republican political strategist and
adviser to presidents Ronald Reagan and George H. W. Bush, explained
what came to be known as &quot;the Southern strategy&quot; -- how to appeal to the
racism of white Southern voters without pronouncing it openly:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lee Atwater explains the Southern Strategy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Atwater is explaining more than the Southern strategy.  He is
explaining the birth of the good/bad binary.  This sociolinguistic
construct is what has enabled racism to continue to thrive and grow
since the civil rights era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-the-goodbad-binary&quot;&gt;Chapter 5 The Good/Bad Binary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
This chapter explores what is perhaps the most effective adaptation of
racism in recent history: the good/bad binary.  Prior to the civil
rights movement, it was socially acceptable for white people to openly
proclaim their belief in their racial superiority.  But when white
Northerners saw the violence black people--including women and
children--endured during the civil rights protests, they were appalled.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside: The reason they saw this, and were appropriately appalled, was
broadcast TV.  Not cable TV.  Not hyper-personalized Internet TV.
Broadcast TV.  Curated and, yes, censored by the FCC.  But it was still
very much seen as “the people’s airwaves”.  The media during the civil
rights era was not nearly so effectively monetized as it is now.  If we
had today’s media landscape during the civil rights era, none of the
civil rights era would have happened.  The people that were “appalled”
as Ms. DiAngelo says above wouldn’t have even seen the content because
networks like Fox News would not be able to air it for fear of
alienating their audience, and thus, their sponsors.  As it happened
many of those Northerners got on busses and joined in the marches, and
took the punches, and ended up in jail as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in how the media got so messed up as it is today,
where it is seen as an “enemy of the people” by many Americans, please
study
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wnet/americanmasters/education/lesson39_organizer1.html&quot;&gt;Edward R. Murrow’s speech&lt;/a&gt;
from the 1958 Radio-Television News Directors Association conference on
1958-10-15.  Of course, the media are not the enemy of the people, but
because they are so effectively monetized by playing on the very worst
of human nature, it is very easy to find examples that justify that
fascist analysis of the (still) free press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, back to the 60s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
...In other words, racists were mean, ignorant, old, uneducated, Southern
whites.  Nice people, well-intended, open-minded, middle-class people,
people raised in the &quot;enlightened North,&quot; could not be racist.


&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Good/Bad binary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
...The good/bad binary made it effectively impossible for the average
white person to understand--much lest interrupt--racism.

...The good/bad frame is a false dichotomy.  All people hold prejudices,
especially across racial lines in a society deeply divided by race.  I
can be told that everyone is equal by my parents, I can have friends of
color, and I may not tell racist jokes.  Yet I am still affected by the
forces of racism as a member of a society in which racism is the
bedrock.  I will still be seen as white, treated as white, and
experience life as a white person.

...if, as a white person, I conceptualize racism as a binary and I place
myself on the &quot;not racist&quot; side, what further action is required of me?
No action is required because I am not a racist.  Therefore racism is
not my problem; it doesn't concern me and there is nothing further I
need to do.  This worldview guarantees that I will not build my skills
in thinking critically about racism or use my position to challenge
racial inequality.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep.  I was that way until I read this book.  I guess that means I’m
woke?  But, really, I’m still that way.  But now I know that I need to
constantly try to interrupt racism whenever I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good/bad binary protects the racial status quo.  Ms. DiAngelo offers
some statements that flow from the good/bad binary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Color-blind statements insist that people do not see race, or if they see
it, it has no meaning to them.  Color-blind claims include the following:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Color-blind claims&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
The second I term *color-celebrate*.  This set claims that the person
sees and embraces racial differences.  Color-celebrate claims include
statements such as these:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Color-celebrate claims image 01&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Color-celebrate claims image 02&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. DiAngelo states that she’s heard all of these claims in her work at
teaching tolerance.  I believe her.  I’ve heard them myself, and if I interrupt racism, 
I’ll hear them a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
The question is *not* is &quot;Is this claim true, or is it false?&quot;; we will
never come to an agreement on a question that sets up an either/or
dichotomy on something as sensitive as racism.  Instead I ask, &quot;How does
this claim function in the conversation?&quot;...[color-blind and color-celebrate claims]
all exempt the person
from any responsibility for or participation in the problem.  They take
race off the table, and close (rather than open) any further
exploration.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-anti-blackness&quot;&gt;Chapter 6 Anti-Blackness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to highlight Ms. DiAngelo’s treatment of affirmative action.
Rage against affirmative action is so closely entwined with
Republicanism (I won’t say conservatism because conservatism is about as precise a term as antifa at
this point) that I smiled when I saw this important topic was about to
get the DiAngelo treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
There is a great amount of misinformation about affirmative action, as
evidenced in the idea of special rights.  For example, people commonly
believe that if a person of color applies for a position, he or she must
be hired over a white person; that black people are given preferential
treatment in hiring; and that a specific number of people must be hired
to fill a quota.  All these beliefs are patently untrue.  Affirmative
action is a tool to ensure that *qualified* minority applicants are
given the same employment opportunities as while people.  It is a
flexible program --there are no quotas or requirements as commonly
understood...No employer is required to hire an unqualified person of
color, but companies are required to be able to articulate why they
didn't hire a qualified person of color...

Still, this program has been systematically chipped away at, and several
states have eliminated affirmative action programs altogether.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-7-racial-triggers-for-white-people&quot;&gt;Chapter 7 Racial Triggers for White People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you thought only liberal snowflake SJWs could be
“&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolling_coal&quot;&gt;triggered&lt;/a&gt;”?  Turns out
no!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
When ideologies such as color blindness, meritocracy, and individualism
are challenged, intense emotional reactions are common.  I have
discussed several reasons why whites are so defensive about the
suggestion that we benefit from, and are complicit in, a racist system:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Triggers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now she finally answers the question, “what can we do about it?”.
She calls it interrupting racism (FWIW, I prefer racism interrupted).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
These interruptions can take a variety of forms and come from a range of
sources, including:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;interruptions 01&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;interruptions 02&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
When disequilibrium occurs--when there is an interruption to that which
is familiar and taken for granted--white fragility restores equilibrium
and returns the capital &quot;lost&quot; via the challenge...Again these
strategies are reflexive and seldom conscious, but that does not make
them benign

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the sense here that this strategy of interruption can be used in
other contexts than racism.  There’s probably a playbook somewhere of
how to abuse this strategy to manipulate someone.  Perhaps this is
something master gas-lighters instinctively know how to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-8-the-result-white-fragility&quot;&gt;Chapter 8 The Result: White Fragility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
If we become adults who explicitly oppose racism, as do many, we often
organize our identity around a denial of our racially based privileges
that reinforce racist disadvantage for others.  What is particularly
problematic about this contradiction is that white people's moral
objection to racism increases their resistance to acknowledging their
complicity with it.

...

Let me be clear: while the capacity for white people to sustain
challenges to our racial positions is limited--and, in this way,
fragile--the effects of our responses are not fragile at all; they are
quite powerful and because they take advantage of historical and
institutional power and control.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-9-white-fragility-in-action&quot;&gt;Chapter 9 White Fragility in Action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Ms. DiAngelo recounts stories from her work teaching
corporate tolerance classes and shows how the concepts explained in the
preceding chapters play out.  The feelings, claims, triggers,
assumptions, and interruptions can be seen in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-12-where-do-we-go-from-here&quot;&gt;Chapter 12 Where Do We Go From Here?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point, the reader should know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The good/bad binary enables a definition of racism that actually
allows racism to continue unchallenged (evil brilliance, isn’t it?).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A more helpful (and Christ-like) definition is.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;When a racial group’s collective prejudice is backed by the power of
 legal authority and institutional control, it is transformed into
 racism, &lt;strong&gt;a far-reaching system that functions independently from the
 intentions or self-images of individual actors.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;White fragility is what happens when white people who use the
good/bad binary definition of racism are challenged to change their
definition to the more helpful definition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At long last, chapter 12 gave me hope by really showing me, “hey, I can
do this” and “hey, this is really worth doing.”  I hope you end up with
the same feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
However, from a transformed paradigm, when we are given feedback on our
inevitable but unaware racist patterns, we might have very different
feelings:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;More helpful feelings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
When we have these feelings, we might want to engage in the following
behaviors:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;More helpful behaviors&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
What claims might we make when we have these feelings and engage in
these behaviors?  Notice that none of the following claims characterize
us as falsely accused or as beyond the discussion; these claims suggest
openness and humility.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Helpful claims&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
...When our fundamental understanding of racism is transformed, so are
our assumptions and resultant behaviors.  Imagine the difference in our
environment, interactions, norms, and policies if the following list
described our assumptions.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;More helpful assumptions 01&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;More helpful assumptions 02&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
These assumptions might interrupt racism in various ways, such as the
following:

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20200604-white-fragility-highlights-15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;More helpful interruptions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with the hook I set at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the importance of taking action to combat “the apathy of
whiteness” Ms. DiAngelo asks the reader to engage in this thought
experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Imagine you go to the doctor, who tells you that you have an acoustic
neuroma.  Just as she is about to explain what this is and what your
options are, she gets an emergency call and must rush off, abruptly
ending your visit.  What would you do?  You would very likely go home,
get on the internet, and read everything you could find on the
subject...Bottom line: you would care enough to get informed.  So
consider racism a matter of life and death (as it is for people of
color), and do your homework.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t start doing my homework until I was 48 years old.  I’m ashamed
it took me that long.  On the other hand, it’s never too late to start.
If you got this far, you have made a great start on doing your homework.
Thanks very much.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cross posted at LinkedIn, if that’s your thing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flow for developing regular expressions (regex) of moderate complexity</title><link href="/blog/2020/01/29/regex-development-flow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flow for developing regular expressions (regex) of moderate complexity" /><published>2020-01-29T10:40:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T10:40:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/01/29/regex-development-flow</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/01/29/regex-development-flow.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had to add a feature to the UI for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://azuremarketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/apps?search=weblogic%2012.2.1.3&amp;amp;page=1&quot;&gt;Azure Marketplace
Offers for Oracle WebLogic
Server&lt;/a&gt;.
The UI for marketplace entries is written in JSON.  As I stated in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/blog/2020/01/25/arm-development-faster-iteration-time.html&quot;&gt;my
previous post&lt;/a&gt;, JSON is an awful
choice for a DSL for deploying things to Azure.  It is also an awful
choice for declaring a wizard-style UI, but at least the particular use case of &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-resource-manager/managed-applications/create-uidefinition-overview&quot;&gt;building the UI for an Azure Marketplace offer&lt;/a&gt; allows easy &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-resource-manager/managed-applications/microsoft-common-textbox#remarks&quot;&gt;incorporation of regular expressions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post shows a technique for iteratively developing a moderately
complex regular expression (regex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I want a regex that validates that a string is a comma
separated list of numbers or hyphen separated numbers.  The list must
have no whitespace and not have a trailing comma.  For example,
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;80,443,7001,7002,8000-8100&lt;/code&gt; is valid while
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;80,443,7001,7002,8000-8100,&lt;/code&gt; is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler: here is the final regex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;^((([0-9]+-[0-9]+)|([0-9]+))[,]?)+[^,]$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I developed this moderately complex regex using this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://regexr.com/&quot;&gt;https://regexr.com/&lt;/a&gt; to iteratively develop.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write an English language statement of the regex: “I want a regex
that validates that a string is a comma separated list of numbers or
hyphen separated numbers.  The list must have no whitespace and not have
a trailing comma.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decompose the English into its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;a. no whitespace&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;b. numbers&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;c. hyphen separated numbers&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;d. comma separated list&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;e. not have a trailing comma&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write a regex for each part.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;a. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;no whitespace&lt;/code&gt;.  You get this for free with regex by not putting
   any whitespace in the regex.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;b. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;numbers&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;^([0-9]+)$&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;c. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hyphen separated numbers&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;^([0-9]+-[0-9]+)$&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;d. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;comma separated list&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;^((.*)[,]?)+$&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;e. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;not have a trailing comma&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;^(.*)[^,]$&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Combine the parts in a way that works.  Here it was vitally important to make correct use of 
parenthesis (“capturing groups” in regex lingo), and the “or” operator &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Using the parts above, a pseudo regex looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;^(((c.)|(b.))d.)d.'e$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I used “d.” and “d.’” (d and d prime) in my pseudo regex because the
comma separated list needed to be expressed that way.  Also note that
“a.” is met by the absence of any whitespace in the regex, so it is
not present in the regex itself.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Carefully making the necessary substitutions, the following
unreadable mess is a regex that matches a bunch of number ranges or
numbers, separated by commas, disallowing a trailing comma.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;^((([0-9]+-[0-9]+)|([0-9]+))[,]?)+[^,]$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This expression successfully validates strings like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;80,443,7001,7002,8000-8100&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a moderately complex regular expression is easier when you break it down and iteratively develop each part using &lt;a href=&quot;https://regexr.com/&quot;&gt;https://regexr.com/&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gskinner_team&quot;&gt;gskinner&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;addendum&quot;&gt;Addendum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need your regexs as part of an azure &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;createUiDefinition.json&lt;/code&gt;,
save time by testing the whole thing using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/?feature.customPortal=false#blade/Microsoft_Azure_CreateUIDef/SandboxBlade&quot;&gt;Create UI Definition
Sandbox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently had to add a feature to the UI for the Azure Marketplace Offers for Oracle WebLogic Server. The UI for marketplace entries is written in JSON. As I stated in my previous post, JSON is an awful choice for a DSL for deploying things to Azure. It is also an awful choice for declaring a wizard-style UI, but at least the particular use case of building the UI for an Azure Marketplace offer allows easy incorporation of regular expressions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tips for faster iteration times developing ARM templates</title><link href="/blog/2020/01/25/arm-development-faster-iteration-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tips for faster iteration times developing ARM templates" /><published>2020-01-25T14:40:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T14:40:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/01/25/arm-development-faster-iteration-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/01/25/arm-development-faster-iteration-time.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-2020-01-30-export-with-httpsresourcesazurecom&quot;&gt;UPDATE: 2020-01-30 export with https://resources.azure.com/&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you found your way to this post and your first reaction is 
“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Thank%20you%20Captain%20Obvious&quot;&gt;well duh&lt;/a&gt;”,
please leave a comment, because I’d love to know how you came upon your
knowledge which caused you to respond this way.  This was hard-won knowledge
for me, but I suspect I’m missing out on some fundamental bit of
training in the art of efficient ARM template development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ARM template encodes instructions that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-resource-manager/management/&quot;&gt;Azure Resource
Manager&lt;/a&gt;
executes which result in some stuff being deployed to Azure.  As such,
an ARM template is a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-specific_language&quot;&gt;DSL&lt;/a&gt; for the
domain of Azure.  Unfortunately, as DSLs go, it’s awful.  It’s a bigass
JSON file, with all of the pitfalls that entails, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a challenge to manage complexity.  Things can spiral out of
control very quickly unless you are very disciplined while authoring.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The instructions in an ARM template execute over time, in a sequence,
imperatively, but JSON is absolutely not an imperative syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s very easy to make stupid mistakes at authoring time.  You can
opt-in to using &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-resource-manager/templates/use-vs-code-to-create-template&quot;&gt;some
tooling&lt;/a&gt;
to catch some stupid mistakes at authoring time, but a proper DSL
would do a better job of it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;You &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Azure/azure-resource-manager-schemas/issues/851&quot;&gt;can’t even put comments in there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/del&gt; UPDATE: 2020-04-21: // comments in JSON work now.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a DSL for Azure, I think Terraform may be a better fit.  Indeed
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/terraform/terraform-overview&quot;&gt;Terraform is well supported by
Azure&lt;/a&gt;,
but you can’t use it when authoring for the Azure marketplace.  Accept
JSON and move on.  Here are some tips to ease your acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accept-json&quot;&gt;Accept JSON&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post shares some tips I’ve developed to get faster development
cycle times when iteratively developing ARM templates.  The cycle looks
like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mainTemplate.json&lt;/code&gt; somehow.  Write it yourself, export it
from the Azure portal, start with a quickstart, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deploy it to Azure with the Azure CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Look at what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to minimize the time between steps 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tips-for-step-1&quot;&gt;Tips for step 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-the-export-template-feature-as-a-jump-start&quot;&gt;Use the “export template” feature as a jump start&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create the system you want to have in the portal, then use the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-resource-manager/templates/export-template-portal&quot;&gt;export template&lt;/a&gt; 
feature of the portal to download the ARM template JSON file.  You may
want to do this for each big chunk of functionality in your system, then
stitch them together.  Iterate at the command line using the technique
in the next tip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-the-resourcesazurecom&quot;&gt;Use the resources.azure.com&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have observed that the “export template” feature does not always give
you the full JSON.  For example, in the case of Application Gateway, the
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;backendAddresses&lt;/code&gt; was empty, even though it had a pool and targets.  A
colleague pointed out this enormously useful resource
&lt;a href=&quot;https://resources.azure.com/&quot;&gt;https://resources.azure.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a quick sketch of how I used it to get the full JSON of a
deployed Application Gateway.  Note, this is not an ARM template, but it
can help a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visit https://resources.azure.com/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Type in the resource group in which the resource is deployed: ejb012803c&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe make a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;a. If offered with an autosuggest, pick the resource and you are done.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;b. If not offered with an autosuggest.  In the left pane, expand nodes like this&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;subscriptions &amp;gt; Your subscription &amp;gt; resourceGroups &amp;gt; ejb012803c &amp;gt; Providers &amp;gt;
  Microsoft.Network &amp;gt; applicationGateways &amp;gt; ejb012803c
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;start-with-one-of-the-templates-from-azure-quickstart-templates&quot;&gt;Start with one of the templates from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;azure-quickstart-templates&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My extremely helpful colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bmoore-msft&quot;&gt;Brian
Moore&lt;/a&gt; leads a team that curates this
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Azure/azure-quickstart-templates&quot;&gt;vast resource of
templates&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Azure/azure-quickstart-templates/tree/master/test/arm-ttk&quot;&gt;tests for
templates&lt;/a&gt;.
The templates are organized by the kind of thing you want to deploy to
Azure.  For example, here is one for &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Azure/azure-quickstart-templates/tree/master/101-application-gateway-waf&quot;&gt;Azure Application
Gateway&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tips-for-step-2&quot;&gt;Tips for step 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;always-use-the---debug-argument-to-commands-for-which-you-need-to-iterate--like-this&quot;&gt;Always use the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--debug&lt;/code&gt; argument to commands for which you need to iterate.  Like this&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;az group deployment create --debug --resource-group ejb012405c --parameters @20200124-dd-1052162-gateway-parameters.json --template-file arm-oraclelinux-wls-cluster/arm-oraclelinux-wls-cluster/src/main/arm/mainTemplate.json &amp;gt; azure.out 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also causes the output to be redirected to a file, in the
background, capturing stdout and stderr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-tale-of-two-tails&quot;&gt;A tale of two tails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use some tails to observe the output as the command runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grep through the outfile for some low frequency string.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tail -f azure.out | grep &quot;INFO: Accepted&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a separate terminal window, just tail the output for everything,
so you can see if the command simply failed.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tail -f azure.out
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extract-the-properties-template--json-object-from-azureout-so-you-can-interpret-column-offsets-correctly&quot;&gt;Extract the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{&quot;properties&quot;: {&quot;template&quot;: &lt;/code&gt; JSON object from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;azure.out&lt;/code&gt;, so you can interpret column offsets correctly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The template you pass to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;az group deployment create&lt;/code&gt; will have all
formatting removed before Azure sees it, so when Azure gives you error
messages, they are usually expressed like “error on line 1 column
60299”.  You need to translate that to “line N” in your human readable
JSON.  If you save aside the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{&quot;properties&quot;: {&quot;template&quot;: &lt;/code&gt; JSON object
from the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;azure.out&lt;/code&gt; file, you can seek to that column, and then derive
where the error is in your human readable JSON file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;even-though-you-ultimately-need-to-produce-maintemplatejson-iterate-with-smaller-disjoint-files&quot;&gt;Even though you ultimately need to produce &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mainTemplate.json&lt;/code&gt; iterate with smaller, disjoint files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are building a template that ultimately deploys an entire
datacenter, such as with an &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/marketplace/marketplace-solution-templates&quot;&gt;Azure
Application&lt;/a&gt;
you should consider breaking the template into smaller nested templates,
as described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-resource-manager/templates/linked-templates&quot;&gt;Using linked and nested templates when deploying Azure
resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing ARM templates can be very frustrating, especilaly if you are
used to the rapid compile-edit-debug cycle that many actual programming
languages offer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">UPDATE: 2020-01-30 export with https://resources.azure.com/</summary></entry></feed>