<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-09T17:09:11-04:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ed Burns Blog</title><subtitle>Ed Burns blogs here, mostly about Java and software, but sometimes about other random things.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Java EE in Azure Marketplace: What’s Currently Available?</title><link href="/blog/2019/07/07/wls-azure-marketplace.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Java EE in Azure Marketplace: What's Currently Available?" /><published>2019-07-07T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-07T12:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/07/07/wls-azure-marketplace</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/07/07/wls-azure-marketplace.html">&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/05/23/joining-microsoft.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I joined Microsoft “to
enable Java EE developers on Azure.”  The team I joined at Microsoft has
already been working on this goal for some time, so naturally I need to
take stock of the current offerings, whatever they may be.  As African
American tennis great Arthur Ashe said, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/arthur_ashe_371527&quot;&gt;Start where you are. Use what
you have. Do what you
can.&lt;/a&gt;” It turns
out there is an existing template in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://azuremarketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/&quot;&gt;Azure
Marketplace&lt;/a&gt;
for &lt;a href=&quot;https://azuremarketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/apps/Oracle.OracleWebLogicServer12cEnterprise?tab=Overview&quot;&gt;Oracle WebLogic Server
12.1.2&lt;/a&gt;.
Now, this is admittedly ancient, supporting only Java EE 6 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/middleware/1212/wls/NOTES/whatsnew.htm#BGGGHCJD&quot;&gt;Servlet
3.0, JSF 2.1, CDI 1.0,
etc&lt;/a&gt;).
Microsoft will be doing &lt;strong&gt;much&lt;/strong&gt; better than this very soon, but this post
documents how to get WLS 12.1.2 up and running on Azure as it stands
today.  This post will show how to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a VM for WLS 12.1.2 from the existing Azure Marketplace
template provided by Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expose the necessary network ports.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SSH into the machine and create the WLS domain.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start the WLS server.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access the WLS console from the public Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use the console to deploy a simple &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.war&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Validate the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.war&lt;/code&gt; works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shut down the server.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;De-allocate the Azure resources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-and-configuring-the-iaas-vm-within-the-azure-portal&quot;&gt;Creating and Configuring the IaaS VM Within the Azure Portal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- use H4 because it's smaller --&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-log-in-to-the-portal&quot;&gt;1. Log in to the portal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/&quot;&gt;portal.azure.com&lt;/a&gt; and either sign
up or log in.  This is your portal to all of the features of Azure to
which you have a subscription.  Everything you do within Azure
happens within a subscription.  If you are just getting started, you
can get a free trial subscription with &lt;a href=&quot;https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/dev-essentials/&quot;&gt;Visual Studio Dev
Essentials&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-filter-to-your-subscription&quot;&gt;2. Filter to your subscription&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to have multiple subscriptions within your Azure
account.  If your Azure account is associated with multiple
subscriptions, you’ll need to adjust the portal so it only takes
action on resources within that subscription.  Use this this control
to apply the filter.  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-subscription-filter.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Azure subscription filter&quot; title=&quot;Azure subscription filter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-create-a-resource-group&quot;&gt;3. Create a resource group&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left side of the Azure portal is a handy parking lot for actions
you can take.  It’s kinda like the dock in macOS or the task bar in
Windows.  Let’s create a “Resource Group”.  You can think of a
“Resource Group” as a box for grouping related Azure things together.
In this post, we’ll create a resource group to hold our WLS 12.1.2
related resources.  Click the “Resource Groups” icon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-resource-group-icon.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Resource Group
Icon&quot; title=&quot;Resource Group Icon&quot; /&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the “+ Add” button at the top.  Fill in “Resource group with a
descriptive name.  Such as “20190707-wls1212”.  Leave “Subscription” and
“Region” as default, as shown here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-resource-group-pane.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Azure subscription filter&quot; title=&quot;Azure subscription
filter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click “Review + Create”, then “Create”.  You will see a “Resource Group
Created” notification, which will quickly disappear.  You can get this
and all other notifications back by clicking on the “bell” icon, next to
the “Filter your subscription” icon you clicked on in step 2.  Do this
now and you’ll see something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-resource-group-created.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Resource Group Created&quot; title=&quot;Resource Group Created&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the “Go to resource group”.  Take some time to play around with
the resource group view.  As we create things, they will show up here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-create-the-weblogic-1212-service&quot;&gt;4. Create the WebLogic 12.1.2 Service&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the friendly green plus icon at the top of the left navigation
pane.  This will expose the “Azure Marketplace”, a huge library of
things that run on Azure.  Eventually there will be more Java EE related
things in here, but for now place the cursor in the “Search the
Marketplace” box and type &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Oracle WebLogic Server 12.1.2&lt;/code&gt; and press
Enter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;wls1212&quot; title=&quot;wls1212&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the covers, this is an Azure Resource Manager (ARM) template,
created by Oracle and inserted into the Azure Marketplace way back
in 2013.  You can create your own ARM templates.  Check out my colleague Rick Claus’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://regularitguy.com/2016/06/06/how-to-create-an-azure-resource-manager-arm-template-from-scratch/&quot;&gt;blog about ARM templates&lt;/a&gt; for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-create-a-virtual-machine&quot;&gt;A. Create a Virtual Machine&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fill in this form with the following values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource group&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;The resource group you created in step 3.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtual Machine Name&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;The same as the resource group.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Administrator account&lt;/code&gt; section, change the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Authentication
type&lt;/code&gt; to be “Password”.  Set the values as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Username&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adminadmin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Password and Confirm Password&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;3hu6Lfomu4#&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally you can use whatever you like for password.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Inbound Port Rules&lt;/code&gt; section, leave “None” selected, we will
tune the rules later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click “Next: Disks &amp;gt;”.  This is important because the default is to
create the VM with expensive premium SSD disk.  This post is
optimized for cheapness, not speed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set the “OS disk type” to be “Standard HDD”.  Then click the “Review +
create”, then “Create”.  You will see “Your deployment is underway”.
This should only take a couple minutes to complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;b-tune-the-network-settings-to-allow-ssh-and-console-access&quot;&gt;B. Tune the Network Settings To Allow SSH and Console Access&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on “Resource Groups” then select the Resource group you created in
step 3.  This will show you the many different resources that were
created by the ARM template for WLS 12.1.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-resources.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;wls-1212-resources&quot; title=&quot;wls-1212-resources&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to allow SSH and WLS Console access.  Securing an Internet
facing resource is a huge and important topic, but far beyond the scope
of this simple blog post.  Just know that we are doing some things here
that almost certainly are not security best practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the items in the Resource group, click on the “Network security
group”, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;20190707-wls1212-nsg&lt;/code&gt;.  In the “Settings” section of the middle
pane, select “Inbound security rules”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-nsg.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Network Security Groups&quot; title=&quot;Network Security Groups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exposes the panel where we can customize the allowable network
connections &lt;strong&gt;into&lt;/strong&gt; the VM (known as “inbound” connections).  There is
an analogous panel for configuring network connections &lt;strong&gt;out&lt;/strong&gt; of the VM
(“outbound” connections).  You declare whether or not a particular
connection is allowed or dis-allowed by writing “rules”.  This exercise
is going to allow just enough to accomplish the goals of the blog post.
In the table below, rules can be added by clicking the “+ Add” button.
They can be edited by single clicking the row in the table.  When
adding or editing a rule make sure to scroll up and down to make sure
you haven’t missed any fields.  Before you add any rules, let’s examine
the pre-configured ones.  Note that the rows are sorted by increasing
priority.  When Azure detects an inbound connection to the VM, Azure
runs through each row of the inbound rules, in order of priority, to see
if the connection matches the rule.  If it does, the rule is applied and
traversal of the rule table stops.  If it does not, Azure keeps going
through the rows until either a match is found or the table ends.  Note
that Azure has pre-added a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DenyAllInbound&lt;/code&gt; rule with the lowest
priority.  This effectively means “if nothing else, deny the inbound
connection”.  Use the UI to make it so the rules look like the table
shown next.  The rows in the red box are the rows you need to add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-nsg-modified.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Desired Inbound Rules&quot; title=&quot;Desired Inbound Rules&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital Ocean has a great primer on networking terminology at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/understanding-ip-addresses-subnets-and-cidr-notation-for-networking&quot;&gt;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/understanding-ip-addresses-subnets-and-cidr-notation-for-networking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;c-optional-disable-the-auto-shutdown&quot;&gt;C. (Optional) Disable the Auto Shutdown&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nod to the U.S. Government’s National Institute of Standards
(NIST) offical definition of cloud computing (which &lt;a href=&quot;https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/Legacy/SP/nistspecialpublication800-145.pdf&quot;&gt;everyone should
read&lt;/a&gt;)
your VM is pre-configured to auto shut-down at 19:00 UTC.  To disable
this potentially inconvenient setting, go to the Resource Group, click
on the “Virtual machine” row, then type “Auto-shutdown” in the search
box and click on the “Auto-shutdown” hit, as shown in this diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-auto-shutdown.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;wls-1212-auto-shutdown&quot; title=&quot;wls-1212-auto-shutdown&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toggle the enabled to “Off”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-ssh-into-the-machine-to-complete-the-configuration&quot;&gt;5. SSH Into the Machine to Complete the Configuration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we enabled port 22 &lt;a href=&quot;#b-tune-the-network-settings-to-allow-ssh-and-console-access&quot;&gt;in step B
above&lt;/a&gt;, we
can SSH into the host, assuming we know it’s IP address.  This can be
discovered by going to the Resource Group, clicking on the “Virtual
machine” resource.  If you mouse over the IP address, shown in the red
box next, you will see a button that copies the IP address to the
clipboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-ip-address.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;IP Address&quot; title=&quot;IP Address&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a “Cloud Shell” by clicking on the “Cloud Shell” icon on the top
menu bar of the panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-cloud-shell.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Cloud Shell&quot; title=&quot;Cloud Shell&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tip: This action opens up a new shell at the bottom of the current
portal browser tab.  I prefer to have a full tab for the shell.  Click
on the “Open new session” button to get one.  You may close the bottom
shell if you like.  In the cloud shell, SSH into the machine as shown
next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-cloud-shell-02.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Cloud Shell&quot; title=&quot;Cloud Shell&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining actions are documented in more detail &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/middleware/1212/wls/WLAZU/toc.htm&quot;&gt;at
Oracle&lt;/a&gt;, but
that documentation references a version of the Azure console that has
long since ceased to be.  Therefore, this section will update that
content for the simple case of a single WLS domain node.  After doing
these steps, it should be simple to use the out-of-date Oracle
documentation to perform the more advanced configuration, such as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/middleware/1212/wls/WLAZU/toc.htm#CBABAADH&quot;&gt;Creating a Multi-Machine Virtual Network for WebLogic
Server&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-set-the-env-vars&quot;&gt;A. Set the ENV Vars&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Azure Cloud Shell, ensure the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adminadmin&lt;/code&gt; user owns the
necessary directories and files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo chown -R adminadmin /opt/oracle
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cat &amp;gt; wls-env.sh&lt;/code&gt; then paste the following lines, followed by
control-D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;export ORACLE_HOME=/opt/oracle/products/Middleware
export WL_HOME=/opt/oracle/products/Middleware/wlserver
export JAVA_HOME=/opt/oracle/products/jdk1.7.0_25
${WL_HOME}/common/derby/bin/startNetworkServer.sh || true
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;|| true&lt;/code&gt; causes the script to continue even if the Derby server
doesn’t start, for example because it’s already started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Execute the script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;. ./wls-env.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will set the necessary environment variables, and also start the
built-in Derby database.  This should cause someting like the following
to appear in the Azure Cloud Shell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mon Jul 08 15:06:33 EDT 2019 : Security manager installed using the Basic server security policy.
Mon Jul 08 15:06:34 EDT 2019 : Apache Derby Network Server - 10.8.2.2 -
(1181258) started and ready to accept connections on port 1527
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this port is not accessible to the public Internet because you
have not created an inbound rule for it.  It is, however, accessible
within the Virtual Network (vnet) created by the ARM template for Oracle
WLS 12.1.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;b-create-the-domain&quot;&gt;B. Create the Domain&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will modify the included &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;basicWLSDomain.py&lt;/code&gt; WLST script to make to
create a domain to which we can log in to the admin console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd /opt/oracle/products/Middleware/wlserver/common/templates/scripts/wlst
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This directory contains some built-in WebLogic Scripting Template (WLST)
scripts provided by Oracle.  Copy the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;basicWLSDomain.py&lt;/code&gt; so we can
safely edit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cp basicWLSDomain.py 20190709_basicWLSDomain.py
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the line with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;# Please set password here before using this script,
e.g. cmo.setPassword('value')&lt;/code&gt; and insert this line before it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cmo.setPassword('3hu6Lfomu4#&amp;amp;')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, you can use any password you like.  I’m using the same password as
earlier for convenience.  Save the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change to the directory containing the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wlst.sh&lt;/code&gt; tool and execute it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd /opt/oracle/products/Middleware/oracle_common/common/bin
./wlst.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the prompt, execute the script file you just edited:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;wls:/offline&amp;gt; execfile('/opt/oracle/products/Middleware/wlserver/common/templates/scripts/wlst/20190709_basicWLSDomain.py')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will cause
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/opt/oracle/products/Middleware/user_projects/domains/basicWLSDomain&lt;/code&gt;
to be created.  Append the following line to your existing
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/wls-env.sh&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nohup /opt/oracle/products/Middleware/user_projects/domains/basicWLSDomain/bin/startWebLogic.sh &amp;gt; ~/wls-log.txt &amp;amp; 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you examine the contents of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/wls-log.txt&lt;/code&gt; you should see it ends
with output similar to the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:54 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Security&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-090171&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Loading the identity certificate and private key stored under the alias DemoIdentity from the jks keystore file /opt/oracle/products/Middleware/user_projects/domains/basicWLSDomain/security/DemoIdentity.jks.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Security&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-090169&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Loading trusted certificates from the jks keystore file /opt/oracle/products/Middleware/wlserver/server/lib/DemoTrust.jks.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Security&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-090169&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Loading trusted certificates from the jks keystore file /opt/oracle/products/jdk1.7.0_25/jre/lib/security/cacerts.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;DefaultSecure[1]&quot; is now listening on fe80:0:0:0:20d:3aff:fe54:2fff:7002 for protocols iiops, t3s, ldaps, https.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;DefaultSecure[3]&quot; is now listening on 127.0.0.1:7002 for protocolsiiops, t3s, ldaps, https.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;Default[1]&quot; is now listening on fe80:0:0:0:20d:3aff:fe54:2fff:7001for protocols iiop, t3, ldap, snmp, http.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;DefaultSecure[2]&quot; is now listening on 0:0:0:0:0:0:0:1:7002 for protocols iiops, t3s, ldaps, https.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;Default&quot; is now listening on 10.0.2.4:7001 for protocols iiop, t3,ldap, snmp, http.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Warning&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002611&amp;gt; &amp;lt;The hostname &quot;localhost&quot;, maps to multiple IP addresses: 127.0.0.1, 0:0:0:0:0:0:0:1.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;DefaultSecure&quot; is now listening on 10.0.2.4:7002 for protocols iiops, t3s, ldaps, https.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;Default[3]&quot; is now listening on 127.0.0.1:7001 for protocols iiop,t3, ldap, snmp, http.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-002613&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Channel &quot;Default[2]&quot; is now listening on 0:0:0:0:0:0:0:1:7001 for protocolsiiop, t3, ldap, snmp, http.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:56 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;WebLogicServer&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-000331&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Started the WebLogic Server Administration Server &quot;AdminServer&quot; fordomain &quot;basicWLSDomain&quot; running in development mode.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:57 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;WebLogicServer&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-000365&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Server state changed to RUNNING.&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;Jul 9, 2019 11:28:57 AM EDT&amp;gt; &amp;lt;Notice&amp;gt; &amp;lt;WebLogicServer&amp;gt; &amp;lt;BEA-000360&amp;gt; &amp;lt;The server started in RUNNING mode.&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;access-the-admin-gui-to-deploy-a-java-ee-6-war&quot;&gt;Access the Admin GUI to deploy a Java EE 6 WAR.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you see the all important &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;The server started in RUNNING
mode.&lt;/code&gt;, you may safely exit the SSH shell, and, if desired, disable the
inbound rule for SSH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obtain the public IP address for the host as shown
&lt;a href=&quot;5-ssh-into-the-machine-to-complete-the-configuration&quot;&gt;earlier&lt;/a&gt; and log
in to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://&amp;lt;ip address&amp;gt;:7001/console&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everything worked correctly, you should see the following login UI.
I have filled in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;weblogic&lt;/code&gt; as the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Username&lt;/code&gt;, since this is what the
template uses.  Provide the pasword you used when you ran &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;execfile&lt;/code&gt; and
log in to the console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-console.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;WLS Console&quot; title=&quot;WLS Console&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-install-the-simplest-war-that-will-possibly-work&quot;&gt;1. Install the simplest WAR that will possibly work.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplicity, let’s install the simple guessNumber 2.0 war into the
running WLS 12.1.2.  You can download the war &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/jsf-guessNumber-2.0.war&quot;&gt;from this blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following steps will guide you to install the guessNumber war using
the WLS Admin GUI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click on “Deployments” in the “Domain Structure” panel on the left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click on “Install” as shown next.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-console-install-01.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;WLS Console&quot; title=&quot;WLS Console&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click on the hyperlink “upload your file(s)” and upload the
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jsf-guessNumber-2.0.war&lt;/code&gt;.  Click “Browse” and use the file chooser to
select the WAR.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click “Next”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the “Install Application Assistant”, ensure the
“jsf-guessNumber-2.0.war” is selected, and click “Next”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the “Choose targeting style” page, select “Install this deployment as an
application” and click “Next”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the “Optional Settings” page, click “Finish”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your console should have the following appearance, especially the green
text in the “Messages” section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190707-wls-1212-console-install-02.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;WLS Console&quot; title=&quot;WLS Console&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that we are installing the WAR into the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AdminServer&lt;/code&gt; target.  This
is not something one would normally do, but because the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;basicWLSDomain&lt;/code&gt;
is set up with just the one server by default, this is what we will use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-view-the-deployed-app&quot;&gt;2. View the Deployed App&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construct a URL based on the public IP and the context-root of the app.
For example, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://&amp;lt;ip address&amp;gt;:7001/jsf-guessNumber-2.0/&lt;/code&gt;.  Note that
the port is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;7001&lt;/code&gt;, not 8080.  This is because we installed the app in
the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AdminServer&lt;/code&gt; target.  If the deployment was successful, you should
see the simple GuessNumber JSF 2.0 app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-shut-down-the-wls-server&quot;&gt;3. Shut Down the WLS Server&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the “Domain Structure” browser, expand “Environment” and click “Servers”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the “Summary of Servers” panel, click the “Control” tab.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click the checkbox next to “AdminServer(admin)”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pull down the “Shutdown” dropdown and select “when work completes”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thiss will shut down the WLS server.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-shut-down-the-vm&quot;&gt;4. Shut down the VM&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back in the Azure portal click “Resource groups” and select the
Resource group you created to hold this demo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click on the “Virtual machine” type row.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click “Stop”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click “OK”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;5-optional-delete-the-resource-group&quot;&gt;5. (Optional) Delete the Resource group.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t need this server any more, or you want to start over and
try some other experiments, you can delete the entire Resource group
with one action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Azure console, click on Resource groups.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check the checkbox next to your Resource group, and click the ellipsis
at the right end of the row.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Choose “Delete Resource group”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a measure to prevent accidental deletion, you have to type the
Resource group name, then click “Delete”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will delete the VM, network, network rules, disk, and the resource
group itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is very old software, it’s running on the most modern
and flexible cloud environment in the world.  In this post we did the
following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a VM for WLS 12.1.2 from the existing Azure Marketplace
template provided by Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expose the necessary network ports.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SSH into the machine and create the WLS domain.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start the WLS server.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access the WLS console from the public Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use the console to deploy a simple &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.war&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Validate the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.war&lt;/code&gt; works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shut down the server.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;De-allocate the Azure resources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch this space, and the twitters account
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/edburns/&quot;&gt;@edburns&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reza_rahman&quot;&gt;@reza_rahman&lt;/a&gt;, for upcoming
announcments about Microsoft’s plans for Java EE on Azure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As mentioned in my previous post, I joined Microsoft “to enable Java EE developers on Azure.” The team I joined at Microsoft has already been working on this goal for some time, so naturally I need to take stock of the current offerings, whatever they may be. As African American tennis great Arthur Ashe said, “Start where you are. Use what you have. Do what you can.” It turns out there is an existing template in the Azure Marketplace for Oracle WebLogic Server 12.1.2. Now, this is admittedly ancient, supporting only Java EE 6 (Servlet 3.0, JSF 2.1, CDI 1.0, etc). Microsoft will be doing much better than this very soon, but this post documents how to get WLS 12.1.2 up and running on Azure as it stands today. This post will show how to do the following:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Joining Microsoft</title><link href="/blog/2019/05/23/joining-microsoft.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Joining Microsoft" /><published>2019-05-23T14:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T14:01:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/05/23/joining-microsoft</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/05/23/joining-microsoft.html">&lt;p&gt;I am so excited to be joining Microsoft as Principal Java Architect in
their Java Tooling and Experiences team.  I hope to help to make the
future Java on Azure, by establishing Azure as the preferred cloud for
all Java workloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been fortunate to have worked at Sun during their heyday, and I
recall from that time a great admiration for the way Microsoft focused
on developers (developers developers developers).  In particular, the
Project Rave/JavaStudio Creator effort was heavily influenced by
VisualBasic and its associated tooling.  I look forward to being a part
of that kind of company again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be working with my old pal and colleague Reza Rahman to enable
Java EE and Jakarta EE developers on Azure.  We’re hoping to also
support Microprofile as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a mountain of new stuff for me here, so if I’ve ever asked you
for technical help in the past, I will likely ask you again in the very near
future, and I’ll offer the same help in return, as best I can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am so excited to be joining Microsoft as Principal Java Architect in their Java Tooling and Experiences team. I hope to help to make the future Java on Azure, by establishing Azure as the preferred cloud for all Java workloads.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leaving Oracle</title><link href="/blog/2019/05/23/leaving-oracle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leaving Oracle" /><published>2019-05-23T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T14:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/05/23/leaving-oracle</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/05/23/leaving-oracle.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s still unreal to me that I’m writing this, but here it is.  After
over 22 years at Oracle (13 at Sun), I’m moving on to another company.
In my time at Oracle, I have had a chance to help shape technologies
that have had a positive impact on our industry and lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not into bragging, humble or otherwise, but I do want to call out a
few projects with which I am especially thankful to have been involved.
I am not going to name names for fear of leaving someone out, but I am
deeply thankful for all my friends who have helped me over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anything-to-do-with-jcp&quot;&gt;Anything to do with JCP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very glad for my chance to contribute to and validate the Java
Community Process (&lt;a href=&quot;https://jcp.org/&quot;&gt;JCP&lt;/a&gt;) as a demonstrably successful way to allow a broad
spectrum of contributors to practically influence the Java they use in
their own jobs.  Oracle practices a culture of diversity, and this is
one area where the practice was apparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most rewarding part of my career so far was working on JSF as part
of the JCP.  The technology we built, and the community we built around
it, is very special.  There have been many highpoints but one that
sticks out for me personally was the gathering at my house after
the JSFSummit in December 2008 in Orlando.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several other JCP specs that I’ve had the chance to work on,
including Servlet and Bean Validation.  Those have been very rewarding
as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conference-speaking&quot;&gt;Conference Speaking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had my first taste of conference speaking at JavaOne 2002, and my
&lt;a href=&quot;https://javaserverfaces.github.io/presentations/w-jax-keynote-de-en.pdf&quot;&gt;first keynote opportunity&lt;/a&gt;
in 2005.  Since then I’ve been very blessed to continue speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;book-opportunities&quot;&gt;Book Opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very grateful for the chance to co-author several books about Java
technologies.  Those opportunities were possible thanks to the awesome
community around Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nullpointers&quot;&gt;NullPointers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever seen my Rockstar talk, you know about my fondness for
Buckaroo Banzai and his part-time rockstar ways.  Having a chance to act
that out during some fun times at JavaOne, GoTo, and DevNexus was the
fulfillment of a career dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;netscape-6-and-oji&quot;&gt;Netscape 6 and OJI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the heady days of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://edition.cnn.com/TECH/computing/9811/24/aolnetjava.idg/index.html?_s=PM:TECH&quot;&gt;Sun-Netscape-AOL
Alliance&lt;/a&gt;,
I was part of a small group of people from Sun that went into the client
side of that deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;AOL and Sun together will develop the next version of Netscape’s
Navigator and Communicator software clients and AOL will use Java in
its e-commerce offerings, the company said.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gave me a first hand look at the birth of JavaScript and the
management decisions around Java in the browser that eventually lead to
the rise and fall of Applet, JavaFX, and even Java on the desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-opportunities&quot;&gt;Creating Opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I’m very thankful to work on technologies that create
opportunities for others to create things.  Those of us who work on
programming platforms can honestly say that we allow individuals and
entrepeneurs to create their own businesses (often employing many
people, sometimes paying a very good wage) that create solutions for
&lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; customers.  This position in at a lower-level of the value chain
is a great place to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oracle was and is a great place to work, and they have trusted me to
contribute in the above areas and several others.  In return, I have
deep trust in my management chain at Oracle.  I have nothing but good
things to say about working there.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s still unreal to me that I’m writing this, but here it is. After over 22 years at Oracle (13 at Sun), I’m moving on to another company. In my time at Oracle, I have had a chance to help shape technologies that have had a positive impact on our industry and lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TDC 2019 Florianópolis: Raw Notes: Serverless with Knative: Mete Atamel</title><link href="/blog/2019/04/25/tdc-floripa-knative.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TDC 2019 Florianópolis: Raw Notes: Serverless with Knative: Mete Atamel" /><published>2019-04-25T09:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-25T09:45:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/04/25/tdc-floripa-knative</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/04/25/tdc-floripa-knative.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/tdc-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; title=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/meteatamel&quot;&gt;Mete Atamel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/meteatamel/knative-tutorial&quot;&gt;his
tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pronounced “kay native”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;K8s open source building blocks for serverless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points out that K8s is all about servers.  But Knative hides that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Serverless?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Servers are someone else’s problem&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Functions should be idomatic, meaning already familiar to you&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Event driven&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Portable to other clouds&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asserts Knative ticks all these boxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gave-a-bit-of-kubernetes-background&quot;&gt;Gave a bit of Kubernetes Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How K8s uses a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Service&lt;/code&gt; with a stable IP…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers want serverless.  Operators want Kubernetes.  Knative tries
to bridge the gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knative is open source &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/knative&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;picture-high-level-diagram&quot;&gt;Picture: high level Diagram&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190425-tdc-floripa-knative-01-stack.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Knative Stack&quot; title=&quot;Knative Stack&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uses Istio for network, but he feels Istio is too heavyweight for what
they use it for, so they now use Gloo, but even he did not know what
that is.  (This space is moving so fast).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-install&quot;&gt;How to install&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud Run or Cloud Run on GKE or Knative Everywhere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bunch of steps at the command line, mostly with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kubectl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The different parts of knative run in different namespaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-part-is-knative-serving&quot;&gt;One part is Knative Serving?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid deployment of serverless containers.  Automatic scaling, traffic
routing, including directing per revisions.  I guess this means it
supports canary, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;picture-serving-primitives&quot;&gt;Picture: Serving Primitives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/20190425-tdc-floripa-knative-02-serving-primitives.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Knative Serving Primitives&quot; title=&quot;Knative Serving Primitives&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;going-through-steps-in-tutorial&quot;&gt;Going through steps in tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we’ve even seen any functions, we have a ton of network stuff to
do.  I would like to see the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt; for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;helloworld-csharp&lt;/code&gt; C#
Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I worked with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Fn&lt;/code&gt;, but Knative seems to have a
lot more friction.  For example, the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Fn&lt;/code&gt; command line tool builds the
docker container around your function for you.  Here you appear to have
to do that yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He used the term “traffic splitting” instead of “blue green” or some
other term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t understand whey he is doing a bunch of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kubectl apply&lt;/code&gt; to set it
up instead of them having Helm chart(s) for this.  I can understand
using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; for quick updates when the service is already deployed and
you want to update it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He didn’t mention anything about the overhead, if any, of C# in a
serverless environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Showed how &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;annotations&lt;/code&gt; are used to convey autoscaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fun-show-integration-with-twilio&quot;&gt;Fun: Show integration with Twilio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learned that you can put a comma separated list as the argument to
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kubectl get&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;knative-eventing&quot;&gt;Knative Eventing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connect producers to consumers with stuff in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example 1 was not interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example 2: Integrate Cloud Storage to Vision API&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here comes something like the license plate demo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of his examples are in C#.  Is that the only language supported?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;knative-build&quot;&gt;Knative Build&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enables you to build and push the images &lt;em&gt;within your K8s cluster&lt;/em&gt;.
This is a novel idea.  I talked to &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/yanaga&quot;&gt;Edson
Yanaga&lt;/a&gt; last night, he was saying this is the
thing that makes Jenkins obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RedHat has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.openshift.com/knative-building-your-serverless-service/&quot;&gt;tutorial on this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TDC 2019 Florianópolis: Career Tips from Someone Who Knows a lot of Rockstar Programmers 02: Timesheets</title><link href="/blog/2019/04/23/tdc-floripa-career-tips-from-someone-who-knows-a-lot-of-rockstar-programmers-2019-02.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TDC 2019 Florianópolis: Career Tips from Someone Who Knows a lot of Rockstar Programmers 02: Timesheets" /><published>2019-04-23T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-23T08:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/04/23/tdc-floripa-career-tips-from-someone-who-knows-a-lot-of-rockstar-programmers-2019-02</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/04/23/tdc-floripa-career-tips-from-someone-who-knows-a-lot-of-rockstar-programmers-2019-02.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/tdc-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; title=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my talk at 14:10 South Center Career Track, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedevelopersconference.com.br/tdc/2019/florianopolis/trilha-carreiras-e-mentoria&quot;&gt;Career Tips from Someone
Who Knows a Lot of Rockstar
Programmers&lt;/a&gt;,
I will share some of the lessons I learned from the people I interviewed
for the &lt;a href=&quot;/&quot;&gt;Secrets of the Rockstar Programmers&lt;/a&gt; book, and
also include some tips of my own.  Though I don’t claim to be a rockstar
programmer myself (or the newer term: “10x programmer”), I can honestly
say I know plenty of people that who are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been extremely blessed to have been a full time telecommuter
since 2002, first for Sun, and now for Oracle.  Working in this way
presents some unique challenges, and over the years I have developed
some techniques to maintain productivity and forward career momentum,
preserving the personal benefits of telecommuting while continuing to
give the company value for their money.  Perhaps I can do another post
on the broader topic of telecommuting tips, but this post is about one
practical technique that applies to telecommuters and office workers
alike: keeping a personal timesheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the basic idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a spreadsheet that is set up as a timesheet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each time a new month comes around, save the previous month as the
current month.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep track of all of the time you spend working and a couple words
about what you did.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing this since I started telecommuting in 2002, so I have
seventeen years of monthly spreadsheets.  Here is a sample spreadsheet you can download and customize: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/201904-timesheet.xlsx&quot; title=&quot;201904-timesheet.xlsx&quot;&gt;201904-timesheet.xlsx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like my previous post about status reports, this seems mundane and
annoying, but over time, it adds up to a valuable searchable resource.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UPDATED: 2019-07-01: TDC 2019 Florianópolis: Career Tips from Someone Who Knows a lot of Rockstar Programmers 01: Communicating Your Value Add</title><link href="/blog/2019/04/21/tdc-floripa-career-tips-from-someone-who-knows-a-lot-of-rockstar-programmers.2019.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UPDATED: 2019-07-01: TDC 2019 Florianópolis: Career Tips from Someone Who Knows a lot of Rockstar Programmers 01: Communicating Your Value Add" /><published>2019-04-21T18:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-21T18:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/04/21/tdc-floripa-career-tips-from-someone-who-knows-a-lot-of-rockstar-programmers.2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/04/21/tdc-floripa-career-tips-from-someone-who-knows-a-lot-of-rockstar-programmers.2019.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/tdc-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; title=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my talk at 14:10 South Center Career Track, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedevelopersconference.com.br/tdc/2019/florianopolis/trilha-carreiras-e-mentoria&quot;&gt;Career Tips from Someone
Who Knows a Lot of Rockstar
Programmers&lt;/a&gt;,
I will share some of the lessons I learned from the people I interviewed
for the &lt;a href=&quot;/&quot;&gt;Secrets of the Rockstar Programmers&lt;/a&gt; book, and
also include some tips of my own.  Though I don’t claim to be a rockstar
programmer myself (or the newer term: “10x programmer”), I can honestly
say I know plenty of people that who are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for big companies such as IBM, SGI, Sun, and Oracle, I’ve had
the chance to sample many useful corporate trainings.  Even the most
mundane of these, such as “Insider Trading”, offer at least one nugget
of novelty.  The corporate training I want to talk about here is one I
took at Sun at least twelve years ago.  It was called “Communicating
Your Value Add” and it was all about how to articulate your contribution
to your company at performance review time.  The class included a handout,
“Behavior/Performance-Based Questions” whose complete text I reproduce
below.  For discussion and reference, let’s call this &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;perf_handout&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the basic idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get in the habit of producing written weekly status reports as simple
text files.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Annnotate some of the things you’ve done with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;perf_handout.N&lt;/code&gt; Where
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; is the number of the corresponding list item below.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When performance review time comes around, you can grep through your
status reports for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;perf_handout&lt;/code&gt; and your performance review
practically writes itself.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if I successfully introduced a new code review process, my
weekly status report would have a line like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;perf_handout.6: Designed and implemented a new code review process.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you do this for a month or so, you’ll notice some areas you are
missing.  Try to fill those in, or if you can’t try to partner with
someone who you observe is able to do those things and learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here now is the complete &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;perf_handout&lt;/code&gt; content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;behaviorperformance-based-questions&quot;&gt;Behavior/Performance-Based Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;   A sampling of the types of questions that might be used to explore
   your level of accomplishment for specific skills are listed below.
   These questions provide a platform for *communcating your
   achievements* in skill areas such as leadership, decision-making,
   persuasiveness, coping, creativity, tolerance for ambiguity,
   organizational savvy, technical knowledge, and influencing.
   
   1. Describe a time when voicing your opinion was uncomfortable or
   could have had serious consequences, but you did it because you
   believed so strongly in the value of your perspective.
   
   2. What was the most creative idea you introduced on the job?  How
   did you persuade your superior?.
   
   3. Give me an example of the most complex project/assignment you have
   had, including your role and the outcome.
   
   4. Describe a situation at work when you had to make a decision and
   were uncertain about the outcome.
   
   5. What do you when you are communicating with someone and it becomes
   apparent that they don't understand what you are saying or vice
   versa?
   
   6. Describe a situation in which you developed a group into a strong
   working team?
   
   7. Communication and leadership go hand in hand.  Tell me about a
   time when your communication skills enabled you to influence the way
   others thought or acted, even in a very difficult situation.
   
   8. What important goals have you set in the past, and how were you
   able to work towards accomplishing them successfully?
   
   9. Describe how you delegate responsibility in your current job.
   
   10. Have you ever had to take over a leadership role unexpectedly?
   How did it work out?
   
   11. Sometimes it is important to disagree with others, particularly
   your boss, in order to prevent a mistake from being made.  Tell me
   about a time when you were willing to disagree with another person in
   order to build a positive outcome.
   
   12. Describe a time when you had to sell an idea to your boss or
   another authority figure.
   
   13. Give me an example taken from your experiences in report writing,
   preparation of memos, or general correspondence which illustrates
   the extent of your written communication skills.
   
   14. Building rapport can be a very challenging thing to do.  Give an
   example of a time when you were able to build rapport with an
   individual or group at work, even when the situation was difficult
   and the odds were against you.
   
   15. Solving problems requires more than good plans, it means taking
   action.  Give me an example of a time when you were able to take
   meaningful action in resolving a problem.
   
   16. In many problem situations, it is often tempting to jump to a
   conclusion to build a solution quickly.  Tell me about at time when
   you resisted this temptation and obtained all the facts about the
   problem before coming to a decision.
   
   17. Sometimes it is necessary to work in unsettled or rapidly
   changing circumstances.  When have you found yourself in this
   position?  Tell me exactly whay you did.
   
   18. Solving a problem often necessitates evalutation of alternative
   solutions. Give me an example of a time when you actively defined
   several solutions to a single problem using any tools such as
   research, brainstorming, or mathematics.
   
   19. Just about anybody can give a routine, standard answer to common
   problems; however, the payoff is often in the development of unique
   solutions to common problems.  Give me an example of one of your
   unique problem solutions.
   
   20. Describe an assigmnent that represented a unique challenge to
   you.
   
   21. Tell me about a time when you had to cope with strict deadlines
   or time demands.
   
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;performance-review-questions&quot;&gt;Performance Review Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-discussion forms include the questions below which are listed
   under the following categories: Results, Quality, Reliability,
   Leadership, Decision Making, Functional/Technical Skills &amp;amp; Knowledge,
   Communication and Teamwork, and Resourcefulness &amp;amp; Creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
   22. Based on established goals and objectives, for our group, what
   results did you achieve?  If a goal changed, how much progress did
   you make toward the revised goal?
   
   23. What additional contributions did you make?  Were there
   accoplishments that were definitely outstanding?
   
   24. What examples can you recall of instances in which you were
   responsive to your customer or successful in completing a quality
   job?
   
   25. What leadership and decision making abilities have you
   demonstrated?
   
   26. Give me an example of a major decision you've made and the
   outcome.
   
   27. Give me an example of any project you have led and the outcome.
   
   28. How have you improved existing processes and procedures?
   
   29. In what ways have you added unique value to your job?
   
   30. Give me an example of when you have demonstrated technical or
   functional expertise.
   
   31. Tell me about what measures you have taken to ensure that your
   skills are state-of-the-art.
   
   32. Give me an example of an effective presentation you have made.
   
   33. Give me an example of how cooperative interaction with other
   members of the Sun team have been a part of your work.
   
   34. Give me an example of a time when others have been able to count
   on your &quot;being-there&quot; time after time, project after project.
   
   35. Give me an example of when you used strategic thinking in moving
   toward achieving a goal.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-2019-07-01-microsoft-perf-handout&quot;&gt;UPDATE: 2019-07-01 Microsoft Perf Handout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some additional similar questions that I see at Microsoft:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adaptability&quot;&gt;Adaptability&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;36. Tell me about a time when you experienced a major organizational
change (for example, a reorganization, a new supervisor or a new
procedure) that created stress.

37. Describe a time when you proposed a major change in your work
process or job duties. How did others respond to your proposal?

38. Describe a time when you had to complete a project in which you were
provided with very little information or guidance.

39. Tell me about a time when you had to change your priorities in
response to the demands of a changing situation. 

40. Tell me about a time when a project, product, or service
implementation did not go according to plan. 

41. Describe a time when you presented a proposal or provided a service
that was given an unfavorable response by stakeholders. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;collaboration&quot;&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;42. Describe a time when you worked on a challenging cross-functional
team that produced an exceptional deliverable. 

43. Tell me about a time when you developed a relationship with another
area of the company that had no previous history of collaboration. 

44. Describe how you have collaborated with others outside of your
immediate team to resolve a critical issue. 

45. Tell me about a time when you experienced conflict with a team
member. 

46. Describe your most recent experience working with a virtual
team. What were the challenges you faced and how did you work through
them? 

47. Tell me about a time when your attempt to collaborate across teams
was unsuccessful. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;customer-focus&quot;&gt;Customer Focus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;48. Describe a time when you were involved in the resolution of a
complaint from either an internal or an external customer. 

49. Describe a time when you provided outstanding service to an internal
or external customer by anticipating their needs. 

50. Describe a time when you had difficulty determining the needs of a
customer to provide them with a product or service that met their
expectations. 

51. Tell me about a time when you fell short of meeting a customer's
needs. 

52. Describe the strategies you have used to gather information that
increased your understanding of current and future customer needs. 

53. Provide an example of a time when you initiated a change in a
process or policy to improve the quality of customer service 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;drive-for-results&quot;&gt;Drive for Results&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;54. Describe a time when you uncovered something that could be
problematic for your organization or team. How did you correct the
situation before it became an issue? 

55. Describe a time when you tried to achieve a difficult professional
goal. What obstacles did you encounter that made the goal difficult? 

56. Tell me about a time when you successfully removed an obstacle that
interfered with your ability to complete a task effectively. 

57. Describe a long-term project or assignment of which you took
ownership. How did you make sure each milestone was achieved in a timely
manner? 

58. Provide an example of a time when you had to motivate others to
complete a challenging deliverable. 

59. What has been the most difficult assignment or task in your career
so far? 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;influencing-for-impact&quot;&gt;Influencing for Impact&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;60. Tell me about the most challenging situation that you have
experienced, when you had to persuade someone to accept your
point-of-view. 

61. Describe a time when you had to persuade someone to complete a task,
but had no formal authority over their work. 

62. Tell me about a time when you had to convince others to implement a
new procedure or process. 

63. Tell me about a time when you successfully influenced multiple
stakeholders with varying agendas. 

64. Give me an example of a relationship that you developed through
networking that had a positive impact on your work. 

65. Give an example of a successful method (for example, research
findings, anecdotes, stories, metaphors, or analogies) that you have
used to convince a stakeholder to support an idea. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;judgement&quot;&gt;Judgement&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;66. Describe a time when you made a critical error in your work. 

67. Describe a situation when you had to make a major decision under
time constraints. 

68. Tell me about an unpopular decision you've had to make. 

69. Tell me about a time when you had to make an important decision but
had no policies or procedures in place to support it 

70. Tell me about a situation when you had multiple alternatives from
which to choose. What steps did you take to determine the most
appropriate alternative? 

71. Tell me about a situation that required you to build your knowledge
base before solving a complex problem. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;end-to-end-innovation&quot;&gt;End-to-End Innovation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;71.  Give an example of an idea that you suggested that led to
improvements within your organization. 

72. Tell me about a time when you presented a new idea that successfully
addressed a customer’s end-to-end product experience. 

73. Tell me about a time when you identified a risk and offered a unique
method of addressing the risk. 

74. Tell me about a time when you contributed to the development of an
innovative idea that impacted the market, industry, and ecosystem. 

75. Tell me about a time when an innovative product or service you
worked on failed. Looking back, what would you have done differently to
ensure success? 

76. Tell me about a time when you had to make adjustments to a feature
or product, based on considerations of the overall customer experience. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;planning-organizing-and-executing&quot;&gt;Planning, Organizing, and Executing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;77.Describe a situation when you made progress on a project or
assignment despite ambiguity. 

78. Describe a situation when you managed the impact of a change on
schedule, processes, and project goals. 

79. Describe a situation when you led a project with a geographically or
functionally diverse team. 

80. Tell me about a time when you aligned multiple stakeholders to
achieve an objective. 

81. Tell me about a time when you did not meet a planned milestone. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;technical-excellence&quot;&gt;Technical Excellence&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;82. Describe a situation when you came up-to-speed quickly on new tools,
methods, or processes. 

83. Describe a situation when you were able to create improvements in
code, designs, content property, or media assets. 

85. Describe a situation when you sought out a new engineering or
project/program management challenge beyond your role requirements. 

85. Tell me about a time when you sought out a challenging technical
problem. 

86. Tell me about a time when you mentored others in your area of
technical expertise. 

87. Tell me about a time when you had to learn a new technology. What
did you do to gain expertise? 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TDC 2019 Florianópolis</title><link href="/blog/2019/04/20/tdc-floripa-2019.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TDC 2019 Florianópolis" /><published>2019-04-20T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-20T14:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/04/20/tdc-floripa-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/04/20/tdc-floripa-2019.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/tdc-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; title=&quot;I'm speaking at TDC 2019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am blessed to have the opportunity to speak for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://purl.oclc.org/NET/edburns/speaking-engagements/&quot;&gt;fourth
time&lt;/a&gt; at the
GlobalCode Developer’s conference.  My last time there was in November
2009!  I can’t believe it’s been that long.  It was a huge event then,
and it’s even bigger now.  It’s the largest software developer
conference, by number of attendees, in Brazil, and that’s saying a lot.
There are at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedevelopersconference.com.br/tdc/2019/florianopolis/trilhas&quot;&gt;least &lt;strong&gt;49&lt;/strong&gt;
tracks&lt;/a&gt;
over &lt;strong&gt;five days&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some links to my two talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10:10 STADIUM and Java Architecture Track &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedevelopersconference.com.br/tdc/2019/florianopolis/trilha-arquitetura-java&quot;&gt;Table Stakes, Deal Makes: Programming Language Platform Growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;14:10 South Center Career Track &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedevelopersconference.com.br/tdc/2019/florianopolis/trilha-carreiras-e-mentoria&quot;&gt;Career Tips from Someone Who Knows a Lot of Rockstar Programmers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raw Notes: Revisiting Effective Java in 2019</title><link href="/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-effective-java-picks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raw Notes: Revisiting Effective Java in 2019" /><published>2019-03-19T13:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-19T13:45:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-effective-java-picks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-effective-java-picks.html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Credentials&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://developers.redhat.com/promotions/migrating-to-microservice-databases&quot;&gt;Plugged his book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ANZXvXVa1Lg&quot;&gt;Has a three hour version of the talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lambdas&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Streams&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optionals&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default methods in interfaces&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;try with resources&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;factory methods&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimize mutability&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comparable(14)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Live coding&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Minimize mutability.  Value object class.  Why?  Easier to reason
about.  Reduces the chance that the system gets into an
inconsistent state.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Make as many of things &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;final&lt;/code&gt; as possible&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;No ctor, use factory method: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;of&lt;/code&gt;.  Easier for refactoring.
Allows you to change the cardinality, maybe re-use objects with
an object pool.  Flyweight class.  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;BigDecimal.valueOf()&lt;/code&gt;
implementation is an example.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;COMMENT: what about making the zero arg ctor private?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;He used Google Guava, but noted that they have violated backward
compatibility in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Advised to implement &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;equals&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hashCode&lt;/code&gt;. Use the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Objects&lt;/code&gt;
class in the JDK.  I thas an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;equals&lt;/code&gt; method.  Handles all that
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; checking.  But beware of the performance penalty of
autoboxing.  For hashcode, there is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Objects.hash&lt;/code&gt;.  This is
even worse for performance.  If you use the generator for
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;equals&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hashcode&lt;/code&gt; make sure to keep the impls up to date
as the class evolved.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;for hashcode, because it is immutable, you can do it in the
ctor. If you use an object as a key to a hashmap, it must be
immutable.  If you can’t do that, you can make a
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;toHashKey()&lt;/code&gt; method.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;toString()&lt;/code&gt;.  It’s for developers.  Guava
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MoreObjects.toStringHelper()&lt;/code&gt;.  Not for “business strings”.
For busness strings, use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;formatTo&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Formatter&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Formattable&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt;.  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Comparator&lt;/code&gt; interface.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Functional Interfaces.  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@FunctionalInterface&lt;/code&gt;.  Constrains your
code to conform to functional interfaces.  Favor &lt;em&gt;Strategy&lt;/em&gt; over
&lt;em&gt;Template Method&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;You should not need to create a new functional interface.  There
are 41 already in the JDK.  It’s likely it will be in there
already.  Learn these six well: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;UnaryOperator, BinaryOperator,
Predicate, Function, Supplier, Consumer&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Method References.  Five different types&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;static, ie &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Integer::parseInt()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;bounded and unbounded method reference.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Enums&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Can use lambdas or function references in enum initializer.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Credentials</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raw Notes: Das Geheimnis erfolgreicher Teams</title><link href="/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-successful-teams-picks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raw Notes: Das Geheimnis erfolgreicher Teams" /><published>2019-03-19T08:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-19T08:45:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-successful-teams-picks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-successful-teams-picks.html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Successful teams come from successful people&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jobs, Musk, Zuck&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What makes the diffence between successful teams and normal teams.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Google Project Aristotle researched this.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Team A: very structured&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Team B: very loose&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Google found it does not matter.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Google found teams that talk a lot are successful.  “Psychological Safety”&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Clear structure&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Same mindset&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Supported by the larger org.&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;COmpeling direction&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Supportive context&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;SHared mindest&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Have a vision: 2 year plan.  Within that, have “themes” to say
what’s important.  Within that Focus areas, for example, “we’re
going to build a mobile app”.  Helps people orgaize around.  Within
that, all of it has to be measured.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;V T F M&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vision&quot;&gt;Vision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Objective Key Results (OKR)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Objective (not as in vs Subjective, rather as in goal).  It’s an
agile story.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Key results (1000 dailt user)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Score 0.7 (700 users)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stretch goals.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audit quarterly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not too many objectives, with two or three key results.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make goals transparent for everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strong-structure&quot;&gt;Strong Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a common language.  Analogy, making a film, but the actors,
lighting, sound, all sit in different room.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cross functional teams&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Help the developers understand why a particular design was chosen&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Faster + Stronger decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Develop strong teams&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;FIKA drink coffee together, exchange ideas, allow things to be
shared outside of the stress of the regular grind.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Conference Video Fridays&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Team refreshments&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Getting stuff done days.  Work on docs.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Innovation weeks, every six weeks hackathon.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Small things, say thanks, give compliments.  Kudos system.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Welcoming culture for onboarding.  Handholding the new members.
Have a budy system.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trello, acquired by Atlassian,  Showed video.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;supportive-context&quot;&gt;Supportive Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowledge sharing&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;documents, 1:1s, meetings, email: closed systems&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;better: Intranet, Chat,&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Your team space&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Company information&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Pesonal spaces&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Open by default, but of course can be closed.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep decision log, but allow corrections, allow marking obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make services discoverable, but as much as possible self-service.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shared-mindset&quot;&gt;Shared Mindset&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bug fix rotation, helps share the mindset&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Feature creation rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Get a feature buddy.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doing-things-right&quot;&gt;Doing things right&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Process is good for that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it is also important to do the right things.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognize that teams can be very structured or very chaotic.
Create a team playbook.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Looks like design patterns for team activities&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Demo Trust&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Concept Testing&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;(Team) Health Monitor&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;One Fulltime Team Owner&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Balanced Team&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Values and Metrics&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Velocity&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;End-to-end Demo&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.atlassianteamplaybook.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.atlassianteamplaybook.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;right-people--right-tools--right-practices--great-team&quot;&gt;Right people + Right tools + right practices = great team&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Successful teams come from successful people</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raw Notes: Visual Studio Code</title><link href="/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-vscode-picks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raw Notes: Visual Studio Code" /><published>2019-03-19T08:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-19T08:45:00-04:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-vscode-picks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/03/19/javaland-vscode-picks.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;vscode&quot;&gt;VSCode&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Started by saying their goal is not to convert IntelliJ, Eclipse,
NetBeans devs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Editors&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;TextEdit&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;SublimeText&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;jEdit&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Had huge plugin ecosystem.  From sourceforge&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom Editor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum you have IDEs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Text editors&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Keyboard centric&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Lightweight/fast&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Files/folders&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IDEs&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Project systems&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Integrated build&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Debug&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;VCS&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Code understandig&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What about something in the middle?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;VS Code is an editor, but has some capabilities from the IDS&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Code understanding&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Debug&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Everything from the Text editors&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to stick to one editor, VSCode + extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spring Initializr&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IntelliCode&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AI-assited pattern recognition&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demos&quot;&gt;DEMOS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting it up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;code --user-dir empty --extensions-dir empty/extensions
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some basic things you can do&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Maven projects&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Had some demo issues&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;spring&quot;&gt;Spring&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demos-1&quot;&gt;DEMOS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SpringBoot &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@RestController&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initializr&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Go-to-symbol works with Spring beans&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;PetClinic&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AzureDevSpaces&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Rapidly iterate and debug containers in Kubernetes&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Showed how you can drop in a new Service-B in the midst of other
existing services.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/vs-code-blog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jakarta EE TImeline&quot; title=&quot;Timeline&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">VSCode</summary></entry></feed>